We're going to be jumping into plug in development now.
One thing I need to stress is that everything you can do in plug ins can be done in themes and vice
versa.
A lot of the functions we use and themes can be used in plug ins.
This also applies to hooks and even templates.
The reason we're switching to plug ins is because we'll be extending the functionality of WordPress.
Unlike our theme, we just modified WordPress for design reasons now will be making changes that go
beyond design.
You are more than free and allowed to just keep working in your theme, but I highly don't recommend
it.
As you can tell, I like to keep everything separate and organized.
This also applies to plug ins and themes.
Code that extends WordPress should be put in a plug in, while themes should be for design.
It's perfectly fine to bundle your custom plug ins with your theme.
I will show you how to do that when we reach the end of this course.
The plug in I have in mind will allow users to create recipes and submit them.
We will also be creating a user registration and login form as well as managing the recipes, this blog,
and it will be very advanced and as the course progresses, we'll be switching between our theme and
plug.
I want to warn you, though, we will begin to discuss more advanced concepts.
A lot of what we've done so far has been taken care of by WordPress.
We haven't written a single database query, nor did we really have to create our own functions to handle
advanced logic or sanitize data.
This is the part of the course where we will start digging into the core of WordPress and learn how
it works.
I hope you're ready.
Oh.