Creating a plugin is very similar to creating a theme, all plug ins can be found inside the WP dash
content slash plugins folder.
By default, WordPress will provide us with two plug ins, which are the Hello Dolly and a Kismet plug
ins.
We also see the plug ins we installed earlier.
Let's create our own plug in.
Unlike themes, plug ins can be created directly inside the plugins folder or in a subfolder.
However, it's best practice to just create a subfolder with any plugging the plug and I want to create
is going to be called recipe.
I'm going to create a new folder named Recipe.
Inside this folder, I'm going to create a new file named Indexed.
Just like theme's, you need to provide a file header to tell WordPress that this plugin exists.
Unlike Theme's, though, WordPress doesn't require a certain naming structure for plugins.
Actually, if we take a look at the figure press plugin, then you'll see that all code is in the Fakher
Press file and not the indexed file.
You can name the main plug and file whatever you want.
Some developers name it after they're plugins, others just use indexed.
Either one is fine.
I just wanted you to be aware of the two common possibilities.
It's all preference for this course.
We're going to just keep everything inside the index top file.
There's only one requirement to make this an official WordPress plugin.
We must create a file header and find one property.
So let's create a blog comment.
And inside this blog comments add the following plugin name Colen Recipe.
That's it, go to your plug ins page and you should now see your plug in appear.
It doesn't have the rest of the information like the other plug ins, but it works.
This is the absolute minimum requirement for WordPress to recognize your plug.
Nothing else.
In the resources section, I provide a link to the file header Codex page.
WordPress provides a full list of optional headers we can define.
We're going to use a few of these.
Let's get started.
The second header we want to define is the description.
I'm going to put a simple WordPress plugin that allows users to create recipes and rate those recipes.
Up next is the version we'll keep it simple by sending it to 1.0.
Next is the name of the author, put your name down or the name of your organization.
I'm going to put down Udemy, the author, Urai is a link to your personal site or organization site.
I'm going to drop a link to the Udemy site.
Lastly, we want to define the text domain, I know we haven't gone over translations yet, but this
should always be set to the name of your plugin folder.
So set this to recipe.
Let's refresh the plugin page and see if everything works, you should see something similar to what
I see.
Feel free to look at the other headers and define whatever suits your needs.