You can have multiple functions attached to the same hook, it's perfectly normal for several plug ins
to use the same hook.
Let's look at how you would prioritize hooks, open the hooks example, plug in we created previously.
I'm going to copy and paste the WP footer hook and its function.
Then I'm going to change the functioning, I'm going to add underscore V two, I'm also going to change
the text and add version two for formatting reasons.
I'm going to add brake tags to both these functions.
Before you refresh the page, which text do you think will appear first, let's find out, refresh the
page and you'll notice that the first version displays first and version two displays.
Second, if I were to move the second function above the first, then the text positions will switch.
I'm going to refresh the page again, as you can see here, the version to text is appearing first.
By default, WordPress will run functions as first come, first serve.
You can completely override this by using the third parameter, which determines the priority of the
function.
I'm going to switch back these functions and I will use the third parameter of the add action function.
These parameters value must be an integer which determines the priority.
The lower the number, the higher their priority and vice versa.
By default, all functions get the priority of ten.
I want this function to run first.
I'll set it to something like five.
Let's refresh the page and you will now see the version two text appearing first.
Just like that, you can determine the order of your functions by setting the priority.
Even if you're not repeating the same hook.
Setting a priority can be helpful if other plugins are also using the same hook.
If you feel that your plug in deserves to run first, then you should set the priority to a low number.
Now that we understand how the priority works, let's see how plugins initiate these hooks in the resource
section.
I provide a link to the function WP footer.
If you scroll down to the source section, you'll see that all this function does is call a function
called do action.
This function will trigger all hooks related to the string passed in.
In this case, the WP Footer Action Hook is started.
This is how all action hooks are started.
It really is this simple to reiterate.
First of all, hooks need to be registered to register a hook.
You need to use the function, add action.
The hook you want to register is defined in the first parameter.
Keep in mind that WordPress will accept in any name.
If I were to pass in FUX, then WordPress will perfectly accept this.
It's very important to register Hooke's when you're plug in.
MPM is initiated.
After all, hooks are registered, WordPress will run its course and when it's time to run all hooks,
it will use the function do action followed by the name of the hook it would like to run.
WordPress uses this function throughout its core and cause multiple hooks.
This is why we never have to worry about running them to view a list of hooks.
You can find those in the resource section of this lecture.
There are two kinds of hooks which are action hooks and filter hooks.
I also provide a link to what WordPress calls the plugins API.
Here you can find a list of functions that makes hooks all possible.
Of course, you're not limited to the WordPress hooks.
You can even create your own hooks.
Let's explore how that works inside the plugin file.
Create a new action hook for the footer and call the function JHU footer.
I will define the function right afterwards.
I'm going to comment about our previous coat next, create a second function called Jiyu Kill WPE.
This function will never run unless we call it however I want to call it with a custom hook inside the
footer function.
I'm going to call the do action function.
The hook I want to run will be called Jiyu custom footer.
This is a completely custom hook that I just created.
There isn't anything else that I need to do now, any plug ins and things can hook into this event and
run their own functions.
I want to run my function.
J You killed up to do this.
I'm going to use the function, add action, and for the first parameter, I'm going to pass in our
custom hook called G.U. custom footer.
The second parameter is the Jiyu kill WPE function inside the J, you kill WPE function.
I'm going to echo out some text.
Just like that, we created a custom hook and can now run it, let's refresh the page and we should
now see our message being outputted.
Let me break down what's going on when WordPress is initialised, it will load all the plugins at this
point, the template nor the content is loaded.
Our hooks example, plug in will register its hooks.
Eventually, WordPress will begin loading the template, the template, we'll call it the WP footer
function.
As we saw earlier, the WP footer function.
We'll call it the do action function, which will trigger the WP footer event in the code we call the
do action function.
We can then trigger our own custom event.
In this case, the custom event would be Jiyu custom footer from here.
Any functions that are registered to this event will start to run in our code.
We hook into this event and the function that will end up running is the Jiyu Kill WPE function.
This function runs and outputs the text.
That's it.
This also works for filters.
However, the function for running a filter is called apply filters.
There are a couple of other functions, but we won't be going over them as they aren't used as much.
Now that you understand how the plugins API works, it's time to get started with plugin development.
If you feel a little lost, that's OK.
We'll be using the plugins API plenty once again.
Despite its name, the plugins API can also be used in theme's.
It's not exclusive to plugins.