If you've activated the recipe, plug in, then that's fine, but you'll need to deactivate it for now
and this lecture will be doing some plug activation settings and add some plug in security.
As developers, we have to do everything in our power to secure our plug ins.
Of course, we can't account for every hack there is throughout this course.
I'll be sure to advise you what you can do to secure your plug in.
One course of action we can take to secure this plug in is preventing users from calling this plug in
directly.
It's common for hackers to try to visit the file directly instead of letting WordPress load it.
So how do we prevent this?
Well, it's actually quite simple.
Open up the recipe, plug and file at the very top at a conditional statement.
This conditional statement, we'll check to see if a function exists, WordPress loads its own files
and constants before loading plugins so that they're available to us.
The function we want to check exists is called add action.
If this function doesn't exist, then we know for sure that WordPress isn't loaded and therefore we
don't want to run the rest of this script inside this conditional statement.
We're simply going to echo out a message.
Hi there.
I'm just a plug in.
Not much I can do when called directly and then exit out of here.
This way of doing it is common amongst plugins.
Actually, I took this from the plug in a kismet.
This is a plug in Prepackage with most WordPress installations.
Let's take a look.
If we open the Kismet folder and view the Kismet file, you'll find that this is implemented in the
same style and fashion as the recipe plug.
This isn't completely foolproof, but this should stop some of the most basic attacks out there.
Let's begin working on the plug activation now inside the main plugin file.
Let's add some sections first.
Here are the four sections that will make setup includes hooks and short codes.
Under the hooks section, we're going to call a function called Register Activation Hook.
This function is a special kind of hook made specifically for plugins, this function will be called
when our plug in is activated.
This function has two parameters.
The first parameter is the path to our plug in.
We could use some built-In functions to get the path, but there's actually a simpler way of doing this.
The HP provides a constant named file.
This concept will always point to the file it's used in.
The second parameter is the name of the function that will execute.
We'll call this our activate plug in.
Just like last time, I'll be prefixing the variables, functions and anything else with our underscore
to prevent collisions with other plugins and themes, let's define this function now.
Create a folder called Includes, and within this folder, create a file called Activate P.
Within this file, determine the function and make sure to include it from the main plug and file.
Before we execute any code, I want to check if the current version of WordPress is compatible with
this plugin.
You can set this to any version you'd like, but I'm going to keep things simple and say that the minimum
version required is 5.0 inside the activation function.
We're going to use a conditional statement.
Inside this conditional statement, let's call the version compare function.
This is a function that will help you with comparing versions.
The reason we use this function, rather than a traditional comparison operator, is because versions
will usually have multiple decimals.
For example, WordPress currently released version five point zero point one.
This is a number that can't be compared traditionally.
So this function will help you with that.
No matter the schematic versioning you use for the first parameter I'm going to use to get blog info
function and pass in the value version.
This will return the current WordPress installation version, the second parameter is 5.0, which will
be the minimum version required.
Lastly, we'll use the less than operator.
This will basically check if the current version is less than the minimum required version.
For example, if the current version is five point eight, then it would be processed as five point
eight, less than five point zero.
This will return false, which is great because that means our plugin is compatible with the WordPress
installation.
However, if this returns true, then that means the WordPress version is really low.
If it is, then we don't want to activate this plugin.
So we'll use the WP day function and output the following message.
You must update WordPress to use this plugin.
Make this string translatable, the text domain this time will be recipe.
All right, so activate your plug in and you should be able to do so without any errors.
Now we can start developing the plug.
It will be revising this function later to create some settings.
But for now, we'll leave it as is.