We've been using various APIs, such as the metadata API to work with the database up until now by using
these APIs, we've avoided directly querying the database.
However, we're coming to the point where we can't justify using APIs for certain tasks.
We need full control over the database.
And in these next few lectures, you'll see how to do just that.
One of the benefits of using APIs is that we didn't have to create tables or insert data.
While these APIs are useful, they don't provide us with everything we need.
Sometimes you will have to create complex custom queries.
Other times you'll have to create tables.
In this lecture, we're going to create a database table.
This table will contain ratings for our recipes.
First, we're going to create it through an interface and then learn how to create it with code.
I'm using Heidi Vizquel for this.
It's a really great program for communicating with SQL databases.
If you're comfortable with my admin, then by all means, go ahead and use it.
If this is your first time using Heidi, yes, you will.
Then I'll show you how to connect to your database quickly.
For the hostname IP, it should be one two seven zero zero one.
The username should be root and the password should be empty.
The rest of the settings are just fine, as is next.
You should just click open and you should see all your databases go to the database that contains your
WordPress installation.
You should see about eleven tables.
You may see more because plug ins can and are allowed to create more database tables.
Before we create our own table, let's check out how WordPress creates tables.
Open the WP underscore posts tables.
WordPress is database design is very good.
WordPress tries its best to implement the best database practices and it shows here.
One thing you'll notice is that for their IDs is that they use the big integer type to allow for stealing
and large amounts of data.
It's always good practice to follow how WordPress designs their database.
This way you can remove any confusion if someone else takes a look at your own custom tables.
You'll also notice that every table starts with WP underscore.
This is very important to note down.
The goal right now is to create a table with Heidi Skills Help and you'll see why in a second.
To create a table, you'll have to click the database and select create new table.
From here we can begin defining the table.
I'm going to call a table WP underscore recipe, underscore ratings and it should have four columns.
I'm going to prefilled these and then go over what you should set.
Paused the video for a second and fill up the form just as I did.
We have four fields named Idy recipe ID rating and user IP.
The ID will be unique and we'll be setting it as our primary key to create a primary key.
You just right click and select create new index primary.
The type should be big int.
We use big events as this is what WordPress uses for their own ID's.
The link should be 20 with auto increment as the default.
The recipe ID will contain the idea of the post.
This will also be the type big event with a length of twenty.
The rating will contain the user rating along with their user IP.
Let's create our table now and you should receive no error so far.
Great.
The reason I had you create this table through high school is because Heidi will generate the query
for us in two locations.
If you look at the bottom, you'll notice all these SQL queries being executed.
It even has the create query.
However, it's all compressed into this one line.
There is actually a more cleaner and formatted version which is available under this create code tab.
Copy this and make sure you have it in hand.
When we create this table via code, I want to create this through our plug in and not through Hidesign.
Well, let's open the activation file and get started.
The first thing I want to do is include the global variable WP DB.
This variable contains an object with methods and properties for interacting with the database.
This object is created by WordPress for you and is already connected to the database.
I'm going to create a variable named CREATE Sequel and this will contain a string with our sequel.
Let's copy and paste the query from Heidi Eskil into this string like.
So I'm going to format this a bit by indenting some stuff just to make it look a little bit cleaner
and readable.
We need to modify this query a bit to be compatible and consistent with our database.
First is the prefix.
Not all installations of WordPress will be prefixed with WP underscore.
So I want you to remove this bit and instead we're going to appoint a dynamic prefix.
The WP DB object contains a property named prefix, and this property simply contains the prefix of
the current WordPress installation.
Next up is making the charoset dynamic, the W PDV object has a method called get care set.
Koelie, as it sounds, this will get the colation of the currently installed database.
I'm going to modify this end of the query a little bit.
We don't have to make any further modifications to our secret.
All we have to do now is execute it.
You may be thinking that there's a method in the PDB object for doing this, but there isn't.
Strangely enough, WordPress doesn't include a create table method.
Instead, we have to use a different function.
I'm going to require a file called slash.
WP admin slash includes slash upgrades.
I also appended this to a constant named ABB's path, this consent is created by WordPress and points
to the installation of our WordPress site.
We have to include this file so we can use a function called DB Delta.
This file usually isn't loaded, so we have to load it, the Delta function is used for executing queries
that modify the database and the resource section.
I provide a link to this function.
If you take a look at the source code, you'll find all this code that will assist us with creating
a database.
Here is what WordPress has to say about this function.
Useful for creating new tables and updating existing tables to a new structure.
I'm going to pass this function for our query.
That's it, we're done.
I'm going to go back to high school and I'm going to drop the newly created table.
Dropping a table is just another way of saying building it back inside WordPress, let's deactivate
our plugin and then reactivate it.
You should not get any errors.
Go back to high school and refresh the database.
You should see the recipe ratings table pop up again.
I know this can seem a bit confusing, but working with the database is actually easier than this.
Ninety five percent of the time, you won't have to worry about requiring certain files.
Creating, updating and deleting tables requires the upgrade file.
The reason this file is required is because of security reasons.
It's not normal to load function specifically made for updating, creating and deleting tables on every
page request.
If this function was loaded everywhere, then it would cause some serious security issues for Web developers
and owners.
WordPress provides a lot of methods for executing queries and takes care of sanitizing your queries
for you.
So I promise creating a query like this is a one time thing.
If you're interested in learning more about this process than I provide a link to a WordPress developer
page that provides details about this.