Will be using a plug in and called Jake Query, rate it, I provide a link to this plug in the resources
section of this lecture.
It'll create a simple rating UI that we can use in our plug in.
I already included this plug in for you when you downloaded the assets for our project.
All we have to do now is include it.
You already know how to do this, so why don't you pause this video and give it a try this plug and
it can be found inside the assets folder.
All you need to do is include the query rated DOT men that James and rated dot xxx files.
If you haven't figured it out yet, then let me show you, I'm going to use the WP and Scripps Action
Hook and I'm going to call the function R and Q scripts.
The next step is to create the file that will include our files, create a file named NQ Up that will
contain our function and include it from within the plug and file.
Keep in mind that I created a folder named Front and put the file in here, one last thing I want to
do is set the priority to a high number such as one hundred.
This here is a personal preference whenever I'm in files from within a plugin file.
I like to load my assets last.
This is because I believe theme should have a higher priority when it comes to loading JavaScript and
access files.
I've had many problems in the past where my assets had conflicting issues with the theme because the
theme files were being loaded too late.
I've saved myself many headaches by having my plug ins asset files loaded last.
Now, let's take a look at this function.
I'm simply going to register and in queue my files.
One thing I forgot to mention is that I'm also interviewing a script named Maned James.
This file can be found inside the assets logs folder.
Open this file.
It's just basic jury code, which we will be editing soon back to the NQ function.
I'm doing one last thing, which is making sure that Jake query is being loaded before our files are
loaded.
This should set everything up and we can now begin using the plug in the resource section.
I provide a link to the Ajax in Plugins Codex Page.
This page goes over how to use Ajax and plugins using Ajax on the front end requires a little work.
The first thing we need to do is prepare the data, open the recipe template file.
As you can see, the rating is placed right after the rating text.
We created this div with the class ratings.
I also gave it an ID called Recipe Underscore Rating.
We'll need this as a reference.
I also added this attribute called data dash rate it dasht reasonable and set its value to false.
This plugin will generate a button that will allow the user to reset the rating.
We don't want this by setting it to false.
This will prevent the user from resetting the rating.
All this information can be found on the documentation page of the plug in.
The last attribute I created is called Data Dash or ID.
This will contain the ID of the current post taking a close look.
You'll notice I made this into a placeholder inside the filter function.
Let's add another modification.
All you need to do is search for this placeholder and replace it with the idea of this post.
Let's test this really quick, you should see five stars and be able to rate this recipe.
This works almost perfect.
As you can see, you're able to change your rating.
We don't want this.
We want the rating to be set after the user has done so.
We'll do this inside the JavaScript main file.
I'm going to select the div by its ID and then I'm going to bind an event called Rated.
This event is called When the user rates a recipe inside the function, we can use the this object to
reference the div.
I'm going to select the div again and call the rate method.
This method allows us to change the properties, I'm going to change the Reed only property to true,
this will prevent the user from changing the rating after reading a recipe.
The next step is to create an object called form.
We're going to send this object when we make an AJAX request.
There's only one property we must define, which is the action property.
WordPress will use this to determine what function to execute when it receives an Ajax request.
You'll see exactly how this works in just a moment.
I'm going to set this to our great recipe.
Next, I'm going to create a pride property and set its value to the pride attribute.
The last property you want to define is the rating itself to grab the rating, we can use the rate it
method and pass and value.
This will return the rating.
I want to test this out now, refresh the page and try reading the recipe.
You should not be able to rate this recipe after reading it once.
The next step is to send an Ajax request with all our info so the rating can be saved.
The WordPress admin provides a variable for the Ajax URL on the front end were not so lucky.
We have to generate the URL ourselves.
It's pretty easy though.
Inside the NQ function we're going to use a function called WP Localize script.
This function is used for providing translated strings to your JavaScript files, despite this, WordPress
recommends you use this function for also providing a new URL to its Ajax page handler.
The first parameter is which file will be receiving the translations.
You or else set this to our since this is the file that we're using to send AJAX requests.
Next up is the name of the object we can use for referencing the values.
I'm going to set this to recipe obj.
The last parameter is an array of values.
We only need to create one value and that is the Ajax U URL.
You can name this whatever you want.
By the way, the value of this key will be the euro returned by the admin euro function.
This function has one optional parameter, which is the path relative to the WordPress admin, you,
Earl, I'm going to pass in admin dash Ajax Dot.
This is the path that should always handle your Ajax requests, if we take a look at our folder structure,
you can find this file inside the WP dash admin folder.
Now we can send in Ajax request using GE queries.
Post Method will send an Ajax request to the URL we generated.
Remember the recipe, LBJ is the name we used in the second parameter of the localized function, this
object will contain all our raised value.
The property we want to access is the Ajax.
You are our property.
Next, we want to send the form object and then we'll create the function that will handle the response.
The data argument is a variable that will contain the response body.
The last thing we need to do is to tell WordPress about this Ajax request so we can handle it properly
from the plugin file.
We're going to use an action hook called WP Ajax.
Let's take a look at this hook by viewing its Codex page, I provided a link to this in the resource
section of this lecture.
This book starts with Ajax, followed by the name of the action.
This was set in the form object.
The action hook should be called WP.
Underscore Ajax.
Underscore our underscore rate.
Underscore recipe.
The name of the function we want to execute is our recipe.
You can name this whatever you want.
You don't have to name it after the action, I just do it like this because it makes things easier to
manage.
All right.
Now create a file inside the process folder called Rate Dash Recipe B and define the function here.
Make sure to include it from the plugin file.
Inside the function, I'm going to output the post data.
Let's try using our rating system now, there's one problem, which is how do we know if our data is
being sent and how do we check the data?
This can be done by using chrome developer tools, press F 12 on your keyboard and you should see this
pop up.
In previous lectures, we briefly went over how the elements and console tabs work now will be discussing
how the network tab works, the network tab tracks of what files are loaded and how long it takes to
load those files.
It also provides information about the request and responses.
For the most part, I don't usually concern myself with all this information.
The best part about the section of the developer tools is that you can filter those requests.
Since a web page can make dozens of requests, I'm going to filter it by X HRR, which stands, for
example, HTTP requests.
This is where AJAX requests are being displayed.
With this being displayed, I'm going to rate the recipe.
After reading the recipe, you should see a new request being sent to admin dash AIJAC Stop.
Click on this request and you will see some data being outputted to the right.
It's categorized into five sections.
The headers tab tells us about the header information inside this tab.
It's split into more sections.
The general section provides information about the request.
In general, the response headers provides information about the server itself.
When it replied to our request, the request headers provides information about our own request.
The form data is what we want to see.
Specifically, you'll notice our data being sent so we can now confirm that our request is indeed being
sent with the data we provided.
Next, I want to check if the server is receiving this data properly under the preview or response tab
will be able to check out the service response.
We see our data being outputted with Pete.
Not only have we confirmed that our data is being sent, but the correct function is being executed
when our data is received.
Before I move on, there's one thing I want to highlight.
The difference between the preview and response tab is that the preview tab will display the response
as if the response was rendered by a browser.
So any stylings applied to the responses page will be applied to this little preview.
The response tab will show the response completely raw and or plain text.
There is one last thing I want to do before we move on to processing the rating.
Back inside the main plugin file, I'm going to copy the Ajax Hook again and paste it below.
I'm going to change Ajax to Ajax, no priv.
The difference between these two is that they know PRIV version will also process Ajax requests from
users who are not logged in.
No priv stands for no privileges.
We want our guests to be able to rate our recipes as well.
This step is optional and is up to you.
Whether you believe guests should be able to make Ajax requests, you don't have to worry about both
of these being triggered as WordPress is smart enough to tell which one to use depending on the user,
and the next lecture will begin processing the data and save it.