I'm back inside the admin side of WordPress and I'm on the recipe page right now, there's no way for
me to know how many ratings each recipe has or what the rating for each one is.
Wouldn't it be nice if I could see all the data here in this table?
At this point?
You can already guess how we would do this.
If you were thinking action hoax, then you were correct along with showing the rating count and the
actual rating.
We're also going to remove the tags column as it's kind of useless information for this post to get
started.
We're going to look into when the WordPress admin dashboard is initialized inside the main plug and
file at an action hook called admin in.
It's the name of the function will be recipe admin in it.
This function doesn't exist, so let's create it inside the includes folder, create a folder named
admin.
This is where we'll store files related to the admin site exclusively.
Then inside this folder, create a file named in it to find the function and include it from the main
plug and file.
Inside this function, I'm going to add a new filter hook called managed post type posts columns.
This hook doesn't have to be used inside the admin in it hook.
The reason we're adding it here is to keep things organized.
I could have very well put this hook inside the main plug and file, but I don't want that file to be
too cluttered with hooks.
There's also the advantage of having all the admin hooks in one file rather than mixing them together
with other hooks.
I provide a link to this and the resource section to more about this hook.
Let's take a look at the Codex page.
The Post type in the name can actually be replaced with the name of the post type where the column will
be updated.
So let's go back to the filter hook and replace this word with recipe, since that is the name of our
post type.
This filter hook will give us an array of columns already set by WordPress, we have the option of returning
a modified version of this array or a brand new array of columns.
Let's set this filter Hooke's function to our add new recipe columns.
I'm going to create a file called columns with the admin folder and define the function here.
Make sure to include it from the admin init function.
This function will be passed a column zarei, we're not going to use this, though, instead I'm going
to create an array called new columns.
The key of these arrays will be used to identify each column and the values will be the names of each
column.
This will be outputted into the header and footer of our table.
If we take a look at the Codex page, WordPress provides a list of default columns.
We can say, I'm going to use all of these except the tags and comments column.
You should have something similar to what I have.
You'll also notice that I'm making each column name translatable right after the categories column and
two more columns called Count and Rating.
When it comes to custom columns, you can name these whatever you want.
I'm going to keep it simple.
These column names will also be translatable.
The last step is return the new columns.
Since these are custom columns, it is our responsibility to output the data for each column back inside
the admin init function.
We will now add an action hook called Managed Post Type Post Custom Column.
I provided a link and the resources section for this action hook, this hook will allow us to output
info for each column.
The post type keyword should be replaced with a custom post type.
This hook will affect.
In our case, it would be recipe.
The function we want to call is our managed recipe columns.
This hook will pass our function to arguments that we'll need.
I'm going to set the priority to 10 and the accepted arguments to two, I'm going to define this function
inside the columns page file.
The two variables that will be passed in our column and posted the column variable is equal to the key
in the columns array and the ID is the idea of the current post.
I'm going to use a switch statement here.
I'm going to check the column and see if its value is equal to either count orating.
Otherwise, I'm just going to break the statement.
Don't worry about the other columns, since they are WordPress columns, WordPress will handle setting
those values.
It's our custom columns we need to worry about for both of these columns.
I'm going to grab the recipe metadata and simply echo the corresponding values for each column.
Something I want to highlight is that I'm checking if the key in the array is set for each of the respective
columns.
This is just in case the metadata isn't available.
Refresher table and you should now see our columns appear.
We only have one recipe, but we can already see the amount of ratings it's received and the average
rating.