Our plugin is almost complete.
There are just a few more things that need to be done.
The next thing on our list is to make a widget.
This widget will display a recipe of the day.
If you open the static template, you'll find a widget that displays the recipe of the day will be creating.
This will be using a few WordPress APIs to make this work.
The first API is the Widgets API.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the Widgets API.
WordPress provides some really good examples on how to implement your own widget.
We will have to use some object oriented programming to create a widget.
Don't worry, it's easy inside the main plug and file.
Let's use the action hook called widgets in it.
This book is called When Widgets Are Initialized, we will be able to register our widget with this
hook.
The function will want to call is our widgets in it.
We're going to define this function inside a file called Widgets.
We create this file inside the includes folder and include it from the main plug and file.
This book is called Very Early On, so to make sure our file is included properly, we have to prepend
the plug and directory to the inclusion.
We can accomplish this by using the name function and passing in the plug and royal constant like so.
This file will now be loaded properly.
Next, let's register the widget to register a widget, we have to call the register widget function.
This function has one required parameter, and that's the name of the class that contains our widget.
I'm going to pass in our daily recipe widget.
This class doesn't exist, let's create it now, I'm going to create a folder called Widgets inside
the Includes folder.
Next, create a file called Daily Dash Recipe and create a class called our Daily Recipe Widget.
Lastly, include this file from the main plugin file.
The code for loading the which is finished, let's focus on creating the widget now, this class has
to extend that WP widget class.
This class will help integrate our widget with WordPress, a system it'll leave us to take care of the
rest by displaying the widget and setting up the fields, go back to the Widgets API documentation page.
You'll find a default usage section.
Let's copy the code inside the class and paste it into hours.
Let's go through this one by one, the construct function is where we'll be setting up the widget.
There's only one thing we need to do, and that is called the parent constructor method.
This method has three parameters.
The first parameter is an ID for the widget.
Set this to our daily recipe widget.
The second parameter is the title of the widget.
This will be displayed on the widgets admin page and will help users identify your widget.
Let's call this widget recipe of the day.
The last parameter is an array of additional options we can set for now, we only want to set the description.
The description will be displayed on the widgets admin page.
The description should be short and concise.
Let's set this to displays a random recipe each day.
WordPress will now officially recognize the widget, the next method is called widget.
This method takes care of displaying the widget on the front end.
I'm going to skip this for now.
I promise we'll get back to it later.
Before I move on, I'm going to move this method to the very bottom.
The reason I do this is because of my workflow, I usually like to set up the widget method last.
Now, the second method, formerly the third, is form WordPress will call this method to render reform
that will allow the user to customize this widget your past in a variable named instance.
This contains the form values of the current instance of the widget.
Our widget won't be super complex.
We're only going to have one field.
And that's the title of the widget.
First, let's create some default values since there's only a title will set the default title to Recipe
of the day.
Next, we're going to set the instance variable to the value returned by the function WP Pass ARGs.
This is a utility function provided by WordPress, this method will merge to erase together and return
the merged array.
If the instance already has a title, then the default won't override that title.
Otherwise, the title will be set from the default array.
This will guarantee that will have a title set.
Whether this is a new instance or not, the widget would be considered a new instance.
If the user has dragged and dropped the widget onto a sidebar for the first time, the widget would
be considered an old instance.
If the widget is already on the sidebar, let's begin displaying the fields.
I'm going to paste in this bit of code.
Pause the video if you need to and copy what I have, let's go over what this code does.
We have a label element will set the four attribute for the value returned by the get field method.
This method will generate an ID for our field.
You simply pass in the name of the field.
We actually use this method twice.
The second time is for the ID attribute in the input field.
The next method is the get field name.
Just like the get field ID method.
This method will generate a name for our input.
You may be thinking, why is this important?
Can't we just generate our own names and IDs?
The word widget form is submitted with Ajax.
WordPress takes care of submitting the data and updating the corresponding fields since WordPress is
handling the submission and updates.
But it's required to give these fields special names rather than us having to worry about those names,
we can use these methods to do it for us.
It's recommended to let WordPress take care of generating these attributes for you, which is what these
functions do.
You'll also notice we don't create form tags because WordPress takes care of that.
To the last attribute we're seeing is the value we output the instances title.
We sanitize the value with the SC attribute function.
This function will make sure that the value can be inserted into an attribute without breaking the code.
To recap, the form method is for displaying the form.
It's passed in an instance variable that contains information about the save data for the current widget.
By default, the instance is empty for new widgets.
Since that's the case, we create some default values and merge it with the instance.
That way we always have the minimum data we need.
Lastly, we simply output the fields like so.
The third method we have is the update method.
This method is called when a user submits the form.
This allows us to filter the input in our own way.
This method is passed in two variables.
The first is the new submitted data and the second is the previous instance data.
I'm going to create a new variable called instance.
This will contain all our widget settings, we only have one setting, which is the title, we'll set
the title to the new instanced title.
We're going to just sanitize the title by stripping any tags from the input, using the strip tags function,
then you have to return this instance so that WordPress can then save our widget settings.
Before we finish, let's go back to the widget method and echo out a simple recipe of the day message
will be changing this later.
Let's go to the widget admin page.
You should find the widget ready to use and this widget to your sidebar and place it at the very top,
WordPress takes care of setting up the UI for us and displaying the form.
We can change the title and it will be updated properly.
Let's view our site.
You should see the widget being outputted onto the sidebar.
The widget method is called to display the widget.
Now the question is, how do we display a recipe of the day?
We have to take care of picking a random recipe and make it last for a day.
Then our widget should refresh the recipe of the day.
We can do this a number of ways, like using the options API.
However, there's an API meant for this kind of task, which is called the Transience API.
Before we use that, we have to set up a cron job.
We'll tackle how to do most of these tasks in the next lecture.