It's time to create our very first shortcode, what exactly is a shortcode, a shortcode, it's just
a piece of text that a user can paste into their content that will transform itself into Gmail to render
your content differently.
That sounds similar to how a block works.
Prior to version 5.0, short codes were how you would create dynamic content, slideshows, video players,
call outs and just about anything else was built with short codes instead of short codes.
WordPress highly recommends using blocks with the introduction of Gutenberg.
As time goes on, blocks will be the de facto standard for creating dynamic content.
For now, short codes are still prevalent, and so taking the time to understand how they work will
help you with projects that require you to convert shortcode into blocks.
Luckily, shortcode aren't complicated.
Unlike blocks, you don't need to know any new features of IP or JavaScript.
The short code we're going to create will be very powerful.
What we want to do is provide a form that a user can use to submit a recipe.
In this part of the course, we'll be looking at how to create shortcode codes, make AJAX requests,
sanitizing HTML and creating a post dynamically.
It's definitely a lot to do, but I assure you I'll show you every step of the way.
Let's take a look at the short coats API codecs page, I provide a link to this page in the resource
section of this lecture.
Skimming through this page, you can see that the shortcode API provides a lot of power for customizing
our site.
Shortcode can be used almost like Tagg's.
They can have attributes and even content in between.
Creating a shortcode is almost similar to using hooks inside the main plugin file.
Under the shortcode section, we're going to call a function called Add Shortcode.
This function has two parameters, which is the name of the shortcode and the function to call when
the short code is used.
We're going to call this shortcode recipe creator.
The function we want to call is our recipe.
Create or shortcode.
Let's define this function now, create a folder called Shortcode Inside the includes folder.
Now create a file called creator and define the function inside here, make sure to include it from
the main plugin file.
We're going to simply return a hello world string.
We can now use our shortcode, let's create a page called Submit Recipe and insert the short code.
Inserting a shortcode into the Gutenberg Editta requires a certain block.
If you were to scroll down the list of blocks, you should find a category called widgets.
One of the blocks should be called shortcode.
And this block to the page, basically, it's written just like an HTML element, but with square brackets
instead of angle brackets, input the name recipe creator.
We won't be adding anything else.
Go ahead and publish the page, let's add the page to the main menu as well.
If we navigate to our page, we'll find Hello, World Outputted.
Now that we've confirmed the shortcode is working, we can begin creating the form.
Back inside, the editor create another file called creator Dast Templated.
Open the file inside the assets, extras creator Dasch Templated copy and paste the code from the text
file into the template.
There's nothing super special going on here, it's just a regular form using Bootstrap Mark-Up, each
input field has an ID attribute which will be using to grab the inputs value later on.
I'll provide this template for you.
In the resources section of this lecture, you'll notice that I haven't interviewed Bootstrap.
This is because our theme already uses bootstrap.
It's important to include bootstrap, regardless of whether the team has it or not.
It is overkill but necessary.
The only reason I'm not doing this is because this is just an example plugin for this course.
I'm not too worried about adding bootstrap since I already know my theme uses bootstrap.
Let's output this form now like before.
We're going to create a variable called creator of HTML and set its value to the value returned by the
file get contents function.
I'm going to pass in creator Dasch template and set its second parameter to true, then we're going
to simply return this variable.
Refresh your page and you should see the form, this form is pretty simple, we don't have any tags
or categories or featured images.
We're going to keep it to just the title and content.
I want users to be able to use the tiny MCE editor for editing the content.
It may be tempting to use the Gutenberg editor, but currently it's very difficult to load in the Gutenberg
editor.
You don't have to worry about using a different editor as WordPress will still be able to convert the
content into something Gutenberg compatible to load in the tiny MCE Ed WordPress provides a handy function
for us called WP Editor.
Let's use this now.
Right after grabbing our template called the Function WP Underscore Editor.
In the resource section, I provide a link to learn more about this function, this function has three
parameters, which is the default content, the ID and then some additional settings.
We want the content to be empty so will pass in an empty string.
The ID name is very important.
On the Codex page, WordPress tells us to use only lowercase letters or underscores otherwise the editor
won't work properly.
In that case, I'm going to set the ID to recipe content editor.
Let's refresh our page and see the results of this function.
Well, this isn't exactly what we wanted.
We got the editor, but there are two problems.
If you look at the HTML, it's outputted right outside the form, and it didn't replace the text area
filled with the same ID name.
This is because the WP editor function echoes out the editor right away.
We don't want that.
We want to add the editor and replace the TextField with that editor.
To do this, we will need to do some hacking.
The solution is very simple and that's by using PCP's output.
Buffer's PGP provides a set of function that allows us to control the output, which is what we'll need
to make this editor work the way we want it to.
You'll see how this works in just a moment.
First things first.
Let's go back to the template and replace this form group with a placeholder called Content Editor.
Back inside the shortcode function, we're going to create another function called our Generate Content
editor.
Inside this function, we're going to call the function of start.
This is a function that will grab any content that is outputted.
This function will prevent the content from being outputted until you tell it to or until the page is
finished executing.
So if we were to echo out Hello world, this won't be outputted until the script is finished running.
Because of this, we can grab the WP editor function and put it right after the output buffer.
It's safe to assume that the content editor won't be outputted right away.
Create a variable named editor content and set its value to the value returned by the Obbie get clean
function.
This function will grab any content that was outputted before this function was called and return it,
the last step is just to return the ED contents variable.
To summarize what's going on in this function, it goes something like this by calling the Obbie start
function, p p will create a buffer that will grab any content that has output it into a buffer.
There are various reasons you would want to do this, but we do it because we want to grab the editor
and not allow it to be outputted when we call the editor.
This is exactly what happens.
It gets stored in that buffer to grab everything inside the buffer.
We use the objet, get clean function.
Since the editor was stored in a buffer, we don't have to worry about it being outputted.
The Obbie get clean function will also take care of clearing the output so we don't get to editors.
We can now use this function, create a variable named editor HTML and set its value to the value returned
by the R generate content editor function.
Using the string replace function will replace the placeholder with the generated ed HTML.
Let's refresh the page and you should now see the editor placed correctly inside the form.
This is exactly what we wanted in the next lecture.
We'll take a look at how to make this forum work.
Oh.