Let's start working on submitting the recipe.
Let's give the recipe form an idea of recipe dash form.
Above this form, let's add a status div with the ID of recipe dash status.
We'll use this Divx to display a message to the user whether or not the recipe was simple and successfully
open the main dog's file.
This is the same file that should contain the reading submission.
Let's listen for the form submission using the on method.
We'll be given an event object.
We're going to call the prevent default method so that the form isn't submitted.
We want to use Ajax for submitting the form, we're going to hide the form during submission.
This will make sure the user doesn't submit the form twice.
Next, we're going to select the Status d'Hiv and add some HTML, add a simple weighting message.
I'm going to wrap this around some bootstrap markup to make it look good.
Just like last time, create an object that will contain the form values to grab the values, you simply
select the input field by their IDs and use the VAL method to get the value.
For the action will set this to our submit user recipe.
Grabbing the content from the editor is pretty simple when we included the editor, WordPress also loaded
the tiny MCE object.
We can grab the content by using this object and grabbing the current active editor and called the get
content method, which will return unsanitized each HTML.
Lastly, we submit this data using GAO queries post method.
Remember that the recipe object is available to us and we can use it to provide the Ajax You URL inside
the response function, we'll be doing either one of two things.
We're going to check the data object for a status property and check if its value is equal to two.
If it is, then we know that the form submission was a success, otherwise an error occurred.
I'm going to update the status h html appropriately if the submission was a failure.
I'm going to show the form again.
Let's handle the form submission now inside the main plug and file, let's add the action Hook WP Ajax.
We have to append our action to this hook like so the function we want to call will be the same name
as the action.
I'm also going to make this hook available for guests as I'm going to allow for guest submissions to.
Inside the process folder, create the file called submit dash user dash recipe and define the function
here.
We'll need to include this file from the main plugin as well.
Create a variable named output.
This will be an array that will contain the status, set the status to one.
I'm going to perform a very simple check on the title input, I want to know if it's empty.
If it is, I'm going to send back the output with the WP, send Jason function.
This will also kill the scripts.
After this, I'm going to paste in some code.
Pause the video if you need to.
All I'm doing here is sanitizing the input, I'm also creating the metadata.
We create the recipe data array just like last time I've set the rating and rating count to zero.
Something you'll notice is that for the title, I'm using these sanitized TextField function, but I'm
not applying this to the content itself.
We can't use this function for sanitizing the content.
Instead, I'm using a function called WP KSEE Post and the resource section.
I provide a link to a function called WPX says.
Let's take a look at this function in more detail.
There are a few libraries out there in AP that help with sanitizing each HTML.
WordPress provides its own solution, which is the preferred method for sanitizing HTML.
The WPX function is a pretty flexible function as it allows us to define what HTML tags, attributes
and protocols are allowed.
It would be pretty time consuming to have to re-enter what HTML is allowed every time we use this function.
If we scroll down, there's a link to the WP KSEE post function.
This function does the exact same thing as the WP access function, but instead uses the same filter
for posts.
This saves us some time since our recipe post is basically just a post, it makes sense to just use
this Schauder function.
If you prefer to define your own set of HTML and attributes, then I suggest using the WP KSEE function.
All our data is now sanitized and ready to be inserted into the database.
Inserting opposes actually really easy.
We don't even have to use the global WP object to perform this task.
WordPress provides a handy function called WP Insert Post.
I'll provide a link to this function inside the resources section.
This function will insert a post for us and even take care of sanitisation just in case we forgot to
do it ourselves.
There's only one parameter, which is an array of arguments.
There are numerous things we can set, but we won't be using all of them.
The only required arguments are the content and the title.
If we skip anything, WordPress will fill in the rest.
By default, this function will end up returning the idea of the post created, which we will need for
adding the post metadata, creating a variable named post ID and its value will be the value returned
by the WP insert post function.
Pass in an array.
We're going to define the following arguments, post content will be set to the content variable.
Post name and post title will both be set to the title.
The difference between these two is the name will be used for the slug and the title is used for the
human readable title, post status will be set to pending.
By default, this is set to draft, will consider the post complete, but we don't want to publish the
recipe either.
Pending will let administrators know that the Post needs to be reviewed before being published.
Post type will be set to recipe, since that is our post type.
That's it.
Feel free to read over the codex and set the rest of the arguments if you would like to customize this
further.
Next, let's call the update post meta function to set the recipe data metadata.
Our function is almost finished, all we need to do now is update the status in the output array to
two and then output it using the WP, send JSON function.
Refresh the recipe form page and try submitting the form with no input.
You should get an error.
Now, try filling in all the fields and we should see a success message.
You should also have your console open to check for any errors if you've received no errors and received
a success message.
Then there's one last thing we need to check.
Go to the recipe admin page and see if the post has been added.
After confirming that it's available, let's view the contents in the editor, as you can see, everything
was inputted correctly.
This is exactly what we wanted.
We now have a form where users can submit their own recipes.
What I like about this is that even though we're not using the Gutenberg editor on the front end, this
will still work.
The content has been converted into a blog called The Classic Block.
This makes Gutenberg backwards compatible.