Right now, I'm on a website for the WordPress plugin Beeby Press, this plug in is one of the most
advanced plugins out there.
It allows you to turn your WordPress site into a forum.
One of the most prominent features of Beeby press is that developers can write plugins to extend this
plugin.
Here's the thing, though.
Beeby Press doesn't implement its own plugin API.
Beeby Press takes advantage of WordPress plugin API and just adds its own action filter hooks.
Writing a plugin for BBY press is the same as writing a plugin for WordPress.
As we discussed previously, Beeby Press just uses the do action and apply filters functions for creating
its own custom hooks.
Let's say that we publish our plugin and it has now become insanely popular.
It's become so popular that we're getting requests for new features daily.
Unfortunately, some of these requests deviate from the main purpose of the plugin.
We don't want to deviate from the main purpose, nor do we want to limit the functionality of the plugin.
So how do we solve this?
We can use the plugin API to allow developers to further extend our plugin with more plug ins.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the plugin API.
WordPress provides a handful of functions to use the plugin API.
Actually, we've already been using them from the very beginning.
The add action and add filter are functions we've used plenty of times.
You already know how to use these functions, but let's take a look at how you would go about using
them in a different way.
I want to let developers extend the rating function, so let's open up the rating function file now.
Right before the JSON is outputted.
Let's call a function called Do Action.
This function takes in the name of the action we want to trigger, this can be a custom defined one
or one available in WordPress.
Let's integrate custom one and name it recipe rated.
The second parameter is optional.
It's a list of parameters that will be sent to any function that hooks into this hook.
I'm going to pass in an array with the host ID rating and the IP of the user.
That's it, we don't have to do anything else now, any plugin developer can use the add action function
and hook into this action hook.
Even if this hook isn't used by functions, WordPress will not throw errors and will run as usual.
Just be sure to let other developers know that this action is available.
Let's test this out by developing another plugin.
This plugin will email us whenever a user writes a recipe, we're going to take advantage of the hook
we created earlier to do this inside the plugin folder and create a file called Email Dash Recipe Dot.
This will contain our new plugin, I'm not going to bother creating a folder or try and organize this
plugin because this plugin will be very simple.
It'll only be a few lines of code.
I'm going to set the name of this plugin to recipe e-mail rating and set the description to this plugin.
Extends the recipe plugin.
Let's call the add action function and use the custom recipe rated hook.
Previously, we've always passed in a string name of the function we wanted to call this time will pass
in an anonymous function.
Anonymous functions are special to P and not WordPress.
They're only available in five point three or above.
So I can't recommend that you use anonymous functions in production plugins.
If you plan on supporting versions earlier than five point three, our anonymous function will accept
an array with the details about the rating.
We want our new plugin to email the author of this recipe about the new rating.
Let's get the info about the post by using the get post function.
You pass this function, the ID of the posts, the function will return data about the post, I'm going
to create a variable named user email.
We can now grab the author email by using the get the author meta function.
This function has two parameters.
The first is the field we want to grab.
This would be the user email.
The second parameter is the ID of the author.
Our post data will contain a field named Post Arthur, which contains the author, it now we can compose
the subject and message.
The subject will be your recipe has received a new rating.
The message will be your recipe, followed by the title of the Post has received a new rating of and
then we pass in the rating.
The last thing we need to do is send this as an email, WordPress provides a function called WP e-mail.
Why use this function instead of e-mail function?
Well, this function is pluggable, meaning other plugins can take advantage of modifying the email
and its info.
The parameters are the same as BP's mail function.
The first parameter is the recipient's email.
The second and third parameters are the subject and message respectively.
Our plugin is now ready.
You should keep in mind that this won't work on most local servers, sending emails require SMTP, so
you will need to test this on a live site.