Depending on the complexity of your site, you may want to pop in a way for users to register and log
in by default.
WordPress comes with its own login and registration forms, but they're very simple and not appealing
at all.
That's all right.
WordPress can't account for every user situation out there.
Luckily, this problem is solved by using third party plugins.
There are dozens and dozens of membership plug ins out there.
Originally for this lecture, I was planning on recommending one and then installing it.
Then I would walk you through on how to set it up.
But there were two problems I encountered.
The first problem was that the plug ins were extremely bloated.
Now, don't get me wrong, the plug ins were already using have some bloat, but they're not so bloated
that they drastically slowed down the site because of features we're not using.
However, the membership plugins that were usable have thousands of lines of code that we weren't going
to use, such as payment processing, custom fields and so much more.
The second problem was finding plug ins that were super simple, but they weren't exactly developer
friendly.
These plug ins have their own uses and it was too much trouble to make the UI match the theme on our
site.
A lot of them were outdated as well.
So rather than using a third party plug in, I thought this would be a great opportunity to show you
how to do it yourself.
Before we get started, I want to take the time to let you know that membership plug ins are extremely
beneficial for any theme.
If you plan on selling your theme, then including a featured packed membership plug and wouldn't be
so bad.
I recommend it, however, for the theme we're creating, we only need something super simple.
All right, let's get started, some of the steps we'll be taking won't be anything we haven't done
before.
It will be using a shortcode to display the form and an AJAX request to process the information will
be working inside the recipe plug in rather than a custom one just to save some time inside the main
plug in a file called the Add Shortcode function.
The name of the shortcode will be recipe off form, the function to call is our recipe off form shortcode.
Free to file inside the includes shortcode Cerveteri called off Dasch formed to find the function here
and include it from the main plug and file.
Next, create a file named off Dasch form Dasch Templated.
This file will contain all the HTML for the form inside the Udemy theme folder.
We have a template called Off HTML.
I'm going to open this up inside my browser.
Here's what that page looks like, we're basically going to try and recreate this page, if I were to
open this template inside the editor and scroll down, you'll eventually find the HTML for the form.
To be specific, the HTML should be inside the section tag with the ID of content, you'll find div
tags with the classes, call one third and call to third, copy both these elements and their contents
and paste them into the auth form template like so.
After doing so, let's go back to the shortcode function, just like before, will be creating a variable,
I'm going to call it form HTML and its value will be the value returned by the file get contents function
with the template in the first parameter and true as the second.
Then I'll just return the HTML.
Let's test this out now.
I'm going to create a brand new page with a title, My Account.
The content will be the shortcode recipe off form, the template will also need to be set to full width.
Once you've made those changes, save the page and then view it.
You should more or less have what I have on my screen, we can now begin authenticating the user.
The very first thing we should do is make sure the form is secure for submission.
There are various ways you can go about this, but WordPress provides a solution called nonces.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link for more information about this topic.
Let's take a look at what WordPress has to say about nonces.
A Norns is a number used once to help protect you.
URLs and forms from certain types of misuse, malicious or otherwise.
WordPress nonces aren't numbers, but are a hash made up of numbers and letters.
Nor are they used only once, but have a limited lifetime after which they expire during that time period.
The same Norns will be generated for a given user in a given context.
The Norns for that action will remain the same for that user until that Norns lifecycle has completed.
WordPress is security tokens are called nonces, despite the above noted differences from true nonces
because they serve much the same purpose as nonces.
Do they help protect against several types of attacks, including CSR, but do not protect against replay
attacks because they aren't checked for one time?
Use nonces should never be relied on for authentication or authorization.
Access control.
Protect your functions.
Using current user can always assume nonces can be compromised.
So as WordPress states, this helps you create a layer of security by using a token for verifying the
form submission.
But it's not completely foolproof.
The rest of this documentation goes over how to use nonces.
I suggest reading it fully after this lecture.
So here's what we want to do.
I want to load Anon's inside the template.
The process will be simple.
We'll just generate the nonce and then load it in the template using placeholders inside the template
file.
At the very top, I'm going to add a placeholder called Norns.
Underscore Field.
Underscore.
Then inside the shortcode function, I'm going to perform a simple string replace call like we've always
have.
For the replacement, we'll be calling a function called WP Knoxfield.
This will take care of generating a nonce value while also creating an input field containing this value
in the resource section, I provide a link to this function.
There are four parameters which are all optional.
The first one is always recommended, though the action name is a way to reference this field.
You should set one as you'll need to verify it later on.
You'll see how this works in just a moment.
For now, I'm going to set it to recipe off.
The next parameter is name for the input field by default, it's underscored WP notes, I'm going to
set this to the default.
The third parameter is whether to include a refer.
A refer is the Yooralla that the request was submitted on.
It's always good practice to make sure the form was submitted on this page and not through some other
site.
I'm going to set this as true.
The fourth parameter determines whether this field should be outputted or returned set is to false,
which will return the field rather than output it.
Let's verify that the fields are being generated and output it by refreshing the page and checking the
HTML.
Using the developer tools, you'll find two hidden input fields appear right before our forms.
Traditionally, you'll want these fields to appear inside the forum, but we won't concern ourselves
with that since will be using Jorquera and Ajax to submit the form, open the main file.
This is the same file that contains the reading code will be working inside this file for all our JavaScript
needs.
Once again, I'll be using the on method for listening to a form submission and preventing the default
behavior.
We have this div tag with an I.D. of registered Dasch status.
I'm going to modify its HTML contents and let the user know their account is being created.
Then I'll just hide the form to prevent resubmission.
Next, I'm going to create the form object like before the action will be recipe create accounts.
The other five values will just be the forms, input fields.
The last property I want to create will be called Underscore WP notes, it's important, you name it
this as WordPress will be expecting this field when verifying the nonce, the value will be grabbed
from the hidden input field.
The ID of the input field should be underscored, WP notes.
The last thing I want to do is make a jury post request.
It's the exact same way as we did it before, except I'm going to be using promises, the always method
behave similar to the previous way we did it.
It'll accept a function where the response is passed into it, just like last time.
We'll check the status property and display an appropriate message to the end user.
If the registration was a success, we'll just let the user know they can register.
Otherwise we'll tell them it was a failure and display the form again.
Nothing new here.
Pretty simple stuff.
All right, so that basically sets up the front end in the next lecture, will process the data and
create a new user.
Oh.