In the previous lecture, we set up the forum and prep the JavaScript code.
Now we begin processing the data inside the main plug file.
I'm going to use the WP Ajax no priv hook.
This is important.
Users who are not logged in should be the only ones to be able to create accounts.
The function will use the same name as the dynamic look inside the process folder, create a file named
create dash account and define the function here.
Make sure to include it from the main plug and file as well.
Inside this function, I'm going to create the output array with a status key and its value being one.
Immediately afterwards, I'm going to grab the underscore WP Norns field and store it in a variable
called Knot's.
I'm going to check if it's available by using a ternary operator.
If it's set, I'll set this variable to the field.
Otherwise I'll just set it to an empty string.
Next, inside a conditional statement, I'm going to use a function called WP Verify Knot's.
This function will take in the nonce we were given and then the name of the action, if we go back to
the shortcode function, you'll see we named it recipe off, passed that in as a string to the function.
If the function returns false, then we'll want to kill the script with the output like we always do.
I'm going to create an additional conditional statement to check if the rest of the post variables were
set, if any of them weren't, then I'll just kill the scripts.
After performing these simple checks, let's create variables for each of these post values, I'm going
to sanitize each value with these sanitized TextField function, the email will be sanitized with these
sanitized email function.
It works like the sanitized TextField function, except for emails with the data being set, I'm going
to use another conditional statement and perform quite a few checks.
Are we using the username exists and email exists functions to check if the user name or email is already
in use?
These functions are provided by WordPress, and we'll make the necessary SQL queries to check if these
two values are taken while I'm performing these checks, I'll check if the two passwords match and I'll
check if the email being submitted is a valid email using the IS email function.
The is email is another WordPress function that helps with verifying an email and its format.
Be sure to check this conditional statement twice, make sure your code matches mine.
Pause the video if you need to.
If any of these checks pass, I'm going to kill the script again.
If the user has made it this far, then will begin creating the user.
There are two functions available for doing this.
The WP create user and WP insert user functions.
Both do the exact same thing.
The WP create user is a rapper and a more simplified version of the WP insert user function.
This may seem appealing, but it won't do for our purposes.
I want to set more values than this function will allow, so it will be using the WP insert user function
instead.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to this function.
As you can see, this function accepts an array of fields we can set.
We won't be setting all of these, only the ones the user has submitted.
Let's use this function now.
This function will return inside.
If successful.
I want to save this ID for future use.
So create a variable named user ID and assign its value to this function.
Pass an array and set the following fields user log and will be set to the username.
User pass will be set to pass.
We're passing this in as plain text, but you don't have to worry about it being saved as is WordPress
will take the time to salt and hash this password for you before inserting it into the database.
User email will be set to the email.
Use your nice name will be set to the name.
The nice name is used to display a friendlier name to users rather than displaying the username.
That's all you need to do to create a user.
If we look at the documentation, you'll see a list of possible return values.
Here is what WordPress says about the possible returns.
If successful returns.
The newly created users user underscore ID if query fails, returns a WP underscore error object.
So if this fails, we can definitely expect a WP er object.
I'm going to create a conditional statement and use the IS WP error function to help us identify if
the value returned is an error object.
If this returns true, then I want to kill the script and let the user know the registration was a failure.
At this point, the user is completely registered, something WordPress does is send an email to the
admin and user about their registration.
Let's also mimic this behavior for the user.
Only WordPress provides a function called WP New User Registration.
This function will send an email to the user with their credential info, the first parameter is the
user ID, the second parameter is deprecated, so you'll have to pass in.
Not the last parameter allows you to specify who should be sent an email.
There are three possible values for this.
You can set this to admin for the admin to get an email.
There's also user if you want only the user to get the email.
Lastly, you can set this too, both for both admin and user to get the emails.
I'm going to set this to user since I want the user to get the email.
Now that the user has been created, we only have a few more things to do.
This next step is completely optional, but I like to automatically log in the user.
After creating their account to log the user in, we need to grant the user object.
I'm going to create a new variable named user and assign its value to the value returned by the function
user by.
This function will return a user object, it allows you to grab a user with numerous fields and values,
since we have the user I.D., we'll just use that.
The first parameter will be the string ID to specify that we want to grab the user by their ID.
The second parameter will be the ID itself.
They should return the user and all their properties to log in a user.
There are a couple of things we need to do.
First, we need to let WordPress know about the current user.
This will not authenticate the user, but simply tell WordPress that a user is now active within the
system called the said current user function and pass him the user ID along with the user login.
Next, I want to set up a cookie so that WordPress will remember this user for future use called the
function WP set off Cookie and pass in the user ID.
This function has a second parameter, which will remember the user even if they exit out of their browser
by default.
This is false, which is what we want.
The reason I want this is because the user may be registering on an insecure location.
This cookie will only be active until the user exits out their browser.
Next, I want to set off a hook using the do action function.
The hook I want to run is called WP Login and I'm going to pass in two extra arguments.
I'm going to pass in the user login and the user object.
This hook will allow WordPress itself to run any authentication settings and will allow for any other
plugins to perform any setups when a user is logged in after doing all of this.
The user is now logged in.
Before I move on, I want to inform you about a function called Sinon that does all this for us.
But the reason we didn't use it is because it brings back mixed results upon first log in.
When a user logs in for the first time, there is additional setup that WordPress and additional plugins
want to perform.
By doing it this way, we make it easier to let those plug ins do so.
What I just showed you is a more definite way to login a user for the first time to end this function.
I'm going to update the output status key to two, then I will kill the script.
This will let the script know the user has successfully created an account, we're almost done with
the registration since the user is logged in after registering, then we should redirect them to the
home page so that they don't have to stare at this page inside the front NQ function.
I'm going to create another local variable named Home Your URL and set its value returned by the function
home you URL.
Passing a symbol forward slash to let this function know you want the Eurail to the root page itself.
We can now use this variable inside our script right after the status message set, the HCF property
of the location object to the new localized property like so.
You can now test this form, make sure you are logged out or this form will not work.
Try testing this form with invalid info.
Then try testing it with valid info.
You should see a success message for a brief moment and then be redirected to the home page.
You should also notice that you are now logged back in by WordPress.
This is exactly what we wanted.
I'm going to log out again and navigate back to this page in the next lecture.
We'll work on making the login form work.
It's very similar to what we did with the registration form.