In this lecture, we're going to finish up our shortcode by making the law informed work inside the
main JS file.
I'm going to copy and paste the previous JavaScript code we use for the register form.
I'm going to change a lot of this code from the field to the status messages so that they reflect the
log in the form.
Instead, the action will be recipe user login.
Make sure to update the status messages and selections.
Nothing crazy here.
It's what we did previously create a new Ajax Action hook with no privileges.
I'm going to copy and paste the action I used in the form object like so.
Create a file inside the process folder called login and define the function inside here, make sure
to include it from the main plug and file.
Inside this function, I'm going to ground the first two lines from the create account file and paste
it in here.
I'm creating an output variable, grabbing and verifying the nonce and then checking to see if the username
and password was submitted.
I'm going to remove the e-mail and password confirmation from this check.
Really nothing new so far.
I'm going to create a new variable named user that will contain the value returned by the function WP
Sinon.
This function will authenticate users for you, this is the function I recommend you use when you're
authenticating users who have already logged in before this function has two parameters.
The first is an array of the login credentials it will use to verify and authenticate the current user.
There are three fields we can set the user login except the username.
I'm going to sanitize this while I'm at it.
The next key is user password, which accepts the password.
Lastly, the remember key allows you to specify whether the user should be remembered on this device.
I'm going to set this to true.
This will suddenly user in just to make sure we're going to create another conditional statement checking
if this function returns, an error object using the IS error function.
If it is an error object, then we'll just kill the script.
Otherwise we'll update the status to two and kill the script once more.
That will take care of everything if you haven't already, log out and then try logging in.
After confirming that everything works, there's one last thing we want to do.
We're almost finished.
I promise.
If you were to go to the admin dashboard and navigate to settings general, you'll find a setting called
anyone can register.
This setting controls word registration form.
Even if this is ticked off, plugins can still create accounts with code.
We're going to use this setting to our advantage.
I want to hide the form.
If registration is disabled, we'll start by creating a placeholder inside the template.
Find the div tag that contains the whole registration form and add show regg form.
Will replace this placeholder with a style attribute inside the shortcode function, add another string
replacement function.
For the replace function we're going to use, a ternary operator will be performing a check using a
function called get option, we haven't discussed the options API, but this function will grab the
options from the options table.
Using Heidi skill, you can open the WP options table, WordPress stores, all of its settings here.
It also stores transients and plug in options.
One of the options is users can register.
This is the option that is updated.
When you took the checkbox on the admin settings page, if the value is zero, then that means the registration
is closed.
If it's one, then that means registration is open.
We can pass this into the get option function and it'll tell us whether or not registration is open.
If this check returns false, we'll hide the registration form with a simple display success style.
Otherwise, it'll be empty and display, as is save your work, update the settings to disable registration
and try viewing the form.
It should not display the very last thing I want to do is hide these forms if the user is logged in.
Right now I'm logged in and it should not be displaying inside the shortcode function.
Create a conditional statement at the very top call.
The function is user logged in.
If this returns true, we'll just return an empty string.
Refresh the page and you should see nothing up here, that's it, we're finally finished.
It was a lot to go through, but well worth it.