The last thing I want to do is create a logout link.
There was already a logout link inside the admin WordPress bar, but I prefer to create one inside the
theme.
There are two ways we can go about this.
We could edit the theme and add the link, or we can use hooks.
In our case, either solution is valid since we're the creator of the theme.
But Hooke's work universally and we'll scale better.
We'll go with the hooks root inside the main plug and file.
I'm going to add a new filter hook called WP NAV Menu Items.
This hook is triggered when WordPress begins to load in the menu items for a theme navigation menu,
it'll be passed in the raw HTML menu items for us to manipulate the name of the function I want to call
will be called Jiyu new NAV menu items with a priority of nine nine nine.
I set the priority to a high number, as I want the logout link to be placed at the end of the menu,
I'm going to create a new file.
Inside the includes a front folder called Logout Dash linked up and define the function here.
Lastly, make sure to include it.
Since this is a filter, function will be passed in a value and be expected to return it, the value
that's passed in is items, which is the raw HTML menu items.
The first thing I'm going to do is create a conditional statement.
I'm going to check if the user is logged in.
I'll be using the IS user logged in function to accomplish this.
I want to check if they're not logged in, if they aren't, then I'm just going to return the items
as it is.
There's no point in displaying the logout link.
If they're not logged in in the first place.
If they are logged in, then I'm going to generate the link to the log out page, create a variable
named New Link.
I'm going to set its value to a pair of opening and closing line tags.
In between these tags, I'm going to call the function WP log in out this function will generate a link
to the login and log out pages of WordPress.
However, since we're only displaying this link, if the user is logged in, it will always show the
log out.
This is fine by us.
This function has two parameters which will want to take advantage of.
The first parameter is the URL to redirect the user to.
If they successfully log out, I'm going to set this to the home URL function.
I'll pass in a forward slash to indicate I want the Eurail to be the root URL and that should set up
the redirection.
The second parameter is whether this link should be echoed out or not.
Since this is a filter function and I'm returning data, then I want this link to be returned by default.
This will be set to true, which will echo out the link.
I'm going to change this to false to return the link now that the link is generated properly.
All we have to do is return the items and append the new link variable along with these links.
After doing so, let's refresh the page and see what we get, the logout link should appear if you're
logged in.
There is one noticeable problem, though.
The logout link appears in both the primary and secondary navigation menus.
This is a bit redundant.
The filter hook we're using will apply our changes to all menu items, regardless of their status or
location.
Something I do want to know is that this filter hook will only apply to user generated menu items.
As you may know, WordPress will automatically generate a menu item if a user doesn't have one set up.
This is usually the case on Fresh Insulation's of WordPress.
Anyway, let's assume the user created a menu and we want the logout link to appear on the secondary
menu item only to force the link to appear in only the secondary menu.
We only have to make one small change back inside the main plugin file.
We'll have to update the filter hook.
This filter hook is dynamic.
This is optional though, to use the dynamic version.
All you have to do is add the menu log right after the WP nav menu phrase.
In this case it would be secondary.
Just like that, the links should appear only on the secondary menu, refresh the page to see the final
results that should do it.
If you want to learn more about the log in our function, then check out the resource section of this
lecture.
Oh.