I have the filter content file opened, if you don't remember, this function will filter the recipe
content and display the recipe information along with the rating inside the function we use, the global
WP DB object to make a raw query.
This query simply gets the number of readings a recipe has.
I'm going to add some line breaks before and after this query so that you can see it more clearly,
just like any other query.
It's important to sanitize any data we add to it.
We should always take the steps necessary to secure our plugins and theme's WordPress has a method for
securing queries by providing the proper method.
This method works similarly to paedos prepared statements.
They aren't hard to understand or use.
This method will simply sanitize a query before it's executed.
This method requires two things the query itself and the data that should be sanitized.
Let's prepare this query.
It's very simple.
First, we're going to wrap this query around the method from the WP DB object called Prepare.
I'm going to format this a bit by putting the query on its own line.
This method has two parameters.
It accepts a query as the first parameter, and then the second parameter is the data to sanitize.
If we have more than one piece of data like in our query, then we can keep passing in more data.
This function is pretty flexible and can grow to as many parameters as we need it to.
There are two pieces of variables I want to sanitize, which is the post ID and the IP.
Pass these in like so.
This won't work just yet, this method has our query and the data, but they're not tied together.
How does it know where to place the sanitized data?
Well, we'll need to use the special placeholders created by WordPress.
There are the usual placeholders, percent X, percent D and percent F, where percent s is for string's
percent D is for integers and percent F is for floating numbers.
Replace these values with the correct placeholders.
The post ID should be percent D and the IP should be percent s.
That's it.
This method will take in all this information and then return a sanitized query for the actual method
that will run this query.
Let's try checking out a recipe.
Now, here's a recipe we made earlier.
So far, we have no errors.
Let's try reading this recipe and refreshing the page.
Still no heirs and orating was saved using prepared statements is one of the best ways to protect yourself
against SQL injections.
Prepared statements should be used for sequel queries for methods like the insert or delete method.
The WP DB object will already create a sanitized query for you.
Here's what I want you to do now.
I want you to go through our plugin and look for more raw queries and prepare them like we did with
this query.