Let's keep adding on to the recipe, plug in, the next thing we want to do is create one of these dashboard
widgets on the WordPress admin page.
A lot of plug ins add dashboard, which is to provide more info about the plug in itself or the data
it provides.
It's perfect for adding a little news which it feeds so users can be kept up to date.
With your plug in, let's create one ourselves.
The widget will create will provide the latest five readings inside the main plug and file out an action
hook called WP Dashboard Setup.
The function to call is our ad dashboard widgets.
Create a file in the admin folder named Dashboard Dash Widgets and define the function here, as always,
make sure to include this file from the main plug and file.
Creating a dashboard, which is really easy.
You only have to call one function, which is the WP add dashboard widget function.
There are three parameters we need to set.
First is the slug, which can be thought of as a unique ID, set this to our latest recipe rating,
which it.
The second parameter is the title of our widget, set this to latest recipe ratings.
The last parameter is the function to call, which will display the contents of the widget, set this
to our latest recipe rating display.
In the same file, let's define the display function.
We want the widget to display the five latest ratings to do this, we'll need the PDB Global Object
create a variable called latest ratings that will be set to the value returned by the get results method
of the PDB object.
The query will be using will simply select all the data in the recipe ratings recipe.
To get the latest entries, we have to set the order by for the ID column in descending order.
Lastly, limit the amount of results returned by five.
Next, echo out some yellow tags, and in between these tags will run a foreach loop that will loop
through the latest ratings array.
The get results method will return an array of results, each item in the array will be an object.
Now I'm going to create two variables for the title and permalink.
To get these values, we can use the functions, get the title and get the permalink, which will return
the values we need about a particular post.
Notice that we're using these functions inside the plug in and outside of the loop to use these functions
properly.
We have to pass in the post ID.
We can get the ID by accessing the recipe ID property from the rating object.
This is where we stored the post ID.
Lastly, I'm just going to paste in some HTML.
Nothing special going on in here, I'm just echoing out the values and displaying a message that informs
the user about which recipe received a rating and the rating itself.
Save your changes and let's view the admin dashboard again.
We will now see our latest recipe, which it along with the latest ratings.
If you don't see any ratings, then try reading a recipe and come back to this page.