So before we move on to the next section, I want to talk more about shortcuts.
We've used shortcuts to display forms, but I haven't really gone beyond that in this lecture.
We'll explore more about what you can do with shortcuts.
We're going to keep things simple.
I want to create a button where the user will be taken to a Twitter page inside the main plug and file
at a new shortcode.
I'm going to call it Twitter follow.
I'm not going to bother names facing it, since this will be a rather generic shortcode, the function
to call will be named after Twitter.
Follow shortcode.
Inside the shortcode folder, create a file named Twitter Dasch, follow up and define the function
here.
LASLEY Include it.
Basically, a short code is very simple, you just have to return a string and that's what will be outputted
onto the screen, we can take this a step further by allowing the user to add attributes and content,
just like a regular HTML tag.
Let's set things up first.
I'm going to paste in the following code.
There's nothing special going on here.
I'm just returning a link with some classes applied to it to make it look nice.
I also have this nice little Twitter icon.
This is completely static.
And we'll take the user to Twitter.
I'm going to create a brand new page and use this shortcode.
I want you to do the same.
Make sure you publish the page.
All right, so I'm on the page, and as you can see, the shortcode is working as intended.
This is nothing we haven't done before.
The real power of shortcode comes from allowing users to customize its behavior.
Let's start with that.
You use just like regular HTML, short codes can have attributes and they are written in the same fashion.
Back inside the edit page, I'm going to add an attribute called Handle with a value of Udemy.
You can name your attributes, whatever you want, but WordPress does have a few rules in the resource
section of this lecture, I provide a link to the shortcode API.
This page gives really great explanations about how to use the shortcode API.
If you scroll down a bit, you'll find that WordPress says important tip.
Don't use Cammo case or uppercase for your attribute names.
We're going to keep things simple and just use all lowercase letters.
Now that we're specifying an attribute, we can use it inside the code.
Back inside the function.
You can accept all the attributes by adding the parameter acts.
This will be an array with all the attributes where the key is the name of the attribute and the value
is the value itself before we use any attributes.
It's always good practice to make sure each one has the default value.
I'm going to reassign my attributes to the function shortcode atts.
This is a special function meant especially for sugarcoats, it will take in an array of attributes
and make sure all default values are set.
The first parameter is an array of default attributes.
I only have one attribute, which is handle, and I'm going to give this a default value of you to me.
The second parameter to this function is the attributes itself.
So what this will do is set a default value for the handle attribute if the user didn't input this attribute.
We can now use this.
I'm going to replace the static link with the handle name and use the attribute handle instead.
Just like that, the handle name will be dynamic, I'm going to refresh the page and the links should
be updated.
So that's one way to extend shortcode.
The next thing you can do with short codes is use enclosed sort codes.
If you look at the short code on the edit page, you'll notice it's by itself.
However, just like HTML tags, we can add an enclosed version like some.
It's just the shortcode itself, but this time you're adding any forwards to let WordPress know where
it ends, anything placed in between these two shortcode will be passed into our function.
I'm going to set this to follow us.
Let's go back to the function and accept this new data inside the parameters, I can add a second parameter
called content.
This will contain the text inside an enclosed shortcode.
Keep in mind that enclosed short codes are optional for users.
I'm going to set this to a default value, which will be known.
Then I'm going to replace this text with the content variable like so.
I'm going to refresh the page, and as you can see, the text inside the button was replaced.
Short codes are very simple to use as a user and developer, they do make our code look cleaner and
more readable.
There is one last thing I want to show you.
The content placed inside the enclosed short codes can also contain HTML and even short codes.
However, short codes cannot be processed by short codes.
Naturally, if you would like to process short codes inside a short code, then you'll need to do one
simple thing back inside the function.
I'm going to remove the content variable with a function called do shortcode.
This function does, as its name suggests, it will take in a string and process the code inside, it'll
process short codes if there are any.
Just like that, our short code now supports shortcuts.
This is optional to do because I usually recommend it if you have a short code that's very complex and
you want it to be flexible.
All right.
That's basically it for shortcuts.
You can read the documentation to learn more cool tips and tricks for using shortcuts.