And this section will be cleaning up our theme even further.
I just want to adjust a couple of things and prepare everything for production that includes translations,
bundling, plug ins, et cetera.
Of course, we'll have to learn how to battle, test our theme and plug in, which is what we'll tackle
in this section as well.
Let's begin.
If you take a look at the homepage, you'll find all the posts we've created thus far.
However, each post excerpt has these dots right after it.
Each of these are called an ellipsis.
And while they may seem great, I personally don't like them inside the functions file.
We're going to add the filter hook called excerpt more.
This hook will pass and the ellipsis for filtering, however, we want to get rid of these dots, there's
a handy utility function that WordPress provides to return nothing.
Instead of defining our own function that will return nothing, I'm going to pass in the function.
Underscore, underscore, return, underscore, false.
This is a WordPress function that does exactly as it's named, it will return false open the WP Desh
includes function, file and search for this function.
Here is what WordPress is useful for, returning false two filters easily, if you scroll above, there
is even a function for returning true, which is also useful if you ever need it.
I encourage you to explore these functions if you ever need to use them in your own code.
Let's refresh the page and see if the dots are gone.
All right.
That's it for the excerpt in the next few lectures will continue with working on our theme.