In this lecture will be exploring image cropping and image sciences, WordPress makes it easy to crop
images without having to download or use any external third party libraries.
If we take a look at our posts on the homepage, you'll see our images fitting nice and tight.
However, just like Buddy Press, the images may be bigger than they should be.
Inspect the element and check the sizes of the images.
Inside this little preview box, you'll see the science that's on the page and the natural size of the
image, we want the natural size and size on the page to be as close as they can be to save on bandwidth.
To do this, we have to register the image size we desire.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to a function called Add Image Signs.
This function allows you to add a custom image size that WordPress will use whenever a new image is
uploaded by default.
WordPress has some built in image sizes, such as the thumbnail size, which is a size we've used before.
Inside the setup function.
We're going to call this function.
I'm going to add this code right after the themes support functions.
Let's call this function now.
And the first parameter is the name of this size any name will do.
I'm going to set this to J.
You dash post.
Dash image.
The second and third parameters are the width and height, respectively.
These are values you'll have to test out through trial and error.
The sizes I like are 860 by five.
Seventy five.
The last parameter is whether we want a soft crop or a hard crop, if you're unfamiliar with soft or
hard cropping, then check out the link I have in the resource section of this lecture.
This is a very long article that goes over image cropping and WordPress.
It's definitely worth reading, but I'm going to give you a quick rundown on what you need to know.
If you scroll down a bit, you'll come across these two images from the author.
These two images are full sized and not cropped at all.
By default, WordPress will set the fourth parameter to false meaning that images are soft cropped.
If you scroll down further, you'll come across the images resize.
As you can see, the images are not exactly the desired size the author wanted them to be.
The size the author put down is two hundred by two hundred.
So technically these images should be squares, but they're not.
This is what WordPress calls soft cropping.
WordPress will resize an image to the dimensions.
You specify, however, if the ratio of the images cannot be kept intact, it will then resize the image
to as close as to the dimensions you inputted without having to crop any piece of the image or distorting
it.
The next type of cropping is hard.
Croppy, harder cropping will resize an image to the exact dimensions you input it.
However, if an image begins to look distorted, it'll cropped the image to prevent any distortion.
So you're only getting a piece of that image.
If you scroll down, you'll see how that's done.
You just pass in.
True, and WordPress will cropped the image from the center.
If you're not looking for a centering position, you can configure the fourth parameter as an array
and specify where you'd like the cropping to begin.
If you scroll down the examples, you'll see the many ways images can be hard cropped.
So that's basically this article in a nutshell.
After this lecture is over, I highly encourage you to give it a good read.
All right.
So I'm going to set my fourth parameter to false as I want solved cropping.
I prefer my whole image viewable without any cropping the size maybe off than what I desired, but I'm
fine with that.
Usually the size difference is only by a few pixels.
I'd rather have an image off by a few pixels than have an image off by a hundred or even a thousand
pixels.
Now that our image size is registered, we can begin to use it in our own theme.
Open the content dash excerpt template.
Part file.
Look for where we outputted the featured image previously, we set this to for I'm going to replace
this with our custom image size and set this to Jiyu dash post dash image.
Refresh the home page and expect the element.
The signs may or may not be exactly the sizes we specified, but it's pretty close.
I'm going to open the single Templar file and do the same since the width of the post is the same as
the home page.
Look for where we outputted the thumbnail and use the custom size.
Having your own image size is great, but this will not always work.
Some users who install theme may be installing it on an existing WordPress site.
If they have existing images, they may not all be resized.
Only new images are resized and some old ones.
In this case, we have to force all images to be resized to prevent any problems.
Luckily, there's a plug and that does this go to the admin dashboard and navigate to plugins, add
new.
Then I want you to look for the plug and regenerate thumbnails, install and activate this plugin.
After installing this plugin, go to Tool's region thumbnails, the plugin will go through all the images
uploaded through WordPress and resize them all for you using the default settings and your own custom
sizes.
If a plugin also registers a size, it'll also resize the images according to that size.
All you have to do is click this button.
This may take a while, especially if you have a lot of images.
Just be patient.
After all the images have been resized, we are assured that our image size has been applied to all
images on the site.
This is a plug and we are going to recommend to the user when they install our theme will be going over
a how to bundle all the plug ins we installed so far with our theme in a future lecture.