The homepage features a list of posts submitted, however, I want to expand on this, I also want to
display recipe posts as well.
There are two solutions to accomplish this.
The first solution would be to create our own query, ignoring the main query.
However, that's a lot of work to do.
And we don't want to completely ignore the main query as other plugins may want to modify how it works.
Luckily, we can modify the main query to suit our needs.
This is the best solution and it's easy.
Inside the functions file at an action hook called pre get posts.
The function I want to call will be named Jiyu Modify home page query.
Inside the includes folder, create a file named Home Dash Query and define the function inside this
file.
Lastly, include this file.
This hook will be called when the main query is created, but it will not be executed at this point
since it's not being executed.
We have the opportunity to modify it as we please.
This function will be passed in an object called Query.
Whenever we work with the WP query class, we always created a new instance.
However, at this point, we already have an instance to modify a query.
After it's created.
We have to use a method called set, but we'll get to that in just a moment.
Something that you need to keep in mind is that this hook will always give you the main query for every
page, not just the home page.
Since this is the case, we have to use a conditional statement to check for two things.
We have to check if this query is for the home page using the IS home method.
Then we need to use the is main query method to check if this is the main query.
If both return true, then we'll modify query, I'm now going to call the set method and set the post
tight parameter to an array that contains the name of the post types I'd like to retrieve.
I want to get the post and recipe post types.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the WP query class again, you'll find
more information about these methods and properties that I'm using.
All right.
Now that we've modified the main query.
Let's check out the home page.
If you refresh the page, you should have both recipes and posts appearing.
That's all there is to it.
Before I am this lecture, I want to talk about a function called query posts, which you can find in
the resource section of this lecture.
There is a function that you can use to modify the main query, but I highly recommend you don't use
it.
If you take a look, you'll find this note from WordPress that says note this function will completely
override the main query and isn't intended for use by plugins or themes.
It's overly simplistic approach to modifying the main query can be problematic and should be avoided
wherever possible.
In most cases, there are better, more performance options for modifying the main query, such as via
the pre get posts action within WP query.
This must not be used within the WordPress loop.
Try your best not to use this function.
There are a lot of things in plugins out there that use this, but it's just bad practice to do so.