A lot of languages in the world are written from left to right, English, French and German are just
some examples of languages that are read and written from left to right.
There are languages out there that read left to right or RTL like Arabic.
In these cases, having your theme support, these languages can increase your reach and sales.
Unfortunately, there is a problem, which is most of our content by default.
Is Elter meaning left to right?
Actually, developing a theme or plugin for RTL sites requires that you set up a WordPress RTL installation.
This would take too much time.
Luckily, there is a plug in that someone developed that will help us test our site with RTL content,
go to the admin dashboard and navigate to plugins.
Add new search for the plug in called RTL Testor.
Install and activate it.
This plugin will add a new menu item on a Nalpas that will let you switch from Elter to RCL, switch
your site to RTL.
You'll notice things don't really change.
That's because we need to prepare the success that will move things from right to left.
This isn't a success course, so I won't be going over how the system works.
Be aware of that.
To make a site RTL, you have to access code that makes it appear RTL.
I've already created this access files that changed things.
To load these files, we have to register and interview them, open the includes the front end queued
up file to save some time.
I'm just going to paste the register of styles functions.
All these styles will make the necessary changes required to make the site and content arty already.
However, I don't want to include these files right away.
I want to check to see if the site is in RTR mode inside a conditional statement called The Function
is ARTlE.
If this function returns true, then that means the site is in RTL mode, if it is an RTL mode, then
I'm going to interview all the styles we just registered like so.
Now that we're loading the RCL styles, let's test it out, go ahead and refresh the page, the content
should now be reading from right to left, switch back to LTA to test if the site returns to normal.
After confirming the changes, you should be finished.
Adding RTL support is as easy as including the Cyesis files needed to make a site RTL.
You don't have to use any special functions or change the core.