One of the best things you could do is make your site accessible to people with disabilities, accessibility
is a pretty huge topic and there are a lot of steps you need to take to cover every area.
This election will be an overview of what you can do to make your team and plug an accessible to people
with disabilities before we make any changes.
It's important to understand the various kinds of disabilities you may come across.
Usually they can be categorized into four different topics visual such as blindness or colorblindness,
hearing such as deafness or being hard of hearing motor such as a lack of fine motor skills or difficulty
in using a mouse or mousepad cognitive such as learning difficulties, attention deficit disorders or
dyslexia.
It's usually up to the producer of the content to determine how to tackle these situations.
However, as developers, we should also take the time to help users navigate around the site.
The topic we're discussing is what HTML5 calls Aria Aria is short for accessible, rich Internet applications.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to where you can find more information about
this topic.
As you can see, there's a lot of information here and a lot of attributes.
You can say we won't be going over all of them.
This is just a brief introduction to this topic.
So let's get started.
One of the first steps you can take is to make the elements on your page more understandable.
For example, on the sidebar, I have the search widget, if you can recall, this is formatted using
these search form template to us.
It's clear what this will do.
However, that's because we can identify the search icon inside the button and know right away what
it means for people who can't or don't understand.
We will need more information, especially people who can't see this visually.
Open the search form template.
This button is entirely made up of HTML and no text in order to provide more information about this
element, we can apply an attribute called Ariah Dash label.
The value for this attribute can be anything you want.
Usually you would provide a short and concise description about this element.
I'm going to input search just like that.
If a user is using a device such as a screenwriter, then they'll easily be able to identify what this
button does.
You can apply the Ariah Dash label attribute to any element you like.
There are some exceptions, though.
Image tags don't need this attribute because there's the alt attribute that already does something similar
to the Ariah Dash label attribute.
Let's keep moving forward.
One of the biggest ways you can make your site navigable is by using rolls.
Rolls are a way to categorize the sections of your site.
They're very simple and straightforward to use.
If you look at the search form template, you'll notice we have an attribute called Roll.
By adding this attribute, you can specify the type of content that's inside this element.
This is a great and simple attribute to use.
It allows for users to skip around without having to go through each individual element.
Let's play with the raw, attribute some more.
Open the header template.
I'm going to apply the role attribute to the header element.
I'm going to set this to Baner.
The banner is the value you want to set to the element that contains the logo and navigation links,
go to the page that describes Ariah in detail.
If you click no to, you'll be taken to a list of all the values that role can be set to.
There are dozens of them available will only be using the more major ones.
So we told the user where the header is.
The next region we can set is the main content side bar and footer.
Open the single template next.
Applying the role attribute to the div tag with the class post content, I'm going to set this to mean.
This will tell the user this is where the main content is located.
I want to highlight that you should only apply this region once as a standard.
You usually only have one region for the main content.
You don't want to confuse the user.
Be conscious of where you define this region.
All right.
Let's keep going on open the sidebar template and apply the role.
Complimentary attribute.
This will specify the sidebar region, lastly, open the footer file and apply the roll content info
attribute to the footer element.
This is a weird name, but this is usually the name of the region for the footer, just like that,
we set all our regions.
There are so many more things we could do to make this thing accessible.
But I'm going to stop right here.
If you want to test a theme for accessibility, you can simply use a tool called wave web accessibility.
I'll provide a link to this.
In the resource section of this lecture, I'm going to give some final thoughts.
I find that adding accessibility to my themes is not a high priority.
I usually tackle accessibility last and I don't build upon it unless the product I'm building has high
usage.
It really is a case by case scenario.
It's up to you in the end, if you want to make your themes and plugins accessible, it's never a bad
idea to do so.