Let's get started with child themes.
If you heard of child themes but don't know what or how a child theme works, then this lecture is important
for you.
A lot of developers avoid child themes because WordPress doesn't really make it clear how to develop
or use child themes.
I don't want you to be one of those developers.
A child theme is extremely powerful and useful.
What makes it so useful is that you can modify an existing theme without having to worry about your
code becoming irrelevant or overwritten.
Back in the old days, if he wanted to modify a theme, then you'd have to directly edit the files.
Then when an update was available, you'd have to start all over again and keep track of all the edited
files and changes.
It was very annoying and time consuming.
When child themes were introduced, the whole process became so much easier because your code was never
overwritten and the theme was also not modified.
Now that you understand what child themes are, let's get started with creating one.
Go to WordPress dot org and go to the themes pages.
We're going to download a theme called M.H. Magazine Lite.
Then we're going to add this theme to our WordPress site by opening the themes folder and then dragging
the contents of the zip file into this folder like so.
Next, I'm going to copy this folder and I'm going to paste it in again, I'm going to reading this
folder and use the same name, except I'm going to append Dash child.
So I know that this is a child name.
WordPress doesn't require you to name a child.
Anyway, this is just how I prefer to do it and how I recommend you do it, open the child theme and
select every folder in files except the functions, style and screenshot files.
Delete these files.
I'm now going to open my editor and look for the trial theme, open to functions, file and delete all
this code.
I'm just going to leave an open tag for later.
We're going to do the same to the style access file, except you should not delete the headers that
come with it.
From here, we're going to make two changes.
The first change is the name of this theme.
I'm going to add a child theme to the name.
Once again, this is not required, but it makes it easier to tell which theme is the parent theme and
which is the child theme.
Next, we have to define a new property called template.
The value of this property will be the name of the parent themes folder name.
In our case, it would be MH Dash magazine Dash Light.
This value is case sensitive.
Be sure to set this value correctly after that, you're all done.
Let's go to the WordPress dashboard and navigate to appearance.
We now have to make magazine light themes, activate the child themed version and then try visiting
your site.
We don't get any errors, not even in the console, but the site isn't displaying correctly.
Why is that?
Well, it's pretty simple.
WordPress is loading the style access file because that's what the parent team does.
WordPress will load the functions, file from the parent theme and load the child themes function file.
Let's take a look at the parents function file.
If you scroll down a bit, the parent theme and cusa a file with the function get stylesheet.
You are right, this function will return the URAI to the current theme style access file.
Even if we're using a child theme, this would be the child's style access file and not the parents
style access file.
The parent style access contains all the main styles for the theme.
The question is how do we load both the parent styles and the child styles?
There are a couple solutions here, but the developer friendly.
One is by using action hooks, let's open the child things function file and add the action hook WP
NQ Scripts.
I'm going to be using an anonymous function, since we won't be doing much with this child thing.
I'm going to register the parents style to get the parent style access, we first have to use a function
called get template directory, you or I.
This function will get the director of the parent theme without the forward slash, since we're in the
parent team directory.
We can append the style X file name.
Next, I'm going to register the child theme style access file by using the function get stylesheet
uteri, which will return the URL of the current theme style access file.
Lastly, I'm going to interview both philes.
Refresh your site and you should now see that it's working properly just to make sure I'm going to open
the child's style access file and change the background color of the body to yellow.
Refresh the page.
That's absolutely hideous, but at least we know our styles are loading correctly.
If your changes aren't being loaded, you can press control five on your keyboard to force a refresh
with a clear cache for this page.
That's pretty much it for child themes.
From here, you can add anything you like.
If you were to create a file named for or for inside the child theme, then the child themes 404 template
will load instead of the parent themes version.
It's that simple, actually.
Let's try that really quick in the address bar of your browser.
Type in some random characters and you'll see the parent themes for a four template being loaded.
Let's create our version by creating a forum for PHP file inside the child theme and just add the text
for all four.
Let's refresh this page and you will now see the child themed template being loaded instead of the parents
version, WordPress is smart enough to know which template to use your child themes.
Templates will be loaded over the parent themes templates.
You're now free to overwrite anything from the parent theme.