Throughout this course, we've been bundling various plug ins with our theme.
We even have a custom plugin developed forcing the user to manually download each plug and would be
a pain.
It would be nice if the user could download all the plug ins at once.
We could just download it and then include it with Pete.
But this would be inefficient.
We would have to manually update each plug and every time one of them gets updated, it would also bloat
our plug in heavily.
Can you imagine having to manage your plugging along with 10 other plug ins?
It would be disastrous.
The more efficient solution would be to notify the user of the required plug ins and then help them
install those plug ins with a simple UI that would take a lot of code to write.
Luckily, there's a solution that helps with bundling plug ins and making the process so much smoother.
And that solution is called TGF plug in activation and the resource section.
I provide a link to this class.
This class handles a lot of the work for us and it does exactly what we need.
It'll check the user's WordPress site and their plug ins.
It'll check if the site contains the plug ins, need it.
If they don't have those plug ins, then it'll allowed a warning notice and instruct the user to install
those plug ins.
It will also provide a UI for installing those plug ins.
It's a very lightweight class.
It's just one file, so you don't have to worry about your theme being bloated.
Let's get started.
First, we need to download this file, go to the download section.
You're allowed to download this plugin without any modifications.
But there's this handy little generator that takes care of modifying the plug in to suit our needs.
I'm going to set this to work with our theme and for the fields.
I'm going to input our theme settings like so.
Feel free to follow along after setting up this field click generate, you should receive a zip file.
There are a lot of files inside the zip file, but the only file we care about is the class dash TKM
Dash plugin dash activation page PDF file.
Let's open the Udemy theme folder and navigate to the includes folder.
Create a new folder called Lives and drop this file into this folder.
Open your code editor and required this file from within the functions file.
We used the require one function instead of the include function, because this is what the developers
recommend.
So will heed their advice.
Keep in mind that this class can also be used in plugins.
This can possibly cause errors as we may get errors related to redefining an existing class.
Luckily, we don't have to do anything because the developers have taken care of this for us.
If you were to open this class, you'll find the classes wrapped inside this conditional statement.
This statement will check of this class has already been defined.
If it has been, it won't be redefined.
Like I said before, this is a great piece of code to use in your theme or plug in.
All right.
Now we can begin using this class inside the zip file.
There is another file called Exampled that provides a very detailed example on how to use this class.
It's neatly commented and all examples are clear after this course, I highly recommend you take the
time to look over this example file so that you can get the most out of it.
The first step we need to take is to use an action hook called T.G. MPLX Register.
The function to call is Jiyu register required plugins.
Create a file inside the includes folder called Register Dash Plug INS and define the function here.
Include this file from the functions file.
We're first going to create an array called plug ins.
This will be an array of plug ins.
Our theme requires each plug and we want to require will also be an array.
First, we need to determine which plug ins we want to come.
Bundled with our theme, go to the plug ins admin page.
We have some plug ins here that are only for development purposes, so we don't want to bundle those.
I'm going to deactivate some and will go over the ones we do want to bundle.
All right, so I just deactivated some plugins here are the plug ins I want to come bundled with our
theme and since integration WP Quad's Buddy Press Recipe, Regenerate Thumbnails, Woo Commerce, WordPress,
Popular Posts and WP subtitle.
Let's start with the WP Kwon's plugin.
To add a plug into the array, you just add another array.
The array must have certain keys so TGF knows which plug in to grab from the WordPress plugin repository.
The first key is the name of this plugin.
We can grab this from the plugin page, which is ad sense.
Plug in WP Kwon's.
The next to said is the slug, this would be the plug ins, unique dorelle from the WordPress repository.
You can grab this from the euro of the plug and page.
You don't need the whole euro.
Just this bit that says quick dash, add cents.
Dash reloaded.
Lastly, we can set the required key, we have two options here, if we set this to true, then this
class will tell the user of this plug in is required for the thing to work.
If false, then WordPress will recommend this plug in and said it's up to you whether a plug in is required
or recommended.
I'm going to set this to false.
I'm going to pause the video and do this for the other plugins, except for the custom recipe plugins
as those require different settings.
All right, so I added the plug ins, all I did was I went to each plug and repository page and grabbed
the title and your URL from that page, the last plug, and we need to include is the custom plug.
And we developed this plug in is not available anywhere.
There are two solutions here.
We can upload our plug into the repository, but that takes a long time.
And I just want this plug in to be exclusive to this theme.
Luckily, GM is also willing to look for plug ins in other locations like inside your own theme.
Here's what I want you to do.
Zip up the recipe, plug in and cut the zip file.
Next, open the unity theme folder, create a folder called Plugins and paste it inside here.
Now we just have to let them know about this plug in, add another array and set the name to recipe.
The slug should be set to the name of the plugin folder, which is recipe.
The next key is a must, which is source, this path can be a system path or an HDP.
You, Earl, I'm going to use the function, get template directory and then append the path to the
recipe.
Plug in zip file.
Lastly, I'm going to set the required key to true.
Next, we need to create an array called config.
This will contain the settings for the class, there are a lot of settings we can set, but the following
are the only ones we care about.
Idy this is a unique ID.
Keep in mind that we can use this class multiple times.
We want to make sure that these plug ins and settings are related to our theme only.
I'm going to set this to you.
To me.
Menu, this is the menu slug that WordPress will use for displaying the UI, the recommended path is
to dash install dash plugins.
Parents slug, this will be the page to use for displaying the UI once again, it's recommended we use
the theme Stop PHP file.
Capability who can install and activate the plugins will be using the edit the options capability.
Has notices a boolean value which will determine whether or not the admin will be notified about the
required plugins, we want to set this to true.
Dismissable whether or not the notice messages can be dismissed, set this to true as we don't want
to annoy users with irremovable notices.
The very last step is to call a function called TKG MPLX, this function has two parameters, which
is the plugins to install and then the configuration settings.
That's it.
Let's go to the plug ins page.
We should see nothing changed so far, but let's see, activate Buddy Press for a moment.
You'll now see a notice telling us that the team recommends Buddy Press as an activated plug in.
Let's click install plug ins.
We now have this table of plug ins to install along with additional information.
Activate Buddy Press again.
Just like that, we were able to install and activate a third party, plug in with very little code
and work.
Now, we don't have to worry about keeping track of this plug in as WordPress will do it for us all,
thanks to the NPR class.