Developing a theme can be really fun, but as you may have saw throughout this course, I'm all about
efficiency and organization.
Creating a theme from scratch can be time consuming to speed things up.
It's not a bad idea to use a starter template that takes care of all the boring stuff and templates.
Then you can just take it from there and customize it.
Here are some suggestions I recommend the best free starter template is called Underscores Underscores.
It's developed by a bunch of fantastic developers who all agree on how theme should be developed.
The people who develop this starter theme are the same people who work on the word press corps itself.
Every single line of code in this template has a purpose and is carefully inputted for the best practices.
If you were to download this template and view some of the code.
You'll notice that they organize their code a bit differently.
That's perfectly fine.
You can organize your code anywhere you like.
You could do it the way I taught you.
Or you could use someone else's organization system, or you can just organize it the way you like.
There was no right or wrong answer here.
I recommend you download this theme and play around with it a bit.
It's well documented and easy to understand.
Another solution is under strap, which is the underscore theme, but with more features.
Specifically, it has bootstrapped for included.
If you like bootstrap, then this might be something you'll want to use.
Next up is Sage by Roots.
This starter theme is for hardcore developers.
Out of all the recommendations I provide, this one is the most advanced.
It goes beyond the basic PVP includes statements and has support for bootstrap, for blade templates
and so much more.
This is something I want to go over with you in the future.
Let me know on the comments if you'd be interested in a section for this starter theme.
I truly believe it would be beneficial to anyone.
An alternative is called Genesis by Studio Press.
This is the most popular premium starter template available.
I hear nothing but good things about this template.
It's about sixty dollars, but it comes with so many features and it comes with functions that would
be useful to you for team development.
The support is top notch and the code is well written.
I highly recommend this if you need help with theme development.
Another starter template is from Wu Commerce called Storefront.
Storefront is a starter template that comes with e-commerce integration out of the box.
It provides good practices and support.
I encourage you to explore any of these themes to learn more about theme development.