We're going to start things off by creating a theme, as I stated previously, this course does not
focus on most of the HTML access and JavaScript provided to you.
This is because WordPress is very flexible when it comes to developing themes.
With that said, I already have a static template ready.
You can download this template in the resource section of this lecture.
This template was built with version four of Bootstrap.
I've done nothing to this template that makes it WordPress ready.
I will walk you through every step to convert it from a static template into a WordPress theme.
If you have a template ready, then feel free to use it.
You don't have to make any access or HTML changes at this moment.
Any kind of template will work.
If you're new to WordPress development, then I recommend you use the template I provide.
Let's take a look at some of the pages.
Let's you the home page.
As you can see, everything is pretty standard.
We have a header puter sidebar and a list of posts.
Everything that you see here will be turned into a fully functional theme while the design is simple
and clean.
Don't let that fool you.
We're going to make this thing very flexible.
Now that we have an idea of what we're going to create, it's time to start coding, open the text editor
of your choice and point it to the WordPress directory we installed in the previous lecture.
Inside the WordPress installation navigate to WP dash content slash themes.
This is where WordPress will search for theme files from the start.
WordPress has already pre-package some themes for you.
We want to keep our theme separated from the rest of the themes.
So create a new folder called Udemy.
It's required that you create a folder for your theme.
This is so themes don't conflict with each other.
It's also great for organization inside this folder.
We will have to create two files.
The first file is styled that success and the second file is indexed.
These are the only two files required by WordPress to create a theme, the style access file is where
we will place or file header information.
A file header is just a comment block placed at the very top of the style that Keith's file that describes
our theme.
Let's open this file and create a file header in the resource section.
I provide a link to more information about the file header.
The file header is a blocked comment placed at the top of the file that has meta information about a
theme or plug.
I'll explain more in just a moment, but let's see this in action.
Scroll down to the theme file, header, example, section copy and paste this into the style that CSFs
file.
I'm going to remove most of this info except the theme name change this value to you.
To me.
That's it, this is the absolute minimum requirements for a theme, go to your WordPress admin dashboard
and navigate to appearance themes and empty blog with the theme name, you should appear.
You can actually activate this theme and start using it.
If you did everything right, then you should receive no errors.
Let's go to the front end of the site.
You will see an empty page.
However, WordPress throws no errors because we did everything required.
If you take a look at the source code, then you will find that WordPress added absolutely nothing because
that's our team's job.
As you can see, WordPress gives you complete control over your theme.
Let me prove this even further.
Open the index top file and add the text.
Hello, world.
Refresh the front page and you will now see it outputted WordPress is very smart and will automatically
load this file without us having to write any logic.
The index top file can be thought of as the default template for WordPress.
There are various templates we can create, but we'll cover that later.
I'm going to temporarily switch back to the theme.
Twenty seventeen.
Then I'm going to delete the index file.
I'm going to refresh the admin things page and you'll notice that the broken theme section appears below.
It's telling us that the index template file is missing.
WordPress is capable of finding out this information, even though this team is inactive.
The absolute minimum requirement for creating a WordPress theme is the style that iest index files and
the file header with just the name of a theme.
I'm going to create the index file again so we don't see this broken theme section.
Let's go back to the file header in the style that file.
Let me go over what's going on.
When WordPress retrieves a list of themes in your WordPress installation, it'll go to the WP dash content
slash themes folder.
Each theme should have its own folder, and WordPress will go through each one and look for a file name
style that counts.
If this file is available, then WordPress will scan the contents of this file and look for something
called a file header.
If a file header is available, WordPress will then extract each piece of information from that header.
The format is the name followed by a colon and then the value.
The data inside this comment is what WordPress calls meta information for theme's.
The only thing you need is the theme name.
I'm going to rehab the meta information we previously removed.
Let's go over this one by one.
The thing, Urai is a link to where users can view where your theme can be found.
Officially, I'm going to remove this piece of information, feel free to keep or remove it as well.
The author is the name of the creator of this theme.
This can be your own personal name, or if you're on a team, then the name of your team.
I'm going to set this to Jack, the author.
Uteri is the URL to your own personal site or your URL to your team's site.
I'm going to set this to https coingate you to me dot com.
The description is a brief summary about your theme, let's get this to a simple bootstrap WordPress
theme.
The version is the current version of this theme, since this is a brand new theme, will be setting
this to one point zero.
You can use whatever version schematic you want.
WordPress doesn't force you to stick any specific version schematic.
The license is simply the name of the license you'll be using.
I'm going to leave this as is for now, will be going over licenses later in this course.
The license uteri is the URL to where the user can find more information about the themes.
License the tags is the comma separated list of words that describe your theme.
This piece of information is used by WordPress as theme repository to help users find your theme.
If you plan on uploading your theme to WordPress dog, then setting this piece of information is important.
I don't plan on uploading this to the repository so we can remove this.
The last property we can set is the text domain.
The text domain is very important when it comes to translating our theme.
You can think of the text domain as a unique idea for our translations.
It's common practice to set the text domain to the same name as your folder.
In our case, we're going to send it to you.
Me, I promise you will be going more over what the text domain does and its role in WordPress development
later in the course.
For now, just know that if you want to make your themes or plugins translate ready, then set the text
domain to something unique right below.
There's this small bit of text.
You do not have to add this bit of information.
Authors usually use this space to add in more info about the theme, such as license info or developer
notes.
WordPress will not bother scanning this part of the file, so you do not have to worry about it.
I'm going to remove this bit.
Let's go back to the Themes admin page and refresh the page, you can click on the theme and you will
now see some of our information displayed.
As you can tell, so far, WordPress handles a lot for us.
If you'd like to know more about file headers, then I highly suggest you read the Codex page I provided
earlier.
This page details what metadata you can create.
You'll notice that it provides information about creating plug ins.
I want you to ignore this for now, as will be developing plug ins in a future section.
There's one last thing I want to do before I in this election.
While not required, WordPress will search for a file called Screenshot Dot PNG.
This file is basically a screenshot of your theme that will be displayed on the admin side of WordPress
and the resource section.
I provide a screenshot you can use for our theme.
Upload it to the Yuta missing directory we just created.
You can now refresh the themes admin page and you will now see our screenshot being displayed.
You can create your own screenshot if you like.
The recommended size for a screenshot is 880 by 660.
However, you should double the size for retina devices.