Let's take a look at how to add styles and scripts through our hook.
It's pretty straightforward.
There are only two steps required to add styles to our pages.
The first step is to register the style.
Registering styles simply means that you're telling WordPress that you have a style sheet and you would
like WordPress to know its location, along with other details.
In the resource section of this lecture, I'll provide a link to learn all about registering styles.
In order to register a style, we need to use the WP register style function under the notes section.
You'll see we're using this function correctly because it says Use the WP and Qs scripts action to call
this function.
Calling it outside of an action can lead to problems.
Since we're already doing that, it's safe to assume we can use this function.
This function has two required parameters.
The first parameter is the handle name.
The handle name can be thought of as a unique name or ID.
For reference, the second parameter is the source to the stylesheet.
Let's go back to the NQ function and call the WP Register style function.
Now we have to pass in a handle for the first parameter, if we go back to the index template, you'll
see we have quite a few stylesheets being loaded.
The first stylesheet is a Google font.
So let's call this handle Jiyu Google fonts.
Just like functions, it's also common practice to prefix our handles with some initials for the second
parameter, lets pass in the euro.
We're loading this font from a sudden so we can just paste the URL like so as a string.
Next up is the Bootstrap Docs file, you'll need to call the WP register style function again, just
like before.
I'm going to use the same naming convention.
The name will be Jiyu Bootstrap.
Unlike the Font's, this file is located within our theme directory, will use WordPress to help us
generate a Eurail to this file.
There's actually a function that will always point to the current theme directory.
This makes it easier on us as we don't have to perform checks.
If the owner of the site changed the name of the theme directory right at the top of this function,
I'm going to create a variable named Urai and set its value to the function.
Get the file.
You are right.
You do not have to pass in anything and you don't have to include any file to get this function to work,
this function is loaded and defined for you by WordPress.
You may notice this function has a similar name to the get the file path function.
The difference between these two functions is that you are riperton will actually get the web URL the
non-driver and get the system path with this dirigibles set.
I'm going to pass it into the function right after this.
I'm going to append the path relative to our theme folder, which as assets exists, bootstrap access.
The first two parameters are required.
These next three are optional, but the last two aren't used as often.
The third parameter is what's most important.
The third parameter is an array of dependencies.
Sometimes your styles may depend on another style sheet to load.
You simply pass in an array of panel names, and WordPress will take care of loading those style sheets
before this one.
If WordPress doesn't find a style sheet, then this style sheet will not be loaded.
For example, if I wanted the Google font to load before the style sheet, then I could pass in the
handle name like so I'm not too worried about dependencies so we can leave this out.
Now that we have that finished, I'm going to register the rest of the styles.
It's the same as before.
Post the video if you need to have what I have, if we refresh the page, you'll notice that this won't
work just yet.
We've only registered our styles.
Now we must tell WordPress we would like to add it to our page.
We now have to use a function called WP and Q style.
I've also included a link to this function in the resource section of this lecture.
This function only has one required parameter, which is the handle name of the style we registered
earlier.
You'll notice the other parameters are similar to the WP register style function.
However, these are only available just in case you forget to register a style.
You should always register a style.
Though the difference between registering and cueing a file is that registering will tell WordPress
about a stylesheet and make it available to be called later on.
While in queuing will instruct WordPress to load our stylesheet onto the page right away.
You will not always want to in Kiwa style on every page as it is inefficient.
There's also plugins out there that will sometimes scan registered siles and perform actions such as
modifying and concatenating style sheets together.
So it's best to register first, then NQ.
Let's nq the font stylesheet right after the register functions called the function WP and Kusile and
pass in the handle name Jiyu Google Fonts.
Let's do this for all the stylesheets.
All right, we're almost done.
I promise there's only one last thing we need to do in order for all this to work.
If we go back to the index template, you'll notice we haven't told WordPress where to load our stylesheets.
Our template is pure HTML.
WordPress doesn't magically scan our files and insert everything in the appropriate place.
We have to tell WordPress where to load our files.
So let's do that.
Go to the head section of the template.
We are going to replace the stylesheets and call the function WP head.
The WP head function is a function defined by WordPress, this function simply tells WordPress that
this is the spot where themes and plugins can NQ their stylesheet and script files.
Let's refresh the page and we should see it working.
If you see something similar to what I see, then you're good to go.
Let's double check some things and open the console.
You'll notice we get a lot of errors, but we'll fix this soon.
What I want you to look for is any 404 errors related to stylesheets.
If you don't see any, then that means you loaded everything correctly.
We can now begin adding scripts.
Adding a script file is almost the same as adding a stylesheet.
However, unlike stylesheets, we can load script files in the footer.
If we take a look at the template, we have all our scripts being loaded into the footer, just like
adding files inside the head tag.
We also have to call a function from the footer to instruct WordPress where to load files in the footer
at the very bottom of the template right before the closing body tag called the WP footer function.
This function allows our theme and other plug ins to load their files into the footer.
All right, now that we have that set up, let's go to the NQ function and start adding our scripts.
Just like stylesheets, we have to register our scripts in the resource section of this lecture.
I provide a link to the WP Register, a script function.
Let's take a look at what WordPress has to say about this function.
As you can see, only the first two parameters are required and they're basically similar to the WP
register style function.
Back inside the index template, we include a script called Plugins.
Let's add this script to the footer through the NQ function.
Let's call the WP Register script function and pass in a handle name.
The handle name will be Jiyu plugins.
I don't have to worry about name conflicts here because stylesheets and scripts are stored separately,
the second parameter is the source.
It's the same as last time.
You just use the URAI variable and append the path.
The path would be assents exact plug ins, James.
Now, in most cases, you always want to load your scripts in the footer to allow our content to be
loaded before our scripts.
So how do we make our script load in the footer?
Let's go back to the documentation and look at the WP Register script function again.
You'll notice that the fit parameter determines whether or not a script is loaded in the footer by default.
It doesn't.
We have to pass in a true boolean value so that we can load the script inside the flitter.
Let's go back to the function and start using this, the third parameter is this scripts dependencies.
In some cases your scripts will depend on the functionality of another script.
You have to pass in an array of handling things for WordPress to make sure those scripts are loaded
first before this one.
In our case, we don't have to worry about dependencies, so we'll just passing an empty array.
The fourth parameter is the version of the script.
If you update your script frequently, this can be a useful parameter to say this is because a lot of
WordPress sites have cache enabled by updating the version, you'll force WordPress to load the latest
version of the script.
I'm going to set this to false as I don't really need to worry about versioning for this script.
The whole point of this part of the lecture is to load the script into the footer, which is the fifth
and final parameter.
All you have to do is pass in.
True, that's it.
Let's include the plugins file using the WP and Qs script function and see if it loads on the page.
You'll notice that WordPress also loads its top now bar for users who are logged in after confirming
that it loads, why don't you pause the video and load the rest of the scripts?
Be sure to remove the script tags after you include them.
All right, so I basically just registered and include the rest of our scripts, you'll notice that
I also removed their inclusions from the footer.
If I refresh the page, you'll see that everything is loaded correctly except for one thing, Jacquier.
We also get a couple of errors inside the console thing that Jake query isn't loaded or defined in the
NQ file.
I didn't bother registering or even skewing it, but one.
Let's go back to the WordPress documentation and take a look at the WP Register a script function on
the contents sidebar.
I want you to click core registered scripts.
You'll be taken to a part of the page that tells you that WordPress registers a number of scripts that
are commonly used by developers.
WordPress automatically registers a large number of scripts libraries like Jaquie or UI and underscore
if we scroll down long enough, you'll find a query.
So all we have to do is in queue this script before and cueing anything else.
Let's do this now.
Refresh the page, and if you did everything right, then you should see that any errors related to
GAO query are now gone.
Now, before I end this lecture, I want to say one very important thing.
Never, ever override word press's default scripts, including query.
There are some developers out there that like to include their own version of jury, which may seem
great and all, but it's really not a good idea.
You aren't the only developer using GE query.
If developers constantly use their own versions of scripts, then this could break a client site and
can cause hours of debugging.
It's so much better to just use a J.A.G. version that's consistent throughout the site.
Inside the HTML template, we use a different version of GE query, but that's only for the email template
and not meant to be used for the WordPress theme at all.
So please don't try and override WordPress query.