Our site is starting to come along really well.
All we need to do is make it more dynamic and fix a lot of the links before we can do this.
We need to have some dummy content setup so let's add some dummy content navigate to the dashboard and
let's add a new plugin in search for the plugin called faker press this plug will take care of generating
dummy content for your site install and activate it.
All right.
So once activated you'll see a new menu item pop up called faker press.
Let's start by creating some users first.
I'm going to create just two users and I'm going to set their roles to offer click generate.
And you should see a success message afterwards.
If the two users were created next I want to create some terms.
Even though we haven't discussed what terms are all you need to know is that they are words and phrases
attached to a post.
I'm going to set the quantity between five and 10 the name size will be between 1 and 3.
The taxonomy is will be set to categories and tags that should do it.
Click generate and that should generate some terms.
Lastly let's create some posts under press posts.
This will allow us to generate some posts and the quantity put 15 and 20.
Change the date to last 15 days.
Set the author feel to all users including the admin.
A lot of these fields are fine as is.
Scroll down to the taxonomy section and select all the terms we created previously
set the rate to 100.
Leave the rest of the fields as is and click generate.
This may take a while for some of you as images are being downloaded for preview.
Hopefully you will receive a success message once that's finished.
Let's view the posts generated.
We don't need to generate any more content from faker press for now so I'm going to deactivate this
plugin let's create one page called about us.
Insert a few words and then publish it.
Lastly let's create a menu.
The menu links should be right under appearance but you'll notice that it's unavailable to us.
This is because we need to tell WordPress that our theme supports menus.
Let's learn how to do that in the next lecture.