Right now, I'm on the documentation page for the Register NAV menu function, the first step to getting
menus to work is to register that just like styles and scripts, WordPress requires you to register
your menus before you can display that this function will help you with that.
As you can see, there's only two required parameters, which is the location and a short description.
The location can be thought of as a special ID.
If we scroll down further, you'll find that WordPress provides an example and this example, WordPress
uses an action hook called after set up theme.
This is the hook WordPress recommends for this function as instructed.
Let's open the functions file just like last time.
We're going to organize our code under the hooks section.
I'm going to call the add action function.
According to the documentation, the most appropriate hook we should use is called after set up theme.
This hook is called When our theme is loaded internally, I don't mean that the page itself is loaded,
but all the functions you defined inside the functions file is loaded.
The function that will be called is Jiyu set up within this function isn't defined.
So we'll have to do that now.
Create a file inside the includes folder called Set Up.
And then I want you to define the function.
Lastly, including.
The reason we aren't creating this file inside the front folder is because some of the functions will
be using here will be applied to both the front end and the back end.
Now that the function is ready, let's call the register now.
Menu function.
We need to provide this function a location and description, I'm going to call this menu primary and
give it a simple description of primary menu.
Before I continue, I'm going to wrap my description inside a function that doesn't really have a proper
name, but it's called By Typing to underscores this function is a special function created by WordPress.
It allows for text to be translated into various languages.
We haven't gone over translations yet, but I'll give you a quick rundown.
WordPress comes with various functions for translating strings, but double underscore function is just
one of the most commonly used ones.
When we start talking about translations, I'll show you the various functions available.
For now, let's focus on this one function.
This function has two parameters.
The first parameter is the string you would like to translate.
The second parameter is the text domain.
This translation is using earlier we talked about text domains when we created the file header.
The text domain is basically the name of your theme folder.
In our case, this would be you to me.
So what does the text domain actually do?
Well, first of all, your theme won't be the only file that has translations.
Users might have various plugins activating those plugins will most likely have their own translations.
You can think of a text domain as an ID.
If we pass in our text domain, WordPress will know you want to use a translation from our theme and
not some other plugin loaded anyway.
We actually have and created a translation file and we won't be doing so right now.
If WordPress doesn't find a translation and WordPress just won't translate the string and return the
original string, you don't have to translate every string, but I highly recommend it.
So you're plug in or theme can be used by the whitens audience?
Possible.
All right.
That's it for now.
If you didn't understand, that's fine.
I'll be going more in-depth in a future lecture.
Now that we've registered our menu, let's display it in the resources section of this lecture.
I have included a link to a function called WP NAV menu.
Let's take a look at it.
As you can see, WordPress has thoroughly documented this function.
It's very powerful and flexible.
We won't be going over every bit here since we don't need to use all the options available to us for
our theme.
Basically, what this function does is generate a menu for us and outputs it onto wherever we call it.
Let's get started with using it.
Open the index template.
I want you to search for the navigation tag with the IDE primary menu right above.
It should be a comment that says primary navigation.
Inside this element, you'll find an unordered list with a comment above it that says Main menu.
I want you to delete this menu like so.
Next, open some tags and create a conditional statement.
We're going to check if the current theme has a particular menu, you can do this by calling the has
now menu function.
We can then pass in the name of location, which is primary, if this menu exists, then we can continue
on inside this conditional statement.
We're going to call the WP now menu function.
This function can be called as is, and WordPress will just use its default settings, but we don't
want that.
We have some things we would like to specify.
This function only has one parameter, which is an array.
So let's create an array.
And in this array, the first item will be theme location.
This key's value should be the location name we use in the register nav menu function, the name of
the menu we registered was called Primary, so this key's value should be primary.
Next, let's define the container.
The container is simply a tag that is wrapped around the Navigations HTML WordPress will generate the
HTML for our menu.
The HTML generated is simply ULE and elai tags or simply known as an unordered list.
The container key simply asks if we want to wrap this unordered list with a div or nav tag.
Depending on your needs, you can use either.
However, our theme is using bootstrap and we already have our navigation wrapped with a div tech,
so we don't want either.
Let's pass in false.
Therefore, WordPress won't wrap our unordered list with a div or Navteq, there's another key we can
set, which is the menu Klasky.
This key allows you to access classes to the ultimate I'm assuming you may want to do this if you're
using your own template to add multiple classes, you just spaced the class names like.
So class one, class two.
For this thing, we don't need to use this key, so I'm going to get rid of it.
We're almost done.
The next key I want to set is the fallback CBG.
In some cases, your users will not have any menu setup.
This is usually true on a fresh installation of WordPress.
This key allows you to call a function to display a default menu.
You can set this to false if you don't want to display a default menu or HTML.
Lastly, we can define the depth.
The depth is how many submenus the user can have currently my success only allows for a depth of four.
If you want to have more depth, you can do so by adding additional access.
If you want to allow an unlimited number of submenu items, then you can set this to zero.
That's it.
Now, if we refresh the page, it won't work as expected.
This is because we haven't created a menu yet.
Let's do that now inside the WordPress dashboard, go to appearance menus and then create a menu.
Take quick notice of the menu settings section, you'll see that there's a some section called Display
Location.
This lists all the display locations we registered in our set up file.
Let's assign this menu to the primary menu.
I'm only going to have the about page assigned to this menu after saving the menu, go back to the front
end and refresh.
You'll notice the about menu item being generated properly.
You can click this if you like, and it will work, but it won't display.
The content will fix that very soon if you haven't already removed the static HTML for the menu.
Let's recap what's going on.
First, we tell WordPress that our theme has a location for menus by using the register, now menu function.
Lastly, we tell WordPress where to load the menu in our template by using the WP now menu function.
Something I want you to note is that you don't have to call these functions from within the hook.
These functions can be called directly inside the functions file.
However, I highly advise that you use hooks whenever possible.
This is so only code that should be called is called in appropriate locations.
If you were to stuff your functions, file with loads of code, then you make it hard to debug it since
so much is going on.
Another thing I want to note is that in the WordPress menu page, you'll see WordPress outputted the
phrase primary menu for the display location.
Earlier I told you about translations and how they're performed.
WordPress acknowledged that this phrase can be translated and tried to translate it.
Since we don't have any translation set.
WordPress then outputted the string as is.
I just wanted you to notice that before I in this lecture, I want you to be aware of how the markup
and accesses for my menu.
This is not a bootstrap menu.
This is a custom made access menu.
Despite Bootstrap coming with its own classes for menus, I decided not to use it.
Now, this is just a success preference and not related to WordPress.
But that being said, bootstrap requires that you set up a menu with certain classes.
Unfortunately, the WP nav menu function is pretty limited when it comes to adding classes to certain
menus.
And these cases you have to use something called a walker.
Walker's are a programming concept and not specific to WordPress.
Only walkers are a way to go through an array and if those arrays have arrays inside of them, it'll
go through that too.
It just keeps going and going until every value has been looped through.
Creating a walker can be fairly complex.
Luckily, there's a developer who has solved the problem of creating a walker with bootstrap markup
in the resources section.
On this lecture, I provide a link to the WP Bootstrap NAV Walker class.
I won't be going through this as it's not necessary for our theme.
However, it's fairly easy to implement.
All you have to do is include the file and then modify the WP nav menu function in the examples below.
All right.
In the next lecture, will focus on the header and footer next.