As this course progresses, will be creating multiple templates.
Keep in mind that the index template is just the default template WordPress uses when there isn't a
suitable template to be found.
Our theme should be consistent.
And so therefore the header footer and sidebar should look the same.
Our templates can get pretty big if we just copy and paste our header and footers.
It would also be a pain to have to edit each template every time he made a change to the header.
Luckily, WordPress provides a solution by providing a couple of functions for including different sections
of our template.
Let's create the required files first.
First, we have to create a file called Headers in our theme's folder.
It's very important that you give the file this name as this is the name WordPress will search for when
trying to include your header from the index template, let's cut everything from the dark tag to the
closing header tags and then paste it into the header file.
Next, let's create a photo op file.
Just like before, we are forced to name it this by WordPress from the index template, cut everything
from the bottom of the file to the opening tag of the footer comment, then paste it into the footer
file like so.
This will leave us with the section tag, with the ID of content.
All right, now all we have to do is include our files at the very top of the index template.
Call the function, get header.
This function will look for a file called header and include it at the very bottom of the file, call
the function, get footer.
Just like the header function, this function will look for a file called Footrot, the HP, I'm going
to format template so it's easier to read.
Once that's done, refresh the page and see if everything is working properly, if you see no errors,
then that means you did everything right.
Let's go over how these functions work.
These two functions will look for files named headers and footers within the themes directory, respectively.
I want you to be aware we're not completely forced to name our files, header up and it up.
Let's say we had a header called Header Dash V 2.0 and we wanted to use this header for post templates
specifically.
Well, all you have to do is pass in the name the two and WordPress will then search for a file called
Header Dash V to.
Don't worry about free pending the word header or appending the extension P WordPress takes care of
this for you.
This way you can have various headers.
These same rules apply to the get futer function for this course will only have one header and footer.
So we don't need to pass in anything to these functions.
All right.
We're almost done here.
I want to do one thing, which is to allow any plugins or WordPress itself to add classes to the body
tag.
By doing this, you can take advantage knowing which features are active on the site with your success.
Let's explore how this is done.
The first step is to open the header template and inside the body tag called the Function Body Class.
This function will add an attribute called class and then output some classes, I have some classes
I'd like added which are the No Dasch transition and stretched classes.
Let's refresh the page and then let's use the developer tool to see what's going on.
Right.
Click and select, inspect anywhere on the page.
What you should be viewing is the elements tab.
This tab allows you to view the HTML of the current page in real time, meaning if any changes were
made inside this template while the user is browsing than the HTML will update accordingly and vice
versa.
If you take a look at the body class, then you'll notice that a few classes have been added that weren't
there before.
WordPress automatically loads these classes for you so you can apply appropriate success.
For example, the admin dashboard class should appear if you're logged in.
However, if I log out, then this class will disappear.
After logging out, you will see the admin bar class disappear.
This is really great.
As you can apply a certain style links to the page depending on the classes added to the body.
I'm going to log back in.
As I stated from the beginning, I did not make any changes to my template to prepare for WordPress,
so even though these classes are loaded, there aren't any styles in my files that takes advantage of
these classes.
Using these classes is completely optional.
Even though we aren't using these functions, there are plug ins that do.
This is an important point I want to make.
Some features you add aren't just for WordPress or yourself.
Sometimes you'll want to add features so plug ins can extend how WordPress functions.
I'm going to remove the body class function for a moment.
Refresh the page and you'll notice our site is a little different from before, if you take a look at
the body tag, then you'll notice some classes still appear.
WordPress has a fallback.
It will use some JavaScript code to add some classes, but most of the original classes are gone.
To prove this further, you can right click and select view page source and you'll notice the body tag
has no classes applied.
I'm going to revamp the body class function because of its usefulness.
Let's refresh the page one more time, and all the S.O.S classes we had before should reappear just
to recap what's going on.
All we did was split up the index template.
We put the header and footer into their own respective templates.
Then we modified the body tag so WordPress can generate some classes.
I'm going to add a link to this function in the resource section of this lecture.
We can now begin working on the sidebar.