I'm currently on the WP query Coatex page, I'll provide a link to this in the resource section of this
lecture.
Here's what WordPress has to say about this class.
WP query is a class defined in WP.
Dash includes a query that deals with the intricacies of a Post's request to a WordPress blog.
The WP Dash blog dash header gives the WP query object information defining the current request and
then query determines what type of query it's dealing with and fetches the request and posts.
It retains a lot of information on the request, which can be pulled at a later date.
This class, which we will go over soon, is probably one of the most famous and most used classes by
WordPress developers.
It's used because it's so simple to get started with.
It provides a lot of options and it's documented quite heavily.
This class lets you interact with the database by grabbing posts.
It seems simple, but posts are very complex and they're designed.
This class is meant to help you get past that complexity.
You may have noticed that WordPress provides a plethora of functions for interacting with the database
where you're allowed to write custom SQL queries.
But that's only when we need complete control.
At this point, we don't need to use custom queries, but I promise you we will go over how to do that
in a future lecture.
For now, the functions and classes provided are tailored solutions for the most common problems we
have.
The WP query class is the exact solution WordPress uses to query for posts that are loaded in our templates.
You'll notice soon enough that the methods are similar to the functions we've used so far.
Before we begin, I want to point out that there's a documentation page for the WP query class on the
developer site.
I'll provide a link to it in the resource section of this lecture.
This page is the more updated version and will soon take over the Codex version.
I showed you the Codex one because it had a better description of the class itself.
From now on will be referring to the developer page.
For any information on the web query class back to our project.
Let me show you how this works.
I'm going to insert this code inside the div tag with the class related posts to get started with the
WP query class, you need to make a new instance of this class.
I'm going to create a variable named RPG query where RPG is short for related posts.
I'm going to create a new instance of a query class, and this class has one argument which is completely
optional.
The argument is an array of keys and values that specify what kind of posts we want.
If you look at the documentation, you'll notice there are literally dozens of keys we can set.
Each key already has a default value.
You do not need to feel pressured to define every single one.
By default, WordPress will set its parameters to look for posts that have been published recently for
the most part.
That's fine, but we would like to make a few adjustments to that.
First, I want to shorten how many results are returned by default.
WordPress will use the setting in reading settings in an earlier lecture we set this to for.
However, I only want two results return.
So we have to set a key called posts underscore per underscore page.
This value controls how many posts a query can return per page by setting this value to two, we assure
ourselves only two posts will show up from this.
Next, we want to make sure that the post we're currently viewing does not show up on this list of posts.
In this case, we can set the post underscore, underscore, not underscore in.
I'm not sure if you can see this clearly, but there are two underscores after the word post, it's
very important your key matches mine.
This key accepts an array of post IDs.
So the question is, how do we get the I.D. for the current post?
WordPress provides a global variable named Post, which we can access directly in the loop.
And the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to learn more about this variable.
Here's what WordPress has to say.
Contains data from the current post in the loop.
This variable is an object that contains properties about the current post.
One of these values is the ID.
It's pretty simple to use.
You just pass him the post variable and grab the property ID like so.
The post variable is always available to us in the loop, the very last thing we need to do is make
sure that the posts displayed are similar to the one the user is reading.
There are dozens of ways to go about this, but let's keep it really simple.
I'm going to assume that posts in the same category should be similar.
So let's make it so that the posts that appear here are in the same category as the one the user is
currently reading.
First, we need to grab the categories assigned to this post, create a variable named categories and
set its value returned by the function.
Get the category.
Despite its name, the function will return multiple categories in an array form, if you're unsure
about what values a function returns, then it's always good practice to actually just print out the
data so you can view what's in it.
I'm going to use the print R function, which is a function that will output array and object data.
Refresh the page and you will see the object being outputted like so now we have a good idea about what
kind of data is returned.
I'm going to remove this print statement and move onto the query object.
To choose a specific category, we must define the cat key.
This key value will only be an integer, which represents the idea of the category, even though we
may have multiple categories.
I'm just going to concern myself with the very first category in the array.
I'm going to use a ternary operator to check if the categories array is empty.
If this returns false, then I'm going to grab the first category in the array, we next need to grab
the idea of that category that it is assigned under the property term ID.
However, if the array is empty, then I'm going to set the value to not that's it.
Let me quickly go over what's going on to query the database for posts.
We create a new instance of the WP query object by passing in this array.
We can specify what kind of posts we'd like to grab.
The posts per page key allows us to define how many posts we'd like per page.
The posts not in key allows us to define what posts should not be returned.
In our case, the current post being viewed should not be returned.
The cat key allows us to define if the posts should be in a specific category.
By doing all this, WordPress will then generate a custom sequel query and then execute that query and
return an array of posts.
All we have to do now is display the results.
We actually already know how to do this.
Inside a conditional statement we can call a method from the RPE query object, which is half posts.
You'll notice that this method is the exact same method used in our main loop, what we have here is
called a secondary loop.
I promise you that.
I will explain what this is in just a moment.
For now, just keep following along.
If this custom query does have posts, then we can use a while loop like so.
Then we can grab the current post using the post method.
Just like last time, I'm going to grab the static HTML and just replace it with its template tag equivalents,
you don't have to use the RPE query variable anymore, as WordPress assumes all post data comes from
it.
For example, if I use the title function, WordPress will grab the title from whatever the current
loop it's in.
Since it's in our custom loop, it'll grab the title from the custom loop.
It will not grab the title from the main loop that encompasses everything.
I hope that makes sense.
If not, I'll go more into detail in just a moment.
For now, I encourage you to pause the video and try it yourself.
All right, if you couldn't get it, that's fine, let's go over it together.
First, I'm going to move the static post into this loop.
The static post is this div tag with the class and post.
Make sure to delete any other static copy.
Then we have to grab the featured image of this post inside a conditional statement, we can use the
has post thumbnail function.
I'm going to place the image and its link inside this conditional statement.
Then we can replace these values with the appropriate template tags for the thumbnail.
I'm going to set the size to thumbnail.
Unlike last time, we don't need the full size image.
By default, the thumbnail size is 150 by 150, which is good enough.
This isn't anything new so far.
Continuing on, we use the functions, the permalink, the title, get the date comments number and
the excerpt.
Really simple stuff here, the very last thing we need to do is reset everything.
Earlier, I talked about main and secondary loops in the resource section.
I provide a link to the function WP reset post data.
It's very important what WordPress has to say here.
Use this function to restore the Global Post variable of the main query loop.
After a secondary query loop using new WP query, it restores the post variable to the current post.
In the main query, differences between the main query loop and secondary query loops are the main loop
is based on the URL request and it's processed before templates are loaded, secondary loops or queries
in theme, template or plug in files.
As I stated in an earlier lecture, WordPress will scan the URL and determine how many and what posts
to display for the page, WordPress will automatically generate a query using the WP query class.
This is what's called the main loop.
Every page you visit has won.
The WordPress team understands that sometimes you'll want to make your own loop and queries.
Therefore, you can also use this class to generate your own queries.
These custom loops are called secondary query loops.
To prove this further, let's take a look at the post function, I provide a link to this in the resource
section of this lecture.
If you look at the source code, you'll see that it's just two lines of code.
All that it's doing is grabbing the global WP query variable and then calling the method the post.
This is similar to what we did in our own code.
WordPress is using the exact same class we are using, which is WP query.
The query that WordPress generates is called the main query.
This query gets stored in the WP query variable, which is accessible to both you and WordPress.
If you wanted to, you could just use this code rather than calling the post function.
However, I think calling this function makes our code cleaner and much more readable.
Inside the single template, we essentially have two loops.
With this in mind, we run into one huge problem and that is how does WordPress know when you're finished
running your secondary loop, you do that by calling the WP reset post data function right after the
secondary loop.
If anything, this is the most important part when creating secondary loops by not calling this function,
you will confuse WordPress.
What will end up happening is that the data inside the loop will become unpredictable.
So make sure you call this function that is the last step.
Refresh the page and you should now see our related posts being displayed.
So far this has been the most complex task we've done, but it's very important that you understand
what's going on.
This will not be the last time we'll use the WP query class.
The WP query class is one of the most used classes provided by WordPress.
Before I in this lecture, let's take a look at some of the cases where using the query class is beneficial
over other available functions to add a list of related posts under the current post, for example,
a list of all posts in the same category to create two loops on the same page, for example, and IQ
page with the question titles at the top and the content beneath to create a custom list of recent posts
in the sidebar or footer of your site.
When the recent posts which it doesn't do what you need, or you'd rather code it yourself to create
custom queries for taxonomy using more than one taxonomy to define what's displayed, to query post
types which aren't outputted by the default query such as attachments.
These are just some of the common scenarios where the WP query class can be used.
Now let's take a look at some situations where it wouldn't be appropriate to use the WP underscore query
class if all you want to do is change the way posts are being displayed for a particular content type
or archive.
Don't use WP underscore query.
Instead, simply create a template file for that archive or content type and modify the loop in that
template file.
If you want to display a few more or less posts than would normally be shown on an archive, don't use
WP underscore query to create a whole new query.
Instead, use pre underscore get underscore posts to modify the main query along with a conditional
tag to single out where exactly you want to do it.
Beware of running too many queries on a page.
You could theoretically create a page with hundreds of custom queries.
But just think of the server load and you need more than four or five queries on a page.
You might want to consider creating extra pages.