In this lecture, we'll explore how to create templates for attachments, the template hierarchy goes
through quite a bit of templates to display attachments.
You can actually get really specific here by creating templates for certain mime types.
First, let's understand what a mind type is.
A mind type is a way for a program or browser to identify what kind of file is being loaded.
It's similar to a file extension except mind types or stored internally into the file itself.
This makes it a bit harder to change as opposed to file extensions.
Checking a mind type is safer than checking for an extension, but it isn't foolproof.
Now that we understand mine types, let's explore the template order WordPress will use.
First, it'll check for the mime type of the file and then search for a template with the same name.
If it doesn't find one, then it'll fall back to the attachment template.
This is followed by the single attachment that uses the slug.
Lastly, the single singular and indexed templates are used in that order.
Anyway, let's get started with creating attachment templates, go to your admin dashboard and look
for the menu item.
Media WordPress will allow you to manage all your uploads through here, all file uploads or what WordPress
considers attachments.
If you use Fakher Press, then you should see quite a few attachments being displayed here.
Veigar press generated these for us, which is nice.
I'm going to click on one of the images and you will see this modal pop up providing more details about
the attachment.
There are two ways to view this image.
You can either use this URL here or you can click on this link that says you attachment page.
Let's view the attachment page.
As you can see, we have the image appearing here and we have the rest of the page being displayed.
By default, WordPress will use the single or indexed templates if an attachment template isn't present.
While I do like that, my theme is being displayed.
There's way too much information here just for the image.
So let's create the attachment template now for this template.
I'm going to copy all the code from the single template into this new template.
Then I'm going to remove the metadata featured image pagination links next and previous links, tags,
related posts and author box.
What you'll end up having is the title content and the comments not really spectacular, but this is
just an attachment template, so the details don't matter as much.
Let's refresh the page and see what we get.
The image will disappear and nothing really displays.
But why is this?
What's happening is that WordPress now assumes you want to display attachments your own way by creating
the attachments template.
You're also given control over how an attachment should be displayed.
WordPress will not do it for you.
So how do we get the attachment info?
Well, there's a special variable that's created that contains all this info back inside.
The template I'm going to print are the post variable.
I'm also going to surround this with pre-tax.
By calling the function, the post, this variable is automatically created for you and you can use
it anywhere in your loop in future, lectures will go over how to use this variable to our advantage.
But for now, we'll just look at what's inside.
Go back to the page and refresh.
You should see the data about the post being printed out.
There's a lot of information being outputted here, but we only care about three properties.
The first property you'll notice is the post type.
It's set to attachment, which WordPress uses to determine if the attachment template should be used.
There's also the mind type being set will actually use these later to create more specific templates.
I'll talk more about that later.
The last property that's important is the Giulietti property.
This will contain the direct link to the attachment itself.
Now that we know where to find this information, let's use it.
I'm going to remove the print statement and then write above the content.
I'm going to create an anchor link.
The text will be direct download and the link will be dynamic using.
I'm going to access the GeoEye property from the post object like so.
If everything worked, then we should be able to refresh the page and see the direct download link appearing,
something I want to highlight is that if you don't see a title, then chances are the attachment itself
doesn't have a title.
If you go back to the media manager, you should see this field where you can set a title set one so
that you don't see a lot of empty space.
All right, this is great, I want to take this a step further, but I want to do is display that image
right below the download link.
But there's one problem we face.
This attachment template will be loaded for any attachment.
This includes videos, applications, PDF files and any other files that aren't images.
Luckily, we can get around this by creating a template for a specific mind type.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the function get allow admin types.
We aren't going to use this function.
But what I want you to look at is this list of mind types.
On the left you have the extension and on the right you have the mind type itself.
You'll see that mind types or formatted in a certain way.
There's the category and then the type of file itself.
For example, there's the image, video, text, audio and other categories.
If we look at the image category, you'll see all the various types of files that fall under this category,
which are JPEG, gif and so on and so forth.
Let's create a template for this.
All you have to do is name your template after the mime type.
In this case, we should name the file image BHP.
Now, any attachments with this mind type will be loaded using this template, I'm going to copy over
the code from the attachment template into this template.
The only change I'm going to make is add an IMG tag right below the direct download link.
Since we know that the URL to the image itself is saved inside the Guity property, I'm just going to
pass that in here.
I'm also going to give this image a class of image, Dasch responsive so that the image doesn't wander
off the page.
Refresh the page and you should now see the image you're hearing this is great because we now have two
attachment templates.
One template is for images that will display the image to the user and another is for any generic attachment.
You can obviously take this even further by adding a video player for videos or a PDF viewer.
The solutions are limitless.
Oh.