We're almost done right now.
I'm in the header file.
We still have some static sections inside the template.
First, let's tackle the title.
WordPress provides two solutions for adding titles to your head.
The first solution is a bit outdated, and that is by using the WP title function.
This function is to be deprecated, but it is still available for backwards compatibility.
I do not suggest using it.
The recommended solution is to add theme support for it.
I'm going to delete the title tags from the head tag and then open the setup file.
I'm going to call the function, add theme support and pass entitled hash tag.
Just like that, WordPress will always generate the title tag for you, any SEO plugins will also be
able to make modifications if they wish.
Next up is the logo itself.
The logo can either be text or an image.
Currently, we only have text.
We are also willing to accept images.
I'm going to call the function app theme support again and pass in custom dash logo.
WordPress comes with a feature for users to upload their own logos.
We don't have to make a form or handle the upload.
You'll see how this works in just a moment.
Go back to the header template and look for the div tag with the idea of logo.
Inside this tag, add a conditional statement.
To check if the user has uploaded a logo, you have to use the function, has a custom logo.
This function will return true if the user uploaded a logo, otherwise it'll return false.
If there is a logo, then we can call a function called the custom logo.
This function will output the image along with a link to the homepage.
In some situations, the user might not have a logo ready when they set up the theme.
Whatever their reason, maybe you should have a backup.
Let's add the else block and manually create a link.
I'm going to use the static version as a template.
I'm going to replace the link and echo out the value returned by the function home yourself.
I'm going to pass in a forward slash so we can specify that we only want the root you out.
Inside the tanks, I'm going to call the blog info function.
This function takes in a string, which is what pieces of information about the blog we want in the
resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to more info about this function here.
You'll find a list of values you can pass in the very first one is name, which returns the name of
the site.
So let's pass that in.
This function will automatically output the value, if you ever want the value returned, then you just
use the get block info function.
Let's refresh the page and check if everything is working so far.
If you look at the title, you'll notice it updates accordingly.
The logo is also showing our text to change the logo to an image you need to click this button called
Customize.
This will take you to the customizer, which is a way to edit your site while also viewing the changes
in real time under site identity.
You will find the form for updating the logo.
I don't have a logo image, so I will leave this alone.
The next two things I want to do is update the menu and fix this advertising spot.
Before I do that, I want to talk about this customizer.
In the past, the WordPress customizer was really hard to work with and did not have as much features.
This may developers make their own settings and options page to change how the theme functions.
However, in recent updates, the customizer is starting to become the main way to modify a theme.
A lot of theme developers are opting to use the customizer.
We will definitely be working with the customizer soon.
For now, let's focus on this secondary menu on the top, we've already created a menu before, so try
creating another one yourself.
If you aren't able to do it, then let's try it together.
I'm not going to go over every detail so will fly by this quickly.
First in the setup function, use the registered NAV menu function.
I'm going to reuse the previous code and replace these values with the word secondary like so.
With the menu registered, we can now display it.
I'm going to go into the admin dashboard and create a new menu and assign it to the secondary location.
Inside the header template, I'm going to copy and paste the last menu into the other menu spot.
I'm going to replace these two values with the secondary menu and then set the depth to one, since
I don't want drop downs for the secondary menu.
Refresh the page and you should now see the secondary menu being displayed so far, everything is really
coming together.
This ad spot has been broken for some time, so let's fix that.
Previously, we used the plug in WP subtitle to add subtitles to our posts.
We will be doing something similar to this and the resource section.
I provide a link to the WP Quad's plug this plug and handles advertisement for WordPress sites.
It's a really great plug in that is updated constantly.
The best part is that it's developer friendly.
We can create our own custom ad spots and have it managed by this plug in.
This frees us from having to handle all the logic ourselves.
I want you to install and activate this plug in through the admin dashboard.
After doing so, look inside the WP dash contents plugins folder.
This is where all your plug ins are installed.
The quick dash ad sense Dash Reloaded plug in is the plug.
And we just installed open the includes API file.
You'll notice in these comments, the developer left notes on how to integrate this plug in into your
theme.
There are two steps you need to do.
The first step is to tell WP Quad's that you have a custom ad spot and your theme.
The second step would be to instruct it where to display the ad spot.
I'm going to register this ad spot in the setup function instead of the functions file.
The reason I'm doing this is because the setup function is called right after our theme has been loaded.
Therefore, I know nothing has been officially processed unless it was put in the function file.
So it's technically the same thing.
The only difference is that it's in separate files.
This makes our code look a whole lot cleaner.
I'm going to copy and paste the commented code into this function like so.
I'm only going to have one spot, you'll see that this code does two things.
First, we use a conditional statement to check if the Function Quad's Register ad exists this way.
We know that the WP Quad's plug in is activated.
Then we call the Function Quad's Register ad, which has two parameters.
The first is the idea of the location.
I'm going to call this Udemy header and for the description it will be Udemy header position.
With this in place, questions will now know we have an ad spot inside the admin dashboard, you'll
find the WP Quad's menu under the ad code section.
I'm going to paste in an image tag.
The image that I'm using is from a site called Placeholder It, I'll provide a link to this image.
This site allows you to modify the size of the image and create a temporary placeholder.
This is really great for web development.
Save the changes and then switch to the position tab.
You'll notice that our new position is showing up at the very bottom.
Activate this position and assign it to the first ad we created.
Make sure to save your changes.
Our ad is ready, and now all we have to do is display it inside the header template, look for the
div tag with the class top dash advert, add a conditional statement that checks for the function Quad's
at.
Then I'm going to call this function and pass an array with the key location, the name of the location
will be the location you passed into the Quad's Register ad function.
This function will return the HTML we passed in previously, so we have to echo it out.
That's it.
Let's check if our ad appears appropriately, just like that, we now have ads on our site with custom
locations.
This plug in is amazing and it takes care of managing ads.
This is the second plugin we've used in our theme.
It's extremely common for theme developers to bundle their themes with plug ins.
This increases the value of your theme in a future lecture.
I will go over how you can bundle plug ins with your theme properly.
The reason I'm not showing you now is because I don't want to have to constantly update multiple files
whenever we add a plug in.
I would rather knock it out all at once when our theme is nearly finished.
For now, we will continue working on the header and eventually move to the footer on the header.
We have these social icons for these icons.
We will be using the word press customizer.
This will introduce us to how the customizer works and how to extend it.
I do want to give you a warning.
So far we've really just been calling functions and using WordPress as templating system to handle a
lot of the logic for us.
WordPress will still help us with extending the customizer, but we will be writing a lot more code
and be focusing more on the code rather than the visual aspect.
The customizer can seem overwhelming, but I promise you we will be using it constantly so you will
get used to it eventually.
I highly recommend you take a break before moving on to the next lecture.
See you there.