We are now going to take a look at the theme customizer API, the theme customizer is WordPress is UI
for customizing the theme.
This is enabled by default for you.
Already you can view the customizer by going into the admin dashboard and navigating to appearance customize
on the sidebar.
You'll find a few options for changing the theme and you'll see our theme being displayed on the right.
Let's see how this works.
Click on site identity and try changing the site title.
Right after making these modifications, WordPress will actually update the preview, what WordPress
is doing is loading the site inside an iFrame.
Every time a change happens, WordPress will refresh the iFrame with the modified data.
Keep in mind that this doesn't take an official effect until you click save.
What makes this customizer even more powerful is that developers are provided an API to add in their
own options and settings.
So here's what we're going to do.
We're going to create some settings to add social links in the header and footer.
We're going to make everything here dynamic, open the functions, file and add an action, hook.
The action we want to hook into is called Customize Register.
This is the hook WordPress, cause when it starts to set up the theme customizer, the function to call
will be called Jiyu Customized Register.
Create a file called Theme Dasch Customizer inside the includes folder and define the function here.
Lastly, include this file from the functions file.
This function will be passed in one variable named WP Customize, this is an object with methods and
properties for modifying within customizer.
This object is an instance of the WP Customize Manager class.
I'll provide a link to this class in the resource section.
This class controls how the customizer works, and most of its functionality will be going over how
this works shortly before we begin working on the customizer.
There are three important concepts you need to know if you don't understand right away.
After I explain it, then that's fine.
I'll be showing you how it works.
There are three steps you'll usually take when working with the customizer directly, the first step
is adding a setting.
The setting is just a value that you save in the database and can be modified through the customizer.
You can then use this value in your theme.
The second step is creating a section.
A section is a way to group a bunch of fields together.
If you look at the customizer, you'll notice that things are grouped together instead of just displaying
every option together.
This makes it easier to control and navigate around.
The third step is creating a controller.
A controller is just an input field, checkbox, color picker or uploader that allows you to change
the setting you made in step one directly.
Let's get started with the customizer, the object passed in has a couple of methods.
The method for adding a new setting is called add setting, and it's called like so.
This method has two parameters.
The first is the ID like anything else.
The idea is something that should be unique so we can refer to it later.
I'm going to set this to Jiyu Facebook handle.
The next parameter is an array of settings, I'm going to provide a link in the resource section of
the lecture for more information about this method.
If you scroll down a bit, you'll see a few settings you can set.
Most of them are optional except one setting, which is the default key.
I'm going to set this as an empty string.
That's all you need to do, one thing I should mention is this setting called transport.
This controls how the value is reflected on the main theme during preview mode.
By default, it's set to refresh.
This means that when this value is changed, then the page will refresh and show that value.
If you want to control how this value is reflected on the theme, you will need to set this to post
message.
However, refresh will work in 90 percent of the time, so will leave this value as is.
This value will now be saved in the database and it can now be manipulated through controllers and be
displayed on our theme.
We now have to create a section to create a section.
We have to call the ad section method.
The first parameter is the ID for this section.
I'm going to set this to Jiyu social section.
The second parameter is an array of settings, the title will be translatable and I'll set it to you,
to me social settings.
Next is the priority, the lower the number, the higher placement it will receive and vice versa.
I'm going to set this to 30.
There's one last method I want to call, which is the ad control method.
This will create an input field and added to a particular section of our choosing, this method is a
bit tricky because there are two ways you can set this up.
The first way is to pass in the settings and have more control over it.
However, this tends to be confusing if you don't know what you're doing.
The second route is to pass in an object that will help you create the field you'd like to create will
be going with the second route because it's really easy to get started in the resource section.
I provide a link to the add control method.
Scroll down to the classes section.
This section provides a couple of classes that can be passed and that will assist us with filling in
the blanks.
The WP customized control class will help you create fields such as text fields, radio buttons, checkboxes
and drop downs.
The color control will create a color picker for you.
The upload control will create a field for uploading files.
The image control also does something similar to the upload control, except you can only upload images.
These other two are unimportant to us as WordPress uses these internally for its own purpose.
So we won't be messing with them at all throughout this lecture.
For our purposes.
The first class is perfect for us since we want to create a TextField for the users handle.
I'm going to click this and you'll see that WordPress provides an example on how this works.
I'm going to copy and paste this and go over what's going on.
The first parameter is the customizer object itself, the controller needs to know more about what's
happening in the customizer so that it can fill in the blanks for you.
The second parameter is the ID for this controller.
I'm going to set this as use social Facebook input.
The last parameter is an array of additional settings, we will only concern ourselves with these four
keys.
The label is just text to describe the field.
This should be a translatable string.
I'm going to set this as Facebook handle.
The U.S. is where it'll appear, we created our own section called Giuse Social Section will assign
this control under that section.
The next key is settings, which is what setting will this field modify?
We created this in step one.
The value for this will be Jiyu Facebook handle.
The last key is type, which is what kind of field this will be by default.
It'll be text, there's also radio, text area, etc. You can find all the types of fields in the documentation.
For now, the default is fine.
I'm actually just going to remove this key.
We are now finished with the customizer.
Let's refresh the customizer and you will now see this new section called Udemy Social Settings.
After clicking it, you'll now see the controller.
I'm going to input Udemy and save the setting.
However, nothing in the preview will change because we haven't told WordPress where we'd like to use
this setting.
Let's review what we did in our customize function first.
The first step was to create the setting, which is the value that's stored in the database.
The second step is to create a section that will group various controllers.
The third step was to create a controller that is assigned under a section and controls one setting.
A lot of people get confused with the difference between the ad setting and add control methods.
The setting will create the database value.
The method will not create an input field.
It will just tell WordPress about the setting and tell it to create a setting in the database.
The control method will not create a database value.
Instead, it will create an input field.
The controller will take care of modifying and updating the database value whenever the input field
is updated.
All right.
Now that we've cleared that up, let's start making our theme.
Recognize the changes inside the header template.
Let's locate a list of social icons in the header inside a conditional statement.
I'm going to call the function, get the mod.
This function will grab a setting you pass in if there is no value or the value does not exist, then
this will return false.
I'm going to pass in Jiyu Facebook handle.
This is the setting we created earlier, if there is a value, then we'll output this one list item,
which is the Facebook link.
I'm going to move the static link inside the conditional statement.
Then I'm going to replace the Eurail for this with the Facebook Eurorail, followed by the value returned
by the theme mod function, we will have to echo out the value since the function will only return it.
That's it.
Let's go back to the customizer and you will now see Airlink appearing.
If I were to empty out this textfield, you'll notice the iFrame refresh and the link disappear.
This is exactly what we want.
The only thing left to tackle is the rest of these icons.
I want you to try this on your own.
Actually, before I let you off.
There's one thing we should do together.
Create a folder inside the includes folder named Customizer.
Then create a file named Social P inside this file.
Create a function named J use social customizer section.
This function will accept BWP customized object.
I'm going to cut and paste the contents from the main customizer function into this function.
Then I'm going to call this function from the main customizer and pass in the customize object.
The last step is to just include this social customizer file.
By doing this, we make things a lot cleaner and easier to manage, these social icons aren't the only
things we'll be using the customizer for this year is just preference and not required by WordPress
itself.
I just like to stay organized and clean.
I want you to create the new settings.
Now all you'll be doing is creating new settings and controllers.
You only need one section which we already defined.
Once you have those ready, then you can modify the theme itself to include the links.
Welcome back.
If you weren't able to do it, then no worries, I have you covered.
As you can see here, I already have everything set up.
I'm going to provide these social customizer function in the resource section so that you can download
it and compare it to your own function.
I also made modifications to the header and footer to include these settings onto the theme.
I won't be providing these as these are just really simple and aren't as difficult to replicate.
If you don't know how to do this, then you really need to rewash this lecture because there's nothing
advanced going on in these templates.
I'll see you in the next lecture.