And this lecture, we're going to continue working with the word press customizer API, there are five
fields will be creating that will do the following.
The first two fields is for these two button icons on the menu.
We'll let the user decide if they want these buttons to be available.
The next option is the text for this copyright message on the footer.
The last two options will allow users to select the pages for the terms of service and privacy policy
links.
Before we get started with the customizer, I'm going to make the search form in the header functional.
I'm going to open the header and search form templates, look for the search form inside the header
template.
You'll notice right away these forms are completely different in appearance and markup, so I won't
be using the function for grabbing this template.
Instead, I'm just going to copy and paste some of the parts into this template.
There are only three things we really need to make dynamic.
That would be the action for the form, the value for the input.
And lastly, make this text translatable.
All right, let's get started with the customizer, I'm going to make a file inside the customizer folder
and name it MEAC, which is short for miscellaneous.
The final function named J, you might see customizer section, this function will accept the WP customizer
object.
From the functions file, I'm going to include this file.
The very last step is to call this function from the main customizer function.
I know that was a lot to do, but trust me, you should always do this as it'll help you keep things
organized.
I've been in that situation where I would stuff my code in the least amount of files possible, and
it was always a pain to maintain, just like last time will be using the three step process to create
these new settings.
The first step is to create the database values using the ADD setting method.
The ID for the first setting will be Jiyu header show search and the default value will be yes.
I'm going to copy and paste this for more times and update the names for each of these.
Feel free to pause the video so that you can have what I have, I have the Jiyu header shoket setting
where the default value is also, yes, the Jiyu footer copyright text will have its default value to
the original copyright text.
The Jiyu footer to page and Jiyu footer privacy page will both be set to zero.
These will be assigned to pages later on.
That right there is step one.
We have all our database settings ready.
The next step is to create a section that will hold all our controllers call the ad section method and
given the idea of Jiyu Mrs. Section.
The title will be Udemy Amici Settings with a priority of 30.
The last step is to create the controllers for each setting, the first controller will be a standard
HTML input field, so we'll be using the WP customized control class to help us out.
As usual, I'm going to pass in the normal stuff, there are a couple of things I should highlight.
The Idy will be Jiyu heter show search input.
I will make sure this is assigned to the miscellaneous section and make its settings correspond to the
correct settings value we created earlier.
Instead of a text input field, I want to create a checkbox.
I will set the type to checkbox.
The values we use for the checkbook can be set by adding the key choices, this key value will be an
array of possible values available.
We only have one value, and that is yes.
The name of the key is the actual value that will be compared to check if the setting matches the checkbox,
the value of the item is human readable text next to the checkbox so the user knows what the checkbox
is for.
Let's refresh the customizer and we should now see our section and the checkbox being displayed.
As you can see, the checkbox is already checked because the default value for this setting is yes,
I want you to do the same for the card button while you're at it.
Try creating the copyright text controller.
It's just a text field, nothing complex.
Pause the video and try it out.
If you didn't get it, that's fine, it's really simple.
I'm going to copy and paste the previous controller twice and change a few things.
I want you to update the ID.
Then I want you to change the label and these settings key for the card button.
For the copyright text, I'm going to remove the choices and type keys by default, the type will always
be text like last time.
You'll only need to change the ID label and these settings key.
That should do it for the two buttons and copyright text, the only fields we have to create are the
fields for the pages.
I'm going to paste this one more time and remove the choices he and update the idee label and settings
keys appropriately.
This time, I'm going to change the type to drop down Dasch pages.
This is a special type.
We can set WordPress or generate a drop down menu and set the options to all the pages that are published.
The value of each option will be the page ID, which we can use later.
This is exactly what we want since the terms of service and privacy policy will be separate pages.
If you don't have a page in mind, then you should set the settings value to zero so WordPress won't
set up page by accident.
This controller is for the terms of service.
I'm going to copy this and set the idee settings and label for the privacy policy.
Now.
Just like that, we should have five controllers in the miscellaneous section, refresh the customizer
and you should see something similar to what I have, because this is a testing environment.
I'm going to set the two page dropdown controllers to some random pages.
I'm also going to update the copyright text to something simple.
Make sure to save the changes, the last thing we need to do is make these changes, reflect on the
theme, open the header template and look for the search and cart buttons.
I'm going to surround these in conditional statements like so.
The condition will check if the values for both these mods are set to, yes, make sure to update the
values in both these functions to the appropriate setting test to customize your really quick and see
if everything works correctly.
The buttons should appear and disappear depending on if the box is checked or not.
I'm going to close the header template and open the footer template.
Let's get to work for the copyright text.
I'm just going to echo out the setting.
Next, I'm going to wrap the links in conditional statements and check of the settings have a value.
Keep in mind, by default, these settings values are zero.
This is also equivalent to false.
So we don't need to perform any checks besides what's returned.
Replaced links and use the permalink function.
Template tags can we use outside the loop?
However, there is one condition you must pass in the ID of the Post or page you like to retrieve information
from most template tags have this as their first parameter.
Let's do that now.
Call the get the mod and get the appropriate setting for each link.
If you don't pass in an ID and you're using this function outside of the loop, then you'll receive
an error.
Let's check out the site now, save any changes.
You made an X out of the customizer.
Make sure the links in the footer work after confirming.
So then you're all done.
Let's take a moment to explore our theme.
When we first started, we had a bunch of links and styles and the content was broken.
Now we have a fully functioning theme.