So far, we've talked about adding settings to the customizer, but what if we wanted to make some changes
to the default customizer that's completely possible and allowed.
If you believe you know a better way, the customizer should be displayed for your theme, then you're
completely allowed to do that.
Let's explore some ways to customize this.
The first thing I want to do is group my sections into something called panels, panels or a way to
group sections.
If the theme customizer had a hierarchy, it would be panels, sections, comptrollers.
Creating a panel is pretty straightforward.
Inside the main customizer file, I'm going to call the ad panel method.
I'm calling this method inside this function instead of a separate file, because it encompasses everything,
however, you're free to organize this however you like.
This method has two parameters, which is the idea and an array of settings.
I'm going to set the ID to you to meet.
The array will have three keys, the first key is the title, which should be human readable.
I'm going to set this to you, to me and make it translatable.
The next key is description, which will be Udemy themed settings, it's important that you add some
P tags as it'll format it properly.
The last key is priority, which will determine the location, the higher the number, the lower placement
it gets.
I'm going to set this to 160.
This will add a panel to the customizer now we can add the sections to this panel to add a section to
a panel, you have to specify it inside the ad section method, open both customizer files for the social
and miscellaneous settings, look for the ad section method calls and add a new key called panel and
pass it in the panel ID, we said earlier.
Refresh the page and you should now see the panel udemy, and if you click on it, you'll find both
sections appearing under it, which is what we wanted.
Now let's talk about customizing existing controllers and sections.
There is this section called Site Identity.
Let's say I wanted to change the title to General.
To do that, you need to grab the section or controller and modify IT settings.
Before we can do that, we have to know the ID of what we want to grab inside the main customized file.
I'm going to vade, dump everything and format it with pre-tax.
Refresh the page and you should see this huge object outputted, you'll find a lot of information related
to the customizer, including all the sections, controllers and panels I'm going to skip to.
These sections are right here.
You'll find all the sections to find.
So far as you can see, you'll find all the keys similar to the ones you can set when using the ADD
section method.
I'm going to look for the section with the title site Identity after finding it.
I now see the ID is titled Tag Line Back inside the customizer file.
I'm going to call the get section method.
This method will grab a section and all its settings you have to pass in the ID, which would be title
tag line, as we saw earlier from here, I can then modify any property I want.
Previously, when using the ad section method, we use an array for the settings.
However, after a section is added, the settings will be converted into an object with properties and
methods.
Because of that, we have to change the settings as if they were properties.
Despite the conversion, the names are usually the same.
In this case, we can set the title to General like so.
This is how you would modify any section, panel or controller for controllers, you use the get control
method for panels, it's get panel for settings, it's jet setting.
If you're unsure about a name or an idea or a particular value, it's always good practice to dump the
customized object like we did here.
I'm going to comment out this bit of code.
All right, the last thing I want to do is customize the user experience, whenever we update a setting,
you'll notice the page refreshes, which is pretty decent, but the loading time is something that's
not really desired.
In this case, we will want to make some settings, not refresh the page.
Rather, we can use JavaScript to update the settings to accomplish this.
We'll have to make some minor tweaks to the settings we defined earlier, opened the Mesi function and
search for the card and search button settings.
I'm going to define a new key called transport and set it to post message.
There are two possible values for this key by default, it's refresh, which will instruct WordPress
to refresh the page whenever this value is updated by setting it to post message, you're telling WordPress
that you will use custom JavaScript code to reflect the changes on the page.
Open the file assets, jazz themed customized JS file.
I created this file for you already and all it is is an empty query.
Initialize your function will be updating this very soon.
I only want to load this file if the customizer is loaded, otherwise it would just be a wasted download.
To do that, we have to add a new action inside the functions file called Customize Preview.
In it, the function to call is Jiyu customize preview init.
I'm going to create a file inside the customizer folder called NQ and define the function here.
Lastly, I'm going to include it, this hook will only run if the customizer is loaded.
Its purpose is for loading stylesheets and scrips only.
I'm going to call the WP NQ script function.
The ID will be Jiyu theme customizer.
Passing the euro like we did previously.
The value for the dependencies is very important here.
We require two things, which is Jake Query and the customized dash preview.
The customized preview file has some helper functions and methods for working with the customizer,
you'll see what those are in just a moment.
The version will be false.
And I want to load this in the footer just like that.
Our file should now be loaded.
Let's go back to the JS file to make the finishing changes.
Since the customized JavaScript file is being loaded, we're provided with an object called WP, which
contains all the methods and properties related to WordPress.
One of these methods is called Customize, which allows you to get the value of a particular setting.
In this case, it would be Jiyu header show search.
The second parameter for this method is a callback function for using the value the callback function
is provided the current value.
I'm going to bind this value so that we can keep an eye out for any changes this method takes in another
callback function that's passed in the new value, we will refer to it as New Val.
Since this is a check box, we can simply check to see if there's any value set, if there is, then
we want to show the search button, otherwise hide it.
The idea of the search button is top dash search.
We can use the show and hide Jake wery methods, respectively.
I'm going to do the same for the cart button.
It's the same bit of code, we're just replacing the IDs.
Let's refresh the customizer one more time.
One thing I should note is that sometimes your code may not be loaded as some browsers will cache files.
So be sure to clear your cache.
If that's the case, test out the code and you shouldn't see the buttons disappearing depending on if
the boxes are checked.
You should not have any page refresh.
All this is being done with JavaScript code, which makes for a smoother user experience.