Right now, I'm in the setup function, I want to start filling in some gaps and adding some features,
so that's what we'll do here in the resources section.
I provide a link to the ad theme support function.
WordPress provides so many features here that we should use.
The first one, we should add, is the feed length feature.
WordPress will generate RSS feeds for us and always make sure it's updated with the latest posts.
If you're unfamiliar with RSS feeds, you'll see what those look like in just a moment.
Inside the setup function, let's use the add theme support function and pass an automatic dash feed
dash links which will instruct WordPress to set up some RSS feeds.
Refresh the site and you'll notice nothing's really changed, but under the hood, there is one small
change, right?
Click and view the page source.
WordPress will generate these two tags inside the head tag that links to RSS XML feeds.
Let's click on this link and you'll be taken to this XML document.
The purpose of this document is for RSS readers to scan this document.
This document contains data about your post.
RSS feeds provide a way for users to know when new content is available on your site without having
to visit it.
RSS has been in decline for some time, but there's still a wealthy amount of people still using this
technology.
Whether or not you want to add it is up to you.
For the most part, it's fast and easy to use.
The next thing I want to add support for it is HTML5.
It can be done by simply calling the same function again and passing in HTML five.
If you can remember, WordPress will automatically generate HTML markup for the search form if we didn't
have a template for it.
This isn't the only time WordPress generates markup for us.
By default, WordPress will make the HTML generated HTML compatible.
However, if your theme takes advantage of HTML five tags, then you'll want to enable this HTML5 feature
to ensure all markup is up to standards.
If you look at the documentation, you'll notice that the second parameter is an array.
Every feature can take advantage of the second parameter.
It varies.
In the case of HTML five, you can specify which markup will have HTML five applied to it.
Even though this parameter is optional, WordPress still wants an array of HTML five elements you'd
like to support.
I'm going to copy and paste the array from the example into our code like so.
The next thing we want to add support for is starter content.
This is a brand new feature and WordPress four point seven.
The purpose of this feature is a way for developers to add dummy content.
When the user is viewing the theme in the customizer.
This dummy content will only be available when the current WordPress installation is fresh, meaning
that the user just created the WordPress site and hasn't created any posts, pages or menus.
If you take a look at the ad themes support function developer page, you'll notice there's almost no
information about this feature.
Since it's new, it's lacking in documentation on WordPress, a site instead there is a blog post about
it.
I'll provide a link to the blog post in the resource section of this lecture.
Here's what the team has to say about it.
One of the hardest things for people setting up sites with WordPress for the first time is understanding
what the jobs are and how a given theme can work for you, especially when there's no content there
to visualize.
There are also significant gaps between local themed previews, screenshots and previews.
Even when there are easy to use site customization tools, it is difficult to figure out where to start
and what things are going to be like to help users along that path.
Four point seven introduces the concept of starter content themes.
Specific functions of content help showcase a theme to users and serve as a starting point for further
set up of new sites.
Let's learn how to use it, call the function, add theme support and pass in starter Dasch content.
For the second parameter, you'll need to pass in an array of dummy content to save time.
I'm going to copy and some code and I'll be going over how all this works.
Try and follow along.
Unlike the other features, this feature in particular requires that you actually set up the dummy content
in this array, you'll find six keys which are all required.
I'm going to minimize these for a second so you can get a better overview of what's going on.
Each of these keys are assigned arrays with their own settings.
The first is widgets.
As you may have thought, the widgets array determines what widgets will be displayed in these sidebars
we created.
We currently have one sidebar and that is the juice side bar.
You set this as a key and its value will be an array of widgets inside the sidebar.
If you look at the blog post, then you'll see that the developers know what kind of predefined widgets
you can pass in.
I'm going to pass him three widgets called text business info.
Search and text about WordPress will automatically generate these widgets with the data they have in
their system.
Since this is just dummy content, I'm not so worried about what's inside the widgets.
As long as something is displayed, the next key is attachments.
We haven't talked too much about attachments, but attachments is the post type WordPress uses to associate
files and images.
If you were to go to the admin dashboard and click on media, you'll be taken to all the attachments
we have on our site.
It's mostly images.
The attachments key allows you to simulate attachments without having to actually upload anything into
the media library.
This will be an array which will accept an array of images or files.
The key will be considered the ID.
We only have one image, which is the image dash about inside this array is more information about this
file image.
There are two required fields which are the human readable name and the location of the file.
The location is relative to the current theme.
If I were to open the assets images about directory, you'll find the image right here.
The next key is posts.
This will allow you to define some dummy posts.
You'll notice I'm just creating the same kind of posts just under different names.
One thing you'll notice is that for the thumbnail key, for each of these posts, I'm using these curly
brackets.
This will tell WordPress to look for any attachments with the ID of Image Dasch about.
This is the same idea we used in the attachments array.
WordPress will be able to make the connection for you.
The next key is the options.
Keep the options.
Key allows you to modify the values in the WP Options Database table.
Let's open the WP Options Table.
I'm going to be viewing the data in Heidi.
Yes, you will.
If you prefer my admin.
That's fine.
WordPress stores all its information inside this table.
Plugins and themes will also store their data here and this array.
The key will correspond to the option underscore name field and the value will correspond to the option
underscore value field.
I'm overriding three options here.
The show on front field determines whether the front page will be a page we created or a list of blog
posts.
I set this to page the page on front is the option for determining what page from our list of pages
will be the front page.
Since we set show on front to page, this key is required.
Once again, I'm using the curly bracket style to tell WordPress that the value will be a post.
In our case, it will be the home page we created earlier in the posts array.
We do the same for the page.
For Perski, the key theme models is where we can override our own theme settings.
These are the same settings we created in the customizer.
The key and values are pretty self-explanatory.
The key is the idea of the setting and its value would be the value for that setting.
The Laskey should be now menus, which allows us to generate menus.
We have two menus which are primary and secondary.
These are the same menus we registered in our theme.
Each of these have arrays for additional settings about these menus.
First is the name which I make translatable.
The items are the actual links you'll notice on using page underscore and link underscore.
WordPress will read these values and if it starts with page underscore, WordPress will automatically
look at the posts key and see if we have any pages with the same name.
So Page underscore about.
We'll look for the about page.
The link underscore is internal WordPress links.
WordPress will generate its own links, which we can take advantage of.
The link underscore home is the link to the home page.
I also leave this note here that says Note that the core home page is actually a link in case a static
front page is not used.
That wraps up this theme feature.
We can't actually test it right away because our WordPress installation is already beyond the point
of a starter site.
However, we can temporarily restart it without having to do a fresh install or clean all our posts
and settings inside the WP Underscore Options table, there is a value named fresh underscore site.
Set this value to one.
This will automatically trick WordPress into thinking that this site is a new site, after doing that,
go to the customizer and you'll notice our site is completely different than what we see on the homepage.
Keep in mind that this data will only apply to the customizer.
It's a way of previewing our site without actually having to force apply these changes.
I'm going to set the fresh underscore site to zero as we're done with the starter content feature.