One section we haven't gotten around to is this breaking news, which is keeping track of popular posts
can be tedious and it's not exactly built into WordPress.
Luckily, there is a plugin out there that will help us out with that.
I want you to go to the admin dashboard and add a new plug in the plug.
And I want to install is called WordPress.
Popular posts install and activate the one by Hektor.
This plugin will automatically help us keep track of what posts are popular by Vieux.
Under settings, you'll find a menu item called WordPress Popular posts here you can control what posts
are popular and additional settings.
We don't need to make any changes at this moment.
Right now, none of the posts are popular.
I'm going to open the homepage within a new tab and view at least three posts.
I want you to do the same.
Refresh the admin page after you've done so, and you'll now see those three posts being displayed as
popular posts.
This is great.
So far there are now two things we need to do.
We need to display the popular posts and then we need to let the user control whether or not they want
to display it while we're at it.
We will also make the text breaking news changeable.
First, let's display these posts inside the WordPress Popular Posts admin page.
I'm going to click on the Parameters tab.
This plugin allows you to display the popular posts two ways.
One way is through a shortcode and the other is through a template tag.
I want to use the template tag.
You'll find a list of parameters we can set to modify the output.
We'll be using these shortly.
Inside the index template.
I want you to perform a conditional check around the popular post widget.
I want to check for two things I want to check of the page being displayed is not a single post and
is the home page using the functions?
Exclamation point is single and is home.
These two functions are at work, press calls, conditional tags, conditional tags or a way to check
what kind of page is being displayed in the resource section, I provide a link to learn more about
conditional tags.
Here is what WordPress has to say about it.
Conditional tags can be used in your template files to alter the display of content depending on the
conditions that the current page matches.
They tell WordPress what code to display under specific conditions.
Conditional tags usually work with P, if else, conditional statements.
The code begins by checking to see if a statement is true or false.
If the statement is found to be true, the first set of code is executed.
If it's false, the first set of code is skipped and the second set of code after the else is executed
and set.
You can read up on this page to learn about the many conditional tags there are, but for now, the
ones we're using will suffice throughout.
This course will be using conditional tags to help us change the final result.
All right.
Now that we know that this is indeed the home page, we can begin displaying the breaking news widget.
I'm also going to check if the WP get most popular function exists.
We can now call a function called WP get most popular.
This function has a one parameter and that is an array of settings we can set back on the admin side,
you'll find that the plug in WordPress popular posts gives plenty of examples on how to use these settings.
There are only three that I want to use and those can be found at the very bottom.
These last three keys determine how the posts are outputting.
The first key we should set is the WP start.
This will be the HTML that will be outputted at the very beginning, we have the static version of widget
here.
I'm going to copy everything from the beginning all the way up to the opening tag with the class of
slider dash wrap.
I'm going to paste this in as the value.
The next key I want to set is the WP, and this should have all the closing tags.
The only thing we have left are these three links, we only need one, so I'm just going to cut one
and get rid of the rest.
The last key to set is the post HTML.
This key value will be the HTML we just cut previously.
Now we have to replace the static parts of this HTML into something like the function will be able to
read and replace.
If you look at the documentation, you'll find that the developer provides you with what values can
be inserted and replaced.
The only ones we're concerned with are the normal and text underscore title content tags.
We just replace the static content with these content tags, make sure to surround them with one pair
of curly brackets so that the plugin will be able to replace the.
Let's refresh the page and you'll see the three posts we previously viewed being displayed as popular
posts, the last thing we need to do is to make it optional to display this widget or not.
Inside the miscellaneous customizer, I'm going to create two new settings.
The first setting is called Jiyu Shohet or popular post widget, which will have a default value of
false.
I don't want this widget to be turned on by default.
The second setting will be Jiyu popular posts, which at title, which will have a default title of
breaking news.
The next step is to create a controller.
I'm going to assign these two controllers to the MEAC section, the first controller will be a checkbox
with an ID of Jiyu show header, popular posts.
Which widget input?
The second controller will just be a text input field with an ID of Jiyu, popular posts, widget title
input.
There's nothing new here after creating these two settings and it's comptrollers, it's time to update
the theme to reflect those changes.
Back inside the conditional statement, I'm going to add one more check.
This will be checking if the theme mod Jiyu show had popular post widget is turned on.
The last thing I'm going to do is change the breaking news static text into its theme, Monju popular
post widget title.
Save your changes and let's check out the customizer, the checkbox should be unchecked, and so therefore
the popular post widget should not be showing.
Try turning it on and then change the text to popular posts.
After confirming if everything worked on the preview, then save your changes and double check on the
front end.
That's it for now.
You'll notice that I spent an awful lot of time talking about other plugins and how to integrate them.
I'm going to show you something in the resources section.
I provide a link to the theme for a site under WordPress.
Popular themes.
You'll notice a lot of themes are killing it and making massive amounts of sales.
I'm going to click on Aveda and you'll notice that this item highlights it's compatible with various
plugins and even comes bundled with some.
It's extremely common to bundle your themes with plugins that help it with certain tasks and functions.
Of course, you'll be put in a situation where you'll have to make your own custom solution and we'll
definitely learn how to make plug in soon.
For now, don't worry, bundling plug ins doesn't make you a bad developer, just a more efficient one.