Our theme is not complete yet, we're nowhere close to that, but I want to make some simple adjustments
before we move on to plugins.
I would like to create a plugin that will allow user submission, user account login, slash registration
and a bunch of other features.
But let's add some finishing touches to this theme.
What I want to show you are just things we overlooked when we were creating the theme.
But these topics don't need a lecture of their own, so we'll be jumping around a little bit.
The first thing I want to do is replace these two attributes in the HTML tag I'm going to call a function
called Language Attributes, which will generate the HTML attributes we had previously.
This course assumes, you know, HTML, but I'll explain what these two attributes to the first attribute
created is called Dyax, which is short for direction.
This attribute will tell the browser whether or not the language used on the site is left to right or
right to left.
Most of the time, WordPress will not generate this attribute because most browsers by default assume
left to write.
The next attribute is called langue, which is short for language.
This attribute will specify what language the page is currently using.
This is beneficial because scripts and styles can display the content differently depending on the language
and the resources section.
I provide a link to more information about this attribute.
If you scroll down to these styling pages section, you'll see how this attribute is used using CSS.
You can check what language the page is using and update the CFS accordingly.
And this example, the default font family is Palazzi no linotype.
But if the language was Arabic and the font family would change to traditional Arabic, WordPress will
handle generating these attributes for you without a problem.
The next thing we want to do is create a meta tag with the care set attributes set to the Dalu return
by the function blog info.
In the resources section, I provide a link to this function, this function will return any value you
specify inside the function.
This function will return information about the current WordPress installation, such as the version
or language.
If you scroll down, you'll notice one of these is cassette, which is short for character set.
This is very important as it'll determine how a lot of your characters are displayed.
If you let the browser handle it, then some characters will be outputted differently than you'd like
by setting the characters that you instruct the browser to display it the same way every time.
That's it for the header.
I'm going to close this and open the single template and make a change inside the loop.
Every post is assigned an ID and classes.
I'm going to modify the route div tag inside the loop.
This tag encompasses everything about this post.
Create an ID attribute that begins with post dash.
Then I'm going to open up some tags and I'll put the ID.
This function will output the ID of the current post by doing this, the Post will always have a unique
ID.
I'm going to call a function called post class.
This function will output various classes for this post that plugins or your team can use to stylize
this post, I already have a few classes being outputted, so I'm going to put these inside this function
like so.
Now, these classes will be added onto the list of classes, that's about it for now.
There are still a few things we can do, but we can take care of that later.
Let's finish talking about the development and then move on to plug ins.