In order to use react, we need to use something called No James, no, James is a program that allows
you to run JavaScript on your computer or server.
The official description is no.
James is a JavaScript runtime built on chromes, Veidt JavaScript engine.
No, just uses an event driven, non blocking IO model that makes it lightweight and efficient.
No doghouses package.
Eco-System NPM is the largest ecosystem of open source libraries in the world.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the official Noga site.
I want you to download the latest version.
As of this course, the latest version is version 10.
If you see a newer version, then feel free to use that as well.
You'll also notice that there's an earlier version available for download, but that's only for those
who are unable to upgrade for one reason or another.
I've already installed no jobs on my computer, so I won't be going through the default installation.
Your installation should just be the default one.
You do not need to configure any of the settings.
All right.
So once you've installed no, James, let's explore what comes with it and how you can use it.
You'll be provided this program called No JS.
It should look something like this initially.
You may think this is a command prompt or terminal, but it isn't.
You can't run commands inside this program.
For example, if I were to run the commands else, then you'll see I get this error.
This program right here will allow you to run JavaScript code without having to create a file.
It's a great way to test things out really quick before you get into real or complex projects.
If I were to create a variable named Foo and assign its value to five, then I'll see this message called
undefined.
However, this variable I created is now available and I can get the value by simply typing in foo.
Every line of code you write here will be output it onto the console.
I'm going to exit out of this program as he won't be using it throughout this course.
I just wanted to show you this.
As you may want to test things out, feel free to play around with it.
The real power of No JS is the commands, modules and package Eco-System that comes with it.
I want you to open your text editor and pointed to any folder you want.
The great thing about no jazz is that you can use it anywhere on your system.
You don't have to use it in any particular folder.
That means you can use it in your documents, desktop or even Windows folder.
I'm going to keep things simple and continue working inside my HHG Docs folder.
I'm inside the folder called Node Dash Example.
Next, I'm going to create a JavaScript file called Index JS inside this file.
I'm simply going to console along the message.
Hello?
Then I want you to open your terminal and point it to this directory.
This is very important.
This will not work unless you're inside the same directory as your file.
I'm using Visual Studio Code and it automatically points to this folder whenever I open my terminal.
If you're not using visual studio code, then it's perfectly fine to use the command line that comes
with your operating system.
You may have to use the code and else commands to help you navigate around once you're inside this directory.
I then want you to run the following command node index.
After running this command, you'll see the message being outputted on to the console.
So what exactly is going on?
Let's take it one step at a time.
When you install no jass, you will be provided with a new command called node.
This command allows you to run a JavaScript file on your computer.
Actually, you don't even have to use a JavaScript file.
Let's just call the node command by itself.
What will happen is that no JS will turn your command line into a JavaScript environment on the spot.
So if I were to type the command ls then I'll get this error.
This is the same error we got last time.
This is basically the same as opening and using that program we used earlier to exit out of this.
You need to press control.
See on your keyboard.
The node command allows you to run JavaScript through the command line to take it a step further.
You don't have to use JavaScript inside the command line right after the node command you can pass in
the name of the file that contains your JavaScript code.
In our case, this would be the index JS file.
However, you don't have to pass in the file extension as node will automatically assume the file is
a JavaScript file.
Once you run, this command node will run whatever JavaScript is inside this file and this example.
All we did was output a simple message.
I'm going to move up one directory using the CD command, then I'm going to try and run the node index
command again right away.
I'll get an error saying that the file can't be found.
This is very important to highlight.
I have to be inside the same directory as this file to use this command properly.
Otherwise I'll just get an error if you want to.
You can just pass in the path and that will work as well.
For example, if I type in the following node will and run the file indexes.
However, I always recommend to just be in the same directory so you don't have to type as much.
It makes things easier.
I'm going to seed back into my directory.
This is just a basic example of what you can do with no JS.
You can run JavaScript on your computer instead of a web browser.
You can do so many things, such as work with the file system, create a web server or even create your
own commands.
The possibilities are endless for this course.
We won't be doing any of that.
The reason being is that we're already doing this kind of stuff in PHP, Apache and MySQL.
We also have WordPress that handles a lot of the logic for us.
So we don't need to use node for that kind of stuff.
So why are we using node?
Well, node can also help with organizing code and use advanced features that simply aren't available
in regular browsers.
These tools will also be helpful when developing blocks for Gutenberg.
Before we can do anything else, we need to understand how modules work and why they're needed.
There was one last thing I want to highlight.
You don't have to name your file in NextG.
Yes, you can name your files whatever you want.
You can name this Foo J.S. and run the command node foo which will run the JavaScript in that file.
All right, let's move onto modules in the next lecture.