And this lecture will be exploring what modules are and how to use them.
Right now I'm on the jury website.
You know what Jay Creary is?
You've used it before.
And it's fairly easy to use in order to use Jorquera on your site, you have to create some script tags
and pass in the path to the jury file.
The browser will automatically load this file for you and then you can use Jaquie anywhere on your site.
The process is pretty straightforward.
Unfortunately, this process only applies to the browser, for you can't use script tags to include
external JavaScript code.
The process is slightly different and requires a little bit of work.
And the resource section of this lecture I provide a link to the common site.
Common JS is a JavaScript module loader as it states here.
In other words, it's a way for you to load JavaScript code from external files.
You'll hear the word modules a lot throughout this course.
A module is just a fancy word for a JavaScript file that you include into your code.
I'm oversimplifying it, but that's basically what it is.
Common JS is a library that allows you to load JavaScript code with more JavaScript code.
You can think of it like loading a few file with the include or require functions.
This means you don't have to use HTML to load your files.
You can download this library and then load it in your browser to get started.
We won't be doing this.
This is because Node already uses the common JS format already.
Let's take a deeper look on the sidebar.
You'll find the link used with Node here.
You'll find information on how to use common G.S. with Node.
On this page, the developer tells you that node isn't using the common JS loader specifically.
Instead, Node is using its own implementation of common JS with the same format and concept.
The node module loader is very similar to the common JS module loader, but you need to understand that
they aren't one hundred percent the same.
What?
That being said, let's take a look at how to use the module loader, open the index JS file we created
earlier.
I'm going to comment about the code we had previously.
As I stated earlier, node already prepares the module load or library for you, so you don't have to
do anything to set it up.
You can get started with using modules right away.
There are usually three kinds of modules you'll be dealing with.
There are modules you create, modules that node creates and modules that other users create.
Let's get started with creating our own modules.
I'm going to create a file named Functions JS.
Inside this file, I'm going to create a symbol function named my funk, and all it will do is output
a hello world message.
All right, now I have two files which aren't connected to node, both of these files are considered
modules.
You heard that correctly.
All JavaScript files are considered modules.
As far as Node is concerned, the main module is what's called the entry point.
The entry point file is the very first file that should be executed by node.
The index file will be the entry file.
So we'll have to load the functions module into this file.
To do that, we have to first create a variable.
I'm going to name my variable FNC.
We will set this value to the value returned by the function require.
This function has one parameter, which is the name of the module you'd like to load.
I'm going to pass in the name of the file, which is functions.
You do not need to append the extension as node will always assume you want to load a JavaScript file.
However, we do have to prepend a dot forward slash.
This will tell no Jast that the module is located in the same directory as the file.
Keep in mind that the variable name can be named anything you want.
In most examples and tutorials, most developers tend to name their variables after the name of the
module in lowercase letters.
This single line of code will load a module and we can reference the module using this variable.
The question is what exactly gets loaded and how is it loaded?
This line of code won't technically work yet.
We have to now export our module before we can use it.
Exporting a module simply means that you're telling node what parts of your code can be used outside
of the file.
Let's explore how that works inside the functions file.
I'm going to use an object called module.
This object is defined for you by a. this object contains properties related to the current model it's
being used in, in our case, this would be the functions file.
Every single file is provided a module object with properties specific to that file.
As I stated earlier, every single file is considered a module.
As far as note is concerned, this module object has a property called exports, which you can assign
any value you want.
The value of this property determines what values other models can access from this module.
I'm going to set this to my func, which is the function above.
Now I can use the function inside the index file.
I'm going to call it.
I'll go over what's going on in just a moment, but first, let's check if this works.
I'm going to run the node index command again.
As you can see, the message was outputted without any error.
Let me recap what's going on here.
The very first thing we do is create a variable named FWC creating a variable is required if you want
to use a module, as this variable will act as a way to reference the code inside the module.
To load a module, you have to use the function, require this function, will load the module you pass
in.
In our case, this would be the functions file inside the functions file.
We have a variable named my func that is assigned to a function.
This function will output a message onto the console node, will load this module into the index file.
However, it will not load the variables, functions or objects from this file.
Instead, it'll look inside the module, exports property and just return the data inside that property.
So in order to pass in our data, we have to assign our data to this property.
Once the module is loaded, we can then just use the data from the module exports property freely.
In our case, this would be the function that outputs a message.
Lastly, we just call the function and the message will be outputted onto the console.
Let me prove this further.
I'm going to define a variable named Foo inside the functions file and assign its value to five.
Then I'm going to go back to my index file and try to log this variable.
If I were to run my command again, I'll get this error stating that the variable FUX is undefined,
even though this variable is defined inside the functions file and I'm loading the module, this variable
is not made available globally to every file that uses it.
In order to use this variable, we have to assign the module exports property to this variable.
Let's say I wanted to pass in multiple values to do this.
We can simply create an object and then assign the data like so.
Since we're returning an object, we have to update the index file to access those properties, change
funk to funk, dot my funk and to access the full property, we have to call it as Funk Dafu.
Let's run the command one more time and we should see the message being outputted along with the value
of food.
All right, so that's how you load code from one file into another.
I want to dig deeper, though.
Here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to comment up the food variable from being logged inside the index file.
Then I'm going to clear up my console, I'm going to console log the module object in both files.
Then I'm going to update my function to output a long list of equal signs so we can see the difference
between these two outputs.
After doing this, I want you to run the command node index.
And the output, you'll see two objects being outputted, as you can see, no takes care of setting
the values for both these modules.
Each object will have a property named filename which will let you know which module object belongs
to which file.
Both modules have an exports property.
If you take a look at the functions module, then you'll notice the export property is filled with both
the function and the foo variable.
These are the values that the index JS file will get when loading this module.
The index module has no exports, so the exports for that file will be an empty object.
Another thing I want you to notice is the parents property.
The parents property will tell you if the module is being loaded from another module.
As you can see, the functions module has the index module as its parent.
The index module has no parents because it is the entry point file.
However, the index module will have the children property, which will tell you what modules this module
is loading.
Something you should keep in mind is that children modules can and are allowed to load more modules.
This creates a module tree structure for the most part.
You never have to worry about these properties as node takes care of filling them out for you.
It's uncommon and not recommended that you modify any of these properties except for the exports property.
All right.
Now that we understand the basics of modules, let's explore some modules that node provides and third
party modules in the next lecture.