We've explored how to load modules in the previous lectures, but now it's time to learn how to use
an actual module, throughout this course we'll be using something called Web Pack.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the Web site.
WINPAC describes itself as a module bungler.
That's not very descriptive.
So allow me to explain further.
Gutenberg requires a lot of files in order for it to function correctly.
As you progressed through this course, you'll find that we'll have dozens of files created just for
the front end.
Loading all these files is bad practice as it can use up resources and hurt the performance of our site.
When PAC solves most of this by combining all your files together.
Let's say you had dozens of JS files for your plugin.
WINPAC will grab all those scripts and try to combine them into one or two files.
It'll also take care of Minifie and optimizing your code for you when PAC can do so much more.
By also combining your styles and compressing your images, it can also create a web server for testing
your site.
On the site.
You'll see that Web pack provides a simple diagram on how it works.
On the left, you'll see various files needed for your code to work.
This includes files from third party frameworks and libraries.
These files will be processed through Web pack and as a result, you'll have fewer files that are ready
to be used in production.
You'll notice that it also processes different file types.
So it's not just JavaScript success and HTML.
Westpac takes a little bit of work to set up initially, but I promise you that it's very easy once
you understand what's going on.
I want to highlight that we won't be using all of web packs features.
We don't need it server because we already have one.
We don't need to compress images or process access files.
We will solely focus on the JavaScript that web pack can help us with.
This is perfectly fine.
You don't have to use Web pack to its full extent.
A lot of the additional features are for developers who want to use Web Pappe with known as the back
end.
Since we're using P and WordPress, we don't need those extra features.
We just want help with the JavaScript code.
Using Web pack is completely optional.
However, as you may have noticed, I like to keep my code clean and organized.
Web pack will really help us with organizing and scanning our code.
I also want to use the latest JavaScript features which aren't available in modern browsers.
This is something we'll explore more as the course progresses.
Let's look at some examples you don't have to follow along.
Just watch.
Right now I'm on a site called Strandberg Guitars.
I'm going to open my developer tools and select the network tab.
We've talked about the network tab before.
It allows you to view the files loaded and how long it takes for those files to load.
I'm going to filter the results to only display JavaScript, then I'm going to completely refresh the
page and see what we get.
As you can see, there are dozens of files being loaded and the site takes some time to load.
Let's take a look at another example.
I'm on the Udemy site now.
I'm going to do the same thing as before.
Open the developer tools and refresh the page right away.
You'll notice one huge difference.
There are way less files being loaded and the site is loading faster.
You may or may not have noticed, but Udemy is a single page app.
Since it's a single page app, you don't have hundreds and hundreds of files that should be loaded.
However, the Udemy development team is very smart.
If the developers use web pack to combine all their files together, which reduces the amount of time
to load their site, I can actually prove this further.
If I click on one of these scripts, you'll see the preview appear on the right.
You'll notice the code has the key word web pack.
Web pack will load its own code to help you organize your code.
If you take a closer look, you'll notice that this file contains libraries such as angular and angular
carousel.
Usually you would expect these to be in separate files.
But with Westpac, we now have one individual file.
This is the power of Web page.
All right, let's get started with using Web pack.
Right now, I'm inside a folder called Web Pack Dash example.
I want you to create a folder and name it whatever you want.
I also want you to open your terminal and navigate to this directory.
I'm using Visual Studio Code, so my terminal will automatically point to this directory.
I'm going to run the command npm in it.
This is a subcommander that will help us generate a basic package file.
You'll see what this looks like in a moment.
After running, this command will be taken through a walk through to help you customize your package
file.
The first field is the name property node will usually recommend some default settings if you decide
to leave these fields empty.
I'm fine with the name, so I'm just going to press enter.
It'll then ask for a version.
I'm also fine with the default.
Then you'll be asked to enter a description.
Even though there is no default.
This value is also optional.
So I'm just going to keep moving forward.
It will then ask for the name of the entry point file by default.
This is set to index JETS'.
Keep in mind that you can name your entry point file whatever you want.
You can set this to Apgar's or even server.
Yes, I'm going to keep it simple and just leave it at the default which is indexed.
The next property is the test.
Command's tests do exactly what they sound like.
They will test your code for any bugs or errors.
However, we won't be doing that, so we'll will leave.
This empty git repository will also be empty since we won't be using git keywords.
Author and license will also be empty.
You'll be asked if the settings you set are fine.
I'm going to say yes and then press enter node will then generate a file called Packaged Dodgson.
Open this file and view the contents.
As you can see, all our settings are now set for the most part.
A lot of these properties are unimportant to us as we won't be using node heavily will only be using
it to help process and combine files.
You'll notice we have this property called scripts where we can define our own commands.
Will take a look at this later, but you should be aware that it contains the test command we were asked
to input earlier.
Since we input nothing, it'll just have this default text saying there was no test command.
Give it.
That's fine.
We won't be using this anyway.
So the default value is just fine as is.
You are allowed to create this file manually, but I always prefer using the command as it makes sure
there are no errors.
The reason we need this package file is because we will be installing and using various modules.
The package file will save the modules we use and even keep track of the versions used.
You won't be able to see the benefits in this lecture, but I assure you that it'll help us in the future.
For now, just make sure you have it.
All right.
Now we can install Web pack to install WINPAC.
You'll need to run the commands, npm install web pack, dash, dash, save, dash dev.
Let's stop right here for the most part, this isn't anything we haven't done so far to install Web
pack, we have to use the NPM install web pack commands.
However, we also have this dash, dash, save, dash, dev text right after it.
And this example, we're using the save dev flag.
This flag tells Node that it should save this module inside the package, adjacent file as it's a required
module.
You'll see what this looks like in just a moment.
All right, let's execute this command node will do its usual thing and install Westpac for us.
Once Westpac is installed, you'll see the node underscore modules up here, along with all the modules
required to make Westpac work.
I want you to open up the package, Jason, file, and you'll notice that there has been one change
to the file by using the save dev flag node will update the contents of this file by setting this property
called div dependencies.
This property contains a list of all modules we have installed.
The benefit of this is that we no longer have to worry about remembering the name of the module.
I want to show you something.
I'm going to delete the node underscore modules folder.
Let's imagine that I'm moving my files from one system to another, transferring modules can take a
bit of time to save some time.
You may want to ignore those files.
Luckily, you don't have to memorize all the names for each package.
Instead, if you have the package Jason file, then you can reinstall all the modules by just running
NPM install.
If you don't specify a module to install, the node will assume you want to install the dependencies
specified inside the package.
Jason File.
I'm going to run this command.
Just like that, I'll have Westpac installed again.
All right, there's one last thing I want to show you before we move on to configuring Westpac.
There are two kinds of dependencies, production dependencies and developer dependency.
Right now, we're using a developer dependency.
Developer dependencies are modules that are only meant for development.
Developer dependency should not be used on a life site.
Production dependencies, on the other hand, are meant to be used for live sites or projects.
I'm going to delete my node underscore modules folder and remove the property dev dependencies.
This time, I'm going to run the command npm, install web pack, dash, dash, save.
There are two flags for saving dependencies, I'm going to run this command and then go over the differences.
Once again, I'll have Watpac installed, let's view the package Jason file again, this time a new
property called Dependencies is created.
This property will contain modules for production only.
The dev dependencies will contain modules for development only.
You can specify what modules should be for production or development by using either the save or save
dash dev Flagg's respectively.
For the most part, it actually doesn't matter in our project because we won't be using node at all
for the production part of the site.
We're only using node for development purposes.
So I just use the save dev flag.
I'm going to delete the node underscore modules folder again and remove the dependencies property.
Then I'm going to run the NPM, install web pack, dash, dash, save, dash, dev, command again.
All right, that was a long introduction, and I know it was a lot to go through, but that's the basics
of getting started with Westpac and the next lecture, we're going to be getting configuring Web back.
Oh.