It's time to learn about Westpac loaders and bable, it is completely possible to use the latest tools
on libraries without note and Westpac, there is a problem with this.
The first is that you'll end up writing more code than usual to accomplish a lot of the things you'd
like to do.
In truth, we're already writing a lot of code just to accomplish these tasks.
However, this is just for setting things up.
Once you have everything set up, you don't have to worry about viewing this code for quite a while.
On the other hand, if you were to try to do these things without these tools, you'll find that you'll
constantly have to update multiple files.
This becomes very hard to manage.
It's just not worth it.
In the end, I highly encourage you to keep pushing through on learning these tools as they will speed
up development.
We're almost close to finishing up the basics before we can learn how to integrate all of this with
WordPress.
The next tool we need to learn is Bable.
Babel takes JavaScript to the next level and the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link
to the official Bable site.
What Bable will do is allow you to write JavaScript that is not implemented in both browsers and note
it will then convert that code into code that the browser or node can understand.
This may seem strange because Web pack seems to do something similar to this.
That's true, but web pack doesn't cover every single feature will need web pack just covers the basics.
By using Bable, we are rest assured that we cover everything.
It's important to note that Bable and Web pack are two completely different tools.
You can use Bable without Watpac and vice versa.
However, these two work very well together and using them both is very easy.
In order to use Bable, we have to load three different modules, Bable is a very modular tool, meaning
that the code is split up into different modules so you can pick what you want to use and leave the
rest behind.
Usually you'll end up using a minimum of three bable modules.
The first module is the Bable Dash core.
This is the heart of Bable.
This module has the core functionality in order to make everything bable related work.
This module will take care of reading your code and then transforming it into code that the browser
can understand.
The second module is the Bable Dash loader module.
This module makes it easy to connect web pack and bable together.
It handles a lot of the work for you.
All you have to do is load and then configure it inside the config file and everything else will be
connected.
The last module will vary depending on what you want.
Basically the bable dash core module is just a way for you to read and parse JavaScript code.
However, it doesn't handle what should and shouldn't be converted.
S6 isn't the latest version of JavaScript.
There's also S7 and escaped.
The latest versions are barely supported in browsers.
Or note, iOS six is considered to be the next standard in web development.
With that being said, if you wish, you can use E seven or eight.
However, for this course we will only be using S6 code.
There are various models with their own set of rules for converting code, if you were to go to the
Babel site under Dock's, you'll find a link to the official plug ins you can use.
There are two types of plug ins, experimental and official.
We won't bother with using experimental plugins as we don't need to go that far under, the official
said.
You'll find a list of modules to use.
So which one do we use?
Well, it really depends on what you want to use.
However, for most cases, the bable dash preset dash in the module is the recommended one.
It's usually reviewed by the team of people and is considered the most stable and usable module out
of them all.
Let's get started with all these modules.
I'm going to enter the following commands.
NPM install dash dash save dash dev bable dash core bable dash loader bable dash preset dash N.V..
This may take a while.
Pause the video if you need to wait.
You may get a couple of warnings, and that's perfectly fine, a good way to confirm if a module was
installed is by looking at the package.
Jason File Noad will usually add your modules to the dependency list if the module was installed successfully.
It's a good indicator of determining if your modules are good to go.
All right.
We can now use Bable as a loader.
What exactly are loaders?
Web pack has a feature called Loaders.
Loaders are a way to extend the way Watpac functions.
It's the same idea for using WordPress hooks you are allowed to load in certain code that will modify
the final result in some fashion.
The Bable dash loader module we installed earlier makes it easy to integrate Bable with Web pack.
All we have to do is update our config file to use this module inside the config file.
Create a new property called module.
Since we're using a third party module, we need to set this property.
This property allows you to modify how third party modules are used with Westpac.
Keep in mind that Bable is technically a module.
So if we want to load the Bable module, we have to set up this property.
Westpac will take care of loading it for you.
All we have to specify is what modules should be loaded with Westpac.
The value of this property will be an object which will contain even more properties about how modules
work with Westpac.
The only property I want to set is the rules property.
This will be an array of modules we want to use with Westpac.
To load a module, you have to create an object like sell.
Each object in this array will represent a module.
We only have one module, which is the Bable dash loader.
We installed three modules, but the Bable loader module is the module that allows us to connect Bable
with Westpac.
To specify a module, you need to set the use properly to Bable Dash loader.
This will tell Westpac to look for a module called Bable, the ash loader, the Bable dash loader will
take care of the rest with connecting the other two modules together.
There is one last thing I want to do before finished with configuring Watpac, I want to set a property
called Test.
Watpac is not just for JavaScript.
Watpac will also apply to images and stylesheets.
Since we're using Bable, Bable will be applied to images and stylesheets.
However, Bable does not process or work with images and stylesheets will get errors on top of that
web page can also be applied to other extensions and file types.
If it's configured to do so.
We only want people to work on JavaScript files to make sure Bable will only work with JavaScript files.
Then we'll have to set this property.
The value of this property will be a regular expression.
The regular expression will be forward.
Slash backslash dot.
Just percent forward slash.
If you're unfamiliar with regular expressions, then I highly recommend you take the time to study the
regular expressions are kind of beyond the scope of this course as they're complicated to explain.
All this will do is make Web pack, use bable for JavaScript files only.
All right.
That's it.
There was one last thing we need to do before everything will work.
We need to create a file named Dot Bable RC.
It's very important that you name it this there is no file extension, it's just Bable Arcy.
Inside this file, you can configure how works.
You have to create an object and the property you want to set is the Presets property.
You simply pass in an array of modules that contain rules on how to modify the output of JavaScript.
To put it simply, you pass in the bable, dash, preset, dash and module.
Babel will look at this array and will load the modules inside this array, the Babel dash precent Dash
V is a module that will look at your code and tell people how it should convert that code into something
that browsers can understand.
It's important that you make one distinction between these two files.
The web config files allows you to control how Web pack works.
The module property allows you to make the bridge between Web pack and a third party module.
However, it does not completely control that module.
Bable needs its own configuration file so you can specify exactly how it'll work.
All right, that's it.
Let's test things out.
I'm going to run the NPM run start command.
You should receive no errors, let's view the HTML file again and see if we still see the message being
outputted.
We can also view the bundle James file, and you'll find it's exactly the same as before.
The reason for this is because we aren't using any advanced features of JavaScript yet.
This will lead us into the next lecture.
We're going to begin using some of the new features that JavaScript has to offer.
I'll see you in the next lecture.