Essex six comes with a lot of features we like to use.
I'm only going to show you what you'll need right at the start.
There are more features than the ones I'm about to introduce, but also use those as the course progresses.
And this lecture, we're going to start talking about the changes to variables.
I'm going to be working inside the index file, make sure any code inside this file is commented out.
As you may know, variables are created using the VA keyword.
I'm going to create a variable named Foo and assign it to the string.
Hello.
Then I'm going to log this variable.
This is pretty basic, but it's very difficult to control.
This is a problem with JavaScript.
It's a very relaxed language and it's not strict at all.
You could just turn on strict mode, but that only does so much.
Right after we define this variable, we can change the value of it to something like the number five.
And this example, that's fine and all, but it becomes a problem when you're working with larger applications
throughout this course will be loading hundreds of JavaScript variables and you'll find yourself needing
more control than usual.
I'm going to run the command node app again next.
You'll see that the number five is being outputted, this is the expected behavior so far, even though
there are different ways to define variables, it's not like those methods are completely replacing
the VA keyword.
Using the VA keyword is still completely valid JavaScript code and will continue to be supported for
many years.
I just wanted you to be aware of that.
All right.
Let's start things off by learning about the CONSED keyboard.
The key consed is short for constant constants in JavaScript work the same exact way constants work.
And I assume for the most part you understand what constants are constants allow you to create variables
that never change.
They can never be changed after being defined.
If you try to change the value of a constant, then you'll be given an error and the value would still
stay the same.
Using a constant is fairly easy.
All you have to do is change the key word from var to const.
That's all you have to do, everything else is still the same.
You can set the constant to any kind of value you want.
It can be a string, no array and even an object.
Let's test this out by running node app index.
After running, this will get an error, the error is telling us that you can't change the value of
a constant, which is what we're doing in our code.
I'm going to comment out this code and then run the command again.
After running, it will see no errors and the concept is working as expected throughout this course,
you'll see me using constants a lot.
Actually, if you were to view any tutorials or look at other people's code, then you'll notice that
constants are widely adopted.
You'll definitely get a lot of practice using constants and you'll be fairly confident using them by
using constants.
We assure ourselves that we have more control over how our variables are set.
So far, we've only tested this with note.
Using constants on browsers is a different story.
I'm going to run my code through web pack.
You should see a success message.
Let's check out the page if you look at the console and you'll see the number of being outputted onto
the console.
Here's the thing, constants on its six feature Web pack and bable, help make sure your code is compatible
with all browsers, including older ones.
Most modern browsers already support S6, but older browsers don't.
Unfortunately, Westpac doesn't have a way to force or simulate this behavior for you, so it has no
choice but to convert the const keyword to VAR.
So you may be thinking what is the point of using S6 if it's going to be converted for backwards compatibility?
Well, there are two reasons.
The first reason is to be able to write code for the future.
That may seem weird, but eventually iOS six will be compatible with all browsers.
One hundred percent.
You'll want to prepare for this.
So when the time comes, you'll have to make very little changes to your code base.
If you were to continue writing code with early versions of JavaScript, you'll find yourself behind
the pack and spend a lot of time updating your code base.
You don't want that.
The second reason is that S6 provides a lot of security and control over your code.
A lot of the tools and libraries you'll be using are written in S6.
Whether you like it or not, this kind of forces you to write your code to be S6 ready.
Since you're loading so much code, you should take extra precautions.
You only want to allow code that should be able to modify your data.
If you keep using var, you'll eventually find yourself in this situation where your code may not behave
the way you expect it to.
There's a lot to be said, but I'll leave it at that.
Let's move on to the next way of creating variables along with constants.
You can also create block scope level variables.
That's a big phrase.
Let me break down what that means.
S6 introduces the key word.
Let's let is another way of creating variables.
I'm going to create a variable named bar and assign its value to ten.
Using let is as simple as changing the key word var to let just like last time, you can create any
kind of variable you want, you can use let four strings, numbers, arrays, objects, etc. I'm going
to log the bar variable and then I'm going to run this script through node.
As expected will see the number 10 outputted, I'm going to create a conditional statement, this conditional
statement will always be true.
Inside this conditional statement, I'm going to reassign the bar variable to five.
Run the command again.
We should get no errors and as expected, will see the number five instead of 10, what exactly does
that do?
Here's where it can come in handy.
I'm going to move my bar variable definition inside my conditional statement like so.
Let's try running the command one more time and see what we get.
You'll receive an error stating that BA is undefined, this can seem strange at first, but it's not.
Once you understand what's going on, let makes it so only code that is on the same level as where it's
defined, you can change it.
And this example, we define the bar variable inside this block statement only code inside this block
statement can access and change the variable bar.
Once this block statement is finished running, then the bar variable is destroyed.
This means we can't access it outside the block statement like we do in this log function.
Previously, everything was working fine when the variable was defined outside the block statement.
That's because the variable was available globally.
This is the power of let variables.
You can control how far a variable can be controlled.
In a way, it adds an extra layer of security.
I'm going to move the bar variable back to the global scope and get rid of this conditional statement.
Lastly, I'm going to run it through Westpac.
Let's review the code on the browser again, as you can see, both variables were outputted with no
errors.
That's basically it for variables.
This is just the basics of these two keywords.
You'll find that both keywords are used in a lot of design patterns for their benefits.
This course is not really a JavaScript course.
I know that may seem weird because for the past two lectures we've done nothing but use JavaScript.
However, I'm only introducing you to the fundamentals and basics of JavaScript.
JavaScript definitely has a lot to offer and I encourage you to learn more about it after you finish
this course.
In the next few lectures will finish things up with arole functions and modules.