He has six modules and the structuring are two new features introduced in JavaScript in this lecture
will be learning both of these.
It's important to know that these two features are completely independent of each other.
You can use either feature without the other.
With that being said, it's actually common practice to use these two features together.
We will be exploring how that's done to start things off.
I want you to create a file named Functions, James.
In previous lectures, we would load modules using the require function for node.
This was perfectly fine.
However, we want to use this code on the browser.
Using the require function is the common method of loading modules.
This is perfectly acceptable for node modules, but I want these files to load on the front where common
JS modules are not supported natively.
S6 modules are the official way to load modules in JavaScript.
Creating and using modules is fairly easy.
We'll just have to do things differently.
Let's start with the functions file.
This file will be a module for the index file.
I'm going to create a constant named halo that will be set to an arrow function.
The arrow function will just console log a simple message.
To export a model and the style of S6, we will have to use the export default keywords.
Right after this, we have to specify what we want to export.
I want to export the hello constant with six modules.
You can export multiple values to export a value.
You just need to use the export keyword.
You can actually just use the export key word by itself.
But if we were to remove the default key word, then we would get an error.
I want to explain why, but it's kind of hard to explain without learning about what the structuring
is first.
For now, let's pretend you can only export one value and to export that value you need both the export
and default keywords.
And this example, we're going to pretend that we can only export this halo function.
This is all you need to do in order to export a module.
Let's learn how to import this module.
Go back to the index file.
I'm going to input the following import functions from Dotzler function Jase's.
Let me break down what's going on here to import a module, you need to use the import keyboard.
This key actually does two things.
It will import a module and give you the opportunity to assign the module a variable name.
All expand more on this in just a moment.
The next thing that you need to do is specify where that module can be found.
Use the key word from to let JavaScript know you want to specify the path to the module to specify a
path relative to this module.
You have to use the dart forward slash followed by the name of the module.
In this case, it would be the functions file.
This one line of code will import the module, then you can just use it normally.
If we did everything correctly, then we should be able to run the NPM run, start command without any
errors.
Let's test this by opening the index HTML file and checking the console, you should see the message
being outputted.
This is a very basic example on how to export and import modules.
When it comes to exporting modules, you will most likely be writing this kind of syntax 90 percent
of the time.
However, for importing modules, the syntax will vary.
I want to go more in-depth into that, but we first need to learn what de structuring is.
The restructuring is a very simple concept to understand and use.
These structuring allows you to extract properties from objects and arrays into their own standalone
variables.
Let's look at an example.
I'm going to insert this code right below here.
I'm going to create a variable named LBJ and this will be an object with two properties called Prop
one and Prop two.
I'm going to set Prop one to five and Prop two to 10.
Now, I'm going to log Propp to.
To access a property, you have to specify the object and then follow it up with the property name.
However, doing it like this can get rather annoying.
In a regular application, you may end up having dozens of objects and it would be annoying to have
to constantly type each object and its property.
This also makes your code less readable and gives it a nested feeling.
Before we hand the structuring.
You would usually do something like this.
You would create a variable and assign its value to the property.
That's fine and all, but it can become increasingly annoying each time you have to do this.
This is where destruction comes into play.
To structure a variable, you need to do the following.
You can use any of the variable keywords and then follow it up with a pair of curly brackets by adding
these curly brackets.
You're telling JavaScript you want to grab properties and put them into their own variable.
You simply pass in the name of the properties, which are Prop one and Prop two.
You have the option of de structuring all the properties or just a select few.
The next thing you need to specify is which object where these properties can be found, which is OBJ.
This line of code does the same thing as the line above it does.
I'm going to comite out the traditional way of doing this.
Then I'm going to update my log function to use the prop to variable, rather than accessing the object
variable, run the NPM run start command, you shouldn't receive any errors.
Check out the index template to see if a number 10 is being outputted.
By itself, this really is an impressive this is a super simple feature.
It was introduced because it makes you write less code and I would say it's more or less readable than
the previous method.
I'm going to comment this out.
While the structuring can be used by itself, you will usually see it used with importing modules.
I'm going to go back to my functions file and I'm going to export a variable named NUM with a value
of five.
We will no longer pretend that we can only export one thing to export multiple pieces of data, you
can just use the export keyboard followed by the name and the value.
I'm going to stop right there.
JavaScript requires that you export a name and value.
If we were to just export the number five by itself, then we would get an error.
You are expected to export a name and value pair.
You cannot just export a value and you cannot just export a name.
If I were to restore this and remove the number five this time, then I would get an error from webapp.
This is super important to understand.
I have to pass in a name and a value.
This is why you would get an error if you were to just export the helo function without the default
keyword.
You were only giving value, but you're not giving it a name.
JavaScript doesn't care that you define the variable above.
You have to give it a name and value on the same line.
So what does the default keyword do that the default keyword allows you to give a default exported value.
You are allowed to export multiple values.
Since you can export multiple values, then you also have the option of importing all those values or
some of those values or just one of those values.
Inside the import statement, you can specify what value you'd like to import.
And this example, we're actually not specifying any particular data.
Even though we have a halo function inside the functions file.
This line will not grab the halo function.
Instead, it'll grab the default value.
With that being said, I don't have to name this halo inside my import statement.
This is just a reference.
Since it's a reference, I can change this to whatever name I want.
I can change this to Foo and then I can update my code to reflect that change.
And this would still work.
This line is saying, hey, I want to import some code from the functions files.
I'm not specifying any particular data.
So give me whatever the default export value is.
I want you to assign the value, return it to a variable named Foo to prove this further, I'm going
to run the NPM Run start command.
I didn't receive any errors then I'm going to view the page again.
You should see the message still being outputted like before, even though you can name the imported
value, whatever you want, it's common practice to name an after the value that's being exported so
it can be easier to understand.
I'm going to change my values back to hello.
The question is, how do we import specific values from a module?
This is where the structuring comes into play.
I'm going to change my hello to a pair of curly brackets.
What will happen is that JavaScript will return an object.
Each property in that object will be each value.
You export it.
You can use the structuring to grab a certain value.
I want to grab my num value.
What this will do is extract that num value and make it into its own variable.
We can then log this variable like so.
I'm going to run the NPM run start command.
There should be no errors thus far.
The number five should be outputted onto the page.
Let's say I wanted to give my imported value a custom name that's relatively easy.
All you have to do is use the as keyword and then follow it up with a custom name.
Then you can use this custom name throughout your code like.
So I'm not a fan of custom names, so I'm going to remove this.
Let's say I wanted to import both the default value and another value.
There are two ways you can go about this.
The first way is by using the asterisk character and then assigning this to a custom name, using the
as keyword.
I'm going to set this to functions.
What this will do is grab all the export and values and assign them as properties to the functions variable,
you can then access to values by their names like.
So if you want to grab the default value, then that is stored under the default property.
Of course, this does mean you will end up writing more code, which isn't what we want.
The second method of getting the value is to just comma separated right before the restructuring.
I'm going to just add hello.
Keep in mind that by not using these structuring, you won't have the ability to specify what value
you want to use.
So JavaScript will just assign this to the default value.
Now, you can use both the halo function and num variable by themselves without having to access it
from an object.
There are a couple more things I want to cover.
You do not have to export a default value.
You can just export the HALO function without assigning it to the default.
I'm going to get rid of the default keyword.
I cannot simply leave it like this.
I have to set a name and a value.
So I have to move this function into the export statement for this to work.
I'll now have to update my import statement, I have to use the structuring since there is no default
value.
Let's see what happens.
If I were to not use the structuring and try to call the helo function, I'm going to run my NPM run
start command.
Westpac will throw an error or stating that there was no default value in order for this to work, we
have to use these structuring.
I'm going to add my curly brackets back in and run the command again.
Then I'm going to view my page as expected, this will output the message, there are a couple more
things we can go over, but this is just the basics.
I know it can seem overwhelming because you can use this in a number of combinations.
I promise you, we will get a lot of practice using this as it's extremely common to use as six modules
and restructuring.
For the most part, you won't have to worry about using a lot of the trickier parts of modules or restructuring.
We're going to keep it really simple and just export some default values.
The examples I show you are super simple, but I assure you that these features are extremely helpful
in more advanced apps.
For now, let's move on to the next lecture and learn about react.