And the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to WordPress as Options API Codex Page,
this is what WordPress has to say about the options API.
The Options API is a simple and standardized way of storing data in the database.
The API makes it easy to create access, update and delete options.
All the data is stored in the WP underscore options table under a given custom name.
This page contains the technical documentation needed to use the options API.
To put it simply, it's a way for us to create options for plug ins and themes.
If you created some web apps, you're probably used to creating a table for your settings.
While this may seem appropriate for your own web apps, it's overkill for WordPress.
A lot of WordPress sites will have dozens of plug ins installed.
It would be pretty hard to maintain the database if every plugin and thing created their own set of
tables with settings.
WordPress has standardize these types of situations by providing the options API.
The Options API will provide an easy way to create, retrieve, update Angelie options and or settings.
Here's what we're going to do.
We will create an admin page with settings related to the recipe plug in the settings will determine
whether or not a user has to be registered to create a recipe or rate one.
I want you to open the activation file.
I'm going to start using the Options API right away before we can edit the settings we need to create
them.
Create a variable called recipe ops.
This variables value will be set to the value returned by the function get option.
This is the first function in the Options API.
This will simply retrieve the value of an option.
The option I want to retrieve is called our ops.
This option doesn't exist, or at least it shouldn't, when the user first activates the plug and if
this option doesn't exist, WordPress will return false next inside a conditional statement.
I'm going to check if this value is false.
It's very important that we do this if a user deactivates and reactivates, does plug in, then we could
end up overriding their settings if they previously activated the plug in.
At this point, the user is activating the plug in for the first time.
I'm going to create an array called Ops.
This array will have a few key value pairs.
I'm going to create two values named rating login required and recipe's submission login required.
Both values will be set to one, which will mean No.
Two, for yes, if the user is required to be logged in to submit or rate a recipe.
Now it's time to add the option into the database.
We're going to call a function called add option.
This function has two parameters, the name of the option and its value.
The name will be our ops.
The value will be the array we just created.
One thing I should be clear on is that you don't have to set the option, as in Iran, you can use any
value you want.
It can be a boolean integer or just a plain string.
However, I want you to use an array, as I don't want to create two different options.
It's much easier to have one option with an array of values.
Now that we're finished, let's deactivate and reactivate this plugin.
You should receive no errors.
To confirm if the option was saved open highest.
Well, I'm going to navigate to the WordPress database and open the WP options table.
I know for a fact that this is the table where options are stored, because that's what was stated in
the documentation, since I know we just created this option, I can then go to the very last row and
see if the R opts option was created.
As you can see, it was created.
The value was pretty weird.
Don't worry about this.
WordPress has to format an array so that it can fit inside the database properly.
All our values are serialized during input and then convert it back to an array when we need it.
In the next few lectures will start creating a page for the plugin settings.
This special page will allow users to update the plugin options.