It's time to update the settings, we'll be taking a look at a special kind of action hook and the resource
section, I provide a link to the admin, underscore post, underscore hook, codex page.
As you can see, this hook is a bit more dynamic than other hooks.
WordPress provides a format for this hook.
It's admin underscore post underscore followed by the action name.
The action name is defined in our form.
In the previous lecture, we created a hidden input field with the name of action and a value of our
save options.
So here's what will happen when we submit this form.
If a request is sent to admin post FTP, the admin underscore post underscore hook will run.
WordPress will check for a post or get variable named action and dependent's value to the admin underscore
post underscore look to determine which function to run inside the admin init function.
I'm going to add the action hook here.
Since we named the hook our save options.
The name of this hook will be admin.
Underscore post.
Underscore our underscore save underscore options.
The function I'm going to run will be called our save options, as you can see, it's the same name
as the action.
You don't have to do this.
You can name this function whatever you want.
I do this because it's much simpler to know which function belongs to which action with the hook ready.
We have to create the file next inside the process folder.
I'm going to create a file called Save Option.
Stop and define the function inside this file.
Now, I'm going to include this file from the main plug and file.
Inside the function, I want you to output the post rate, I'm going to echo out some pretext to format
it and then I'm just going to kill the scripts.
Let's refresh the options page, we should see everything working just fine, go ahead and select some
options.
If we submit this form, you'll see our data being neatly outputted and formatted for us.
Now that we've confirmed our form is being properly submitted, we should check if it's being submitted
by a trusted user.
There are two steps we're going to take to prevent malicious behavior.
First, we're going to check the user's current capabilities.
In an earlier lecture, we talked about capabilities and roles briefly.
We'll be using the same capability we used the last time to display this page.
Let's empty out our function.
And then inside the conditional statement, I want you to call the function current user can.
This function is provided to you by WordPress, what it will do is check the current logged in users
capabilities and see if that user can perform a certain capability passed in by you.
Since we want to use the same capability we use to display the page, I'm going to grab that capability
from the menus function and just paste it in here.
I'm going to check of this function returns false, and if it does, I'm going to kill the script.
Using WP died inside the day function.
I'm going to pass in a simple message and make it translatable.
This is one way to prevent attacks.
Next, we're going to check the nonce WordPress generated for us.
This is pretty simple.
WordPress provides a function called check admin referrer.
This function must be passed in the nonce we created inside the form we called this Norns our options
verified.
So let's pass that into the function.
This function will check not only the nonce, but the page that was referred were not going to put this
function inside a conditional statement because this function will simply kill the script if it turns
out to be false.
We can now start processing the form data and save it.
We're going to grab the R opts option so that we can override its options.
The variable should be called recipe opts.
All I'm going to do is update the options with the post values, I'm going to be using a function called
ABB's into this function, does two things.
It returns a value that is an integer and is an absolute value.
This function is also provided to you by WordPress, and I highly recommend it that you use it.
However, you should know that the options API will sanitize all values for you anyway.
Next, we're going to use a function called update option.
This function has two parameters, which is the name of the option to update and the updated value after
updating the option.
It's time to redirect the user back to the settings page.
WordPress provides a handy function called WP Redirect for this purpose.
The function accepts one parameter, which is the Eurorail to redirect to.
I'm going to use the admin neural function so that we always get the admin URL.
Even if the user changed in the WordPress installation.
This function has one parameter as well, which is the path relative to the admin Yooralla.
I'm going to copy and paste the URL from the URL bar and pasted in here like Selm.
I'm also going to pass in an extra get variable called Stenness and set its value to one by doing this
I can shake up this value is set and if it is, I can display a message about the status of the update.
I'll show you what I mean soon.
Let's try submitting the form.
And if everything worked out, we should see no errors and be redirected back to the options page.
Perfect.
Now we face two more problems.
Our fields aren't showing the updated values and there's no message to let the user know that the update
was a success.
You might have already guessed what you would have to do in order to display our options and its values.
I want you to pause the video and try to figure out a way for the input fields to have the current values
input.
If you already have the knowledge to figure this out, go ahead and try to solve this issue.
Welcome back.
If you figured it out, then that's great if you didn't.
That's fine as well.
We'll go over how to do it together first inside the options page function.
We're going to grab the option using the get option function and store the return value in the recipe
opts variable.
Now, all we have to do is reflect the values onto the input fields for these select menu.
We're going to use a ternary operator.
This is special to me and not WordPress, we're going to check if the values are equal to two.
If it is, then will echo out selected for the second option.
We won't do this for the first option since browser's will set the default value to the first option,
let's refresh the page and see if everything works.
Everything seems perfect.
The last thing we need to do is display the message after a successful submission.
Right above the form tags, insert some tags, we're going to use a conditional statement and check
if the status quo is set in the get variable and we're going to check if its value is equal to one.
If this conditional statement is true, then we're going to display a success message.
Refresh the page and we should now see the success message, this was very simple to do in the next
lecture, we're going to recreate this using these settings API.
I know that seems strange, but just go with me on this one.
I'll see you in the next lecture.