The Settings API is an API I'm not particularly fond of, but that doesn't mean it's not used.
What the settings API allows you to do is create a form that will be handled by WordPress.
This means that you don't have to do what we did in the previous lectures.
You don't have to process the form yourself, manage the options or create your own UI.
The settings API is meant to solve all of that.
Now keep in mind that it's completely optional to use the settings API.
Creating your own UI is completely acceptable.
It's a common route for developers to use.
I highly prefer creating my own UI and processing the data myself.
With that being said, you may prefer to use the Settings API.
This lecture is meant to introduce you to the API and how it works.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the Settings API Plugin Handbook chapter.
This page describes the Settings API in detail.
If you scroll down, they even talk about why you should use the settings API.
The benefits are that it provides visual consistency, it's future proof and it means less work.
It takes care of handling form, submission, security measures and data sanitisation.
Feel free to read over this chapter.
Let's get started with the Settings API.
The very first thing I'm going to do is open the options page.
I'm going to place the settings API form right below our custom one so that we can compare the item,
add a horizontal line separator and then create another form.
This form will have two attributes, which are action and method, the method will be post, the action
will be option stop.
This is the first difference right here, the custom uniform has an action of admen dash postop request
that will be handled and processed by you should be sent to the admin dash post file.
The options stop is exclusively for the settings API.
Keep in mind that WordPress will handle all the form submissions and data sanitisation for you, so
you'll have to send the data to the options PHP file if you plan on using the settings API.
All right.
Moving on inside this forum, we're going to call three functions.
The first function is the settings fields.
This function will output some hidden fields that will help with security and help WordPress identify
what group of options are being submitted.
Option groups are an important concept to remember.
It's really confusing to beginners, but I'll try my best to explain it.
If you look inside the activation file, we create a single option and assign its value to an array.
This array has multiple settings, but to WordPress it's all considered one single row in a database.
If we wanted to, we could have created two options by calling the ADD option function twice and storing
these value separately rather than inside of an array.
That's an acceptable situation to WordPress, it's what WordPress does with its own settings.
It's why when you open the options database table, you saw many individual values rather than arrays
go to the admin dashboard and under the settings menu, select any page I'm going to select general.
Each field in this form has its own option or database.
Wrote in the options table, for example, the site title has its own row.
The tag line also has its own row, so on and so forth.
It's a lot of settings, but it just means that WordPress considers each value important enough to have
its own row in the options database table.
In our case, I don't consider each plugin setting important enough to have its own row in the database.
I just group them all together.
It's easier to manage.
And remember, here comes the problem with creating individual rows for each setting.
WordPress is completely unaware of certain options are related to one another.
Back to the Settings page.
You'll notice that even though these are separate options, they're all grouped and managed together
in this single form.
In order for this to work, WordPress requires that they be grouped together.
This is where option groups come in to play.
Even though each value exists in its own row, they can be grouped together so that WordPress can keep
track of everything.
When you create an option group, you make it easier for WordPress to know which field belongs to which
section and which section belongs to which page.
You'll see how we generate sections and fields in just a second.
Back to the options page.
I'm going to pass in a custom option group called our Ops Group.
Any options assigned to this group will be managed.
Here is what I'm telling WordPress now that WordPress knows what group of options are going to be managed.
I can begin creating the fields themselves.
The next function I want to call is do setting sections.
This will output the actual input fields themselves, we have to tell WordPress what sections we'd like
to output this function, accepts the page name.
Since this is a custom page, we can input a custom page name.
The page name will be our ops sections.
We haven't talked about sections, but sections are a way to group individual input fields.
Together you can have multiple sections, so this function will get all sections that are grouped together.
If that seems confusing, don't worry.
You'll see how it works in just a moment.
The last function I want to call is Submit Button.
This will generate a submit button that is style to work with the form.
It's very simple.
Keep in mind that you don't have to call these functions.
We could if we wanted to create the fields and buttons ourselves, however, that would defeat the purpose
of using the settings API in the first place, since its job is to handle everything for us.
That's it for the form.
Let's begin registering everything.
The Settings API instructs us that we have to register everything from the admin in it.
Hook open this function now just to keep things organized.
I'm going to separate the registration from the rest of the code, create a new file named Settings
Dash API and define the function are settings API.
Include this file from the admin init function and then just call this function at the very end of the
function.
We can now put all our code inside the newly defined function, the first step is to register the new
settings, call the function register setting, pass in the option group name, which is our ops group,
and the actual option, which is our ops.
This function will tell WordPress that the our option is assigned to the group, our ops group.
This function needs to be called for as many options we have.
For example, if we have three options, we call this function three times where the second argument
is for each option, the group should always be the same if all the options are going to be displayed
on the same page.
For instance, if I had something like option two and option three, then I would pass that in like
so.
However, since we saved our option as an array, we only have one row in the database as a result,
we only have to call this function once.
Now that we've called this function WordPress, we'll know that the our absorptions will be handled
by the Settings API.
The next step is to create a section.
A section is a way to group individual fields.
A single page can have multiple sections and each section may have multiple fields.
It's just a way to keep things organized since we only have two fields in the array.
We only really need one section called the Function and Settings section.
This function has four parameters, the first parameter is a custom ID, I'm going to keep it simple
and name it recipe settings.
The second parameter is a readable name, which will be outputted onto the screen.
Set this to recipe's settings.
The third parameter is a function that will be called before the fields are displayed, set this to
our settings section.
Define this function right below an echo out the text, you can change the recipe settings here.
You can output whatever you want, most developers will just output some text that will help users out
when filling out the form.
The last parameter is the name of the page.
This will appear on in our case.
We named it our section.
Any fields assigned under this section will appear on the page.
This section is assigned to you in the options page.
We called the do setting section function, which will output any sections that are assigned to the
page are section.
This is how you connect the two.
Now that we have our sections, we can begin creating the input fields.
Creating fields is a pretty straightforward process.
Right after the section called the Function Add Settings Fields.
This function has quite a few parameters.
The first parameter is the ID for this field.
Technically, you can give this field any ID you'd like, but I'd like to assign it to the option that
that's relevant to this field will be related to the rating login required option.
The second parameter is the label text that will be displayed for this field.
I'm going to use the same text I used in the custom uniform.
The third parameter is the function that will be called for the actual input itself.
I like to use the same name as the ID with the addition of underscore input, underscore KVI where KB
stands for callback.
You'll see what this function does in a moment.
The fourth parameter is the page that this field belongs to.
This is the same as the name we passed in the DU setting sections function.
The fifth parameter is the name this section belongs to, which is the value you passed into the first
parameter of the ad settings section.
The next step is to define the function that we called in the third parameter, this function will output
the input field.
I'm going to ground the R opts option like before.
Then I'm going to borrow this bit of code from the custom form we created.
I want to change two things first, I want to create an ID, the ID should match the ID you assign in
the first parameter of the relative add settings, field function.
Next, I want to change the name attribute, it's very important that you name this attribute correctly,
the name will determine what option is updated in the database.
In our case, it would be the R ops option.
However, this option is not a single value.
If it was, then this would be perfectly acceptable to tell WordPress that we want to update a certain
key in the array.
We need to use square brackets and pass in the name of the key.
In this case, it would be rating login required.
It's very important that you name it correctly or the options will not be updated accordingly.
That's it for the first field.
I'm going to just copy everything from the first field and just update its values accordingly for the
second option.
I'm going to do the same with the function as well.
Your code should look similar to mine once you're finished adding the second field for the second key
in the props array.
We can now test the form, refresh the options page.
You should now see the form appearing right below without changing a value.
Try submitting the settings API form.
You should receive no errors and you should still have the same values in both forms.
Now try updating one field and save the changes.
You should see the change reflected in both forms.
These two forms do the exact same thing, but one is custom and the other is created using the settings
API.
There is no wrong answer here.
You'll find that plug ins and teams will use either solution.
Personally, I like to create my own UI.
I find it easier to manage, but you may not feel that way.
You may like to handle everything through PHP without having to worry about the success and javascript.
That's perfectly fine.
Use the solution that suits you.
Before I am this lecture, I want to do one more thing.
I want to sanitize these values myself.
Using the settings API doing that is very simple.
Go back to the Settings API file.
I'm going to minimize everything for a moment so that you can read the code better.
The Register's setting function has a third parameter, which is optional.
That can be taken advantage of.
The third parameter accepts a function that will sanitize the input when it's submitted.
The name of this function will be our opt sanitize.
To find this function at the very bottom, this function will be passed in the input.
This input should have two values.
All I'm going to do is sanitize both these values by running them through the ABS in function.
This will make sure the values, our numbers and our absolute.
Lastly, you just returned the input so that WordPress can update the option that pretty much wraps
it up for the Settings API.
We will keep working on this plugin, but I won't be using the settings API form anymore.
I'm just going to start out with HTML comments.