A problem has appeared that really isn't visible at first glance, if you take a look at the ED, you'll
see this button called ad media right above it.
This allows you to use the media uploader inside the text editor.
It's really useful, but not completely usable for everyone.
I want you to log out and then sign in as the test user we created earlier.
If you don't remember those credentials, then just create another account and try submitting a recipe.
You'll notice that the button we had previously is gone long out and logged back in as an admin.
So what exactly is going on?
Well, first, let's check out that capability's versus rules table.
First in the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to this page and table.
I've shown you this table before.
It lists all the roles and their capabilities.
By default, all new users are assigned to the subscriber role.
Unless you manually set it, scroll to the very bottom of the table and you'll see that the subscriber
roll only has one capability which is read.
In order to see the ad media button, you need the capability upload files.
This is a very important concept to understand.
WordPress doesn't care very much about what role a user is in.
It cares more about their capabilities.
WordPress, plug ins and themes will check your capability over your role.
All the old does is group your capabilities together.
If you scroll down this page even further, you'll find the default capabilities described in detail
and what you can do with each one.
With that being said, we have to decide on a way where the user can have the capability upload files.
The first solution that comes to mind is just to make it so all users who register are assigned to the
author role.
However, this would also assign them other capabilities we may not want users to have.
Another solution is to modify the subscriber role and just add the upload files capability.
The problem with this is that we shouldn't try to modify default WordPress roles.
The last solution is to just create our own custom role with custom capabilities.
This is the best solution and it's quite simple to implement open the plug in activation file.
At the very end of the function, I'm going to grab the WP Rolls Global Variable, this variable contains
information about the current roles and WordPress.
We need this.
If we're going to add our very own role with capabilities to add a role, we need to call the function
add role.
This function has three parameters.
The first parameter is the role name.
This can be thought of as an ID for the role.
I'm going to set this to recipe author.
The second parameter is a readable name of the role, I'm going to make this translatable and set this
to recipe author.
The last parameter is a list of capabilities this role will have, there are three roles they want to
assign.
I want to set the read and it posts and upload files capabilities to true.
All these capabilities will now be grouped together with this role.
That's all you need to do.
I want you to deactivate and reactivate this plugin.
You shouldn't receive any errors.
Now, all we have to do is tell WordPress that all new registered users should be assigned this role.
Luckily, you don't have to write a single line of code to accomplish this.
Go to settings, General.
If you look at the new user default rule setting, you'll notice that the recipe author appearing as
an option.
I want you to select this role and then save your changes.
To save some time, I'm not going to create a new user, I'm just going to modify the test user and
change their role to the newly created role and save.
Then I'm going to log out and log in as the test user again, try submitting a recipe.
You should see the ad media button up here for the user.
This is exactly what we wanted.
We can now proceed as normal.