I'm now logged back in as the admin user, if you haven't already do the same in this lecture, we're
going to talk about taxonomies.
Taxonomies is a very simple concept to understand, but under the hood, it's very complex.
A taxonomy is just a word or phrase that is associated with the post WordPress provides to built-In
taxonomies called tags and categories.
If you think about it, those two taxonomies make it easier to group post together.
For example, if you owned a music site and you wanted to assign post to the genre rock, then you would
use the category.
By doing this, you could filter posts associated with certain genres.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to learn more about taxonomies.
Taxonomies can make it easier to manage and filter posts.
The concept behind taxonomies is very simple, but WordPress does a lot of work behind the scenes.
To better understand how much WordPress is doing, let's take a look at a database diagram.
WordPress creates three tables just for managing taxonomies.
Let's break down each table.
WP underscore terms stores all of your taxonomy terms.
WP underscore term underscore taxonomy defines what taxonomy each term belongs to.
WP underscore term underscore relationships.
A cross reference table that joins taxonomy terms with your content.
Each of these tables play a significant role when it comes to taxonomies.
To show you how complex things can get, here is what a sequel query might look like when you want to
grab all the posts and their taxonomies.
As you can see, you have to make a lot of Joynes just to grab something so simple.
Luckily, you don't have to deal with this kind of stuff as WordPress has a lot of built in functions
that will handle all this workload for you.
An example would be the WP query class.
This class has quite a few options for grabbing posts with taxonomies.
If you can recall, we grabbed posts related to a single post based on a category and displayed them
right below the content.
This is an example of us using a taxonomy.
It's even easy to create our own taxonomy.
Let's do that now for our recipes.
I want to create a taxonomy for the origin of a recipe.
Many recipes can come from Italy or France or any other country you can think of.
So it would be a good idea to use a taxonomy to group recipes together based on their origin.
To register a taxonomy, you have to use the function register taxonomy.
This function must be called inside the init hook, but we already have something like that.
So let's open the init file now, right after creating the post time.
Let's call this function.
This function has three parameters, the first parameter is the name of this taxonomy in the resource
section of this lecture, I provided a link to this function.
If you scroll down to the list of parameters, you'll find that WordPress provides some information
about this parameter.
The name of the taxonomy name should only contain lowercase letters and the underscore character and
not be more than thirty two characters long.
Let's keep it simple and name this taxonomy origin.
The second parameter is what post type will this taxonomy be associated with?
I want this taxonomy to only belong to the recipe post type, so pass that in like.
So the last parameter is an array of arguments we can set.
If you look at the documentation, you'll notice we can set a number of things.
Let's pass in an array.
There are only three things I'm going to set.
A lot of the default settings are fine the way they are.
I want to set the label to origin.
I'll make this string translatable.
The next thing I want to set is the rewrite rule.
I want the slug to be origin.
The last thing I want to set is the show in reste option, this should be true.
This is important to set if you're using Gutenberg, the Gutenberg editor uses an API called the rest
API.
This is an API.
We haven't been able to go over in depth.
It basically allows WordPress to update the database through requests.
We'll explore the rest API in a later lecture.
Just know for now that it's necessary for custom taxonomies to work in the Gutenberg editor.
These are the only things I want to set Savir changes and navigate to the admin dashboard right under
the recipes menu.
You'll find a new submenu called Origin.
Click on this and you'll find that WordPress generates a UI for you to manage these taxonomies.
If you were to create a new recipe or an existing one, you'll find a panel on the sidebar that lets
you manage the origin taxonomy for this particular post.
As you can see, WordPress does a lot under the hood for you already when it comes to taxonomies.