I want to display my custom taxonomy on the front end before I do that, I want to add some settings
from my taxonomy.
If you were to go to the Origin edit page, you'll find a list of origins and a forum for creating a
new one.
This form is pretty basic, but I'd like to add on to it.
I want to add a new URL for more information about an origin.
To pull this off, we'll have to do a couple of things.
The first step is to add the form fields inside the main plug and file.
Add the action hook called add form fields.
This is a dynamic cook right before the hook name, you have to append the name of the taxonomy, which
is Origin.
This is how WordPress knows which taxonomy this hoax should run under the function I want to call,
we named our origin and form fields.
Next, create a file inside the includes admin folder named Origin Dash Fields, not define the function
inside this file and make sure to include it from the main plugin file.
I'm going to paste in some HTML into this function.
Let's break this down, the HTML here is the same HTML you'll find if you were to inspect the element
on the form, nothing really special here except for two things.
The first thing is the name of the input field.
It should be unique.
I said this to our more info you URL.
The next thing is the paragraph tag, which contains a short description about the input field.
This is completely optional to add, but it's useful to give your users more information about this
field.
That's all there is to creating the input fields.
You don't have to worry about adding form tags as this will already be wrapped in one.
The next step is to save the value.
Back inside the main plugin file, add a new action hook called Create Underscore.
This action hook is also dynamic, it is followed by the name of the taxonomy, which is origin, the
function I want to call will be named are Save Origin Medha.
I'm going to create a new file inside the process folder called Save Dasch Origin, with the function
defined inside, this function will be passed in the term ID.
Lastly, make sure to include it from the main plug and file.
Inside this function, I'm going to check if the field is set, if it isn't, then I'm just going to
return the function.
Just like post terms can have metadata to clarify, the origin is a taxonomy, but each individual origin
is called a term.
This goes for any taxonomy.
The individual categories or tags for a post is called a term so you can have term metadata.
The metadata API can be used for this.
WordPress provides a set of functions to save term metadata, which work the exact same way as the post
metadata functions.
The name of the functions are just different.
I want you to call the update term meta function.
The first parameter is the ID of the term.
The second is the name, which will be more info you URL and the last parameter is the oral.
I'm going to wrap the value with the function escape you URL roar, which will make sure this is a safe
URL.
This will take care of creating the term, it's important to note that taxonomies will have two different
forms of form for creating the taxonomy and another for editing a taxonomy to save some time.
I'm going to go back to the main plugin file and copy this action and replace the second one from create
underscore origin to edited underscore origin.
The edited version will be used when a user updates the user out, the function will be the same.
We're almost done, the last thing I want to do is create the forum field for the edit form page.
The HTML will be different, but the idea is the same.
I'm going to add a new action hook called edit form fields, where the beginning of the hook is the
name of the taxonomy, which will be origin.
The function I want to call will be named after Origin edit form fields.
I'm going to define this function inside the origin dash fields file.
A couple of things will be different from the new form, this function will be passed in an object called
term that will contain information about the current term to grab the metadata.
I'm going to create a variable named U.
RL and its value will be the value returned by the function.
Get Turmeda.
The term object has a property named term ID that will pass in as the first parameter, the next parameter
is the name, which is more info you URL and the last parameter will be set to true.
Now that I have my you IRL, I can display the form with it, I'm going to paste in some HTML, which
is a tad different than the function above.
I know it seems weird, but the HMO tends to be different for both fields, the edit form field uses
tables to format the form.
What's most important is the input field for the value I'm echoing out there you out.
This will take care of the form and saving the data.
I'm going to test this, refresh the page and you should see the field appearing.
I want you to create a new origin.
You can paste in any you URL you want.
I'm just going to paste in a Eurail to the France Wikipedia page, you'll now see the term up here to
the right.
Click on it and check to see if the edit form is working as well.
You don't have to change any values, but if you press update, then you should still see everything
intact.
The next step is to make the origin appear on the front end, along with the more info you orell open
the filter content file.
This is the file that contains the function to modify the output onto the front end.
I'm also going to open the template for this.
I'm going to make one modification to the template.
I want you to add another list item that has three placeholders for the name, the actual value itself,
and then a placeholder for the more info you, Earl.
Inside the filter function, we will replace the text holder with Origin for the actual value itself,
we're only interested in the first origin itself.
I'm going to create a variable named Origin, which will contain the value returned by the function.
WP get post terms.
This function will get all the terms associated with this post, the first parameter is the ID of the
post.
The second parameter is the taxonomy, which is origin.
This function will return an array of terms.
I'm going to create another variable named more info you Earl, I'm going to use the ternary operator
to assign the value for this variable.
I'm going to check if the first item in the origin array is set.
So we know we have at least one item in the original rate.
If there is a value, I'm going to get the more info you are all metadata using the get term meta function,
otherwise I'm going to set this as an empty string.
Now that we have our values prepared, let's display them for the origin itself.
I'm going to use the ternary operator again.
If the first item in the array is set, I'm going to output the name of that term.
Each item in the array is an object.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the function WP get post terms.
If you scroll down to the return value section, you'll find the properties for each object in the array.
One of these is the name, which is what we're using here.
However, if the first term is indeed empty, we're going to use the phrase none.
The very last step to all of this is to display the more info you, Earl, I'm going to use a conditional
statement to check if the more info you call variable is empty.
If it isn't, I'm going to replace the placeholder with a clickable link.
Otherwise, I'm just going to replace it with an empty string.
Let's test this out now.
I want you to view a recipe without making any changes to it, you should see the origin list item with
none next to it.
And no, you are well appearing after you've confirmed that you can now edit this recipe.
I want you to assign the origin we created earlier, save your changes and view the recipe again.
You should now see the origin appear along with the more info you, Earl.
That wraps it up for this lecture.
We've learned how to make taxonomies and settings for our taxonomies.