In this lecture, we're going to explore how to create a rich text block, a rich text block is a block
that allows you to write content with formatting.
It's the equivalent of adding a tiny MCE editor.
You can make text bold and italicized.
This shouldn't be confused with a text area field as text area doesn't allow for formatting to get started.
I've provided some starter files in the resource section of this lecture.
Download it and unzip the contents.
Inside the blocks after victory of our plugin, there should be a folder called Rich Text Blocks with
a single JFS file.
If you open this, you'll find that I'm just importing some components and registering a new block.
This code won't work because we aren't importing it.
Why don't you give that a try and pause the video and try importing this so that web pack can process
it?
Welcome back.
If you were able to do this, then that's great.
If not, that's fine as well.
Let's do it together.
Open the app index file.
This is where we import our blocks right below the recipe block.
Add the following import rich text block.
That's all we have to do now, the block will be loaded properly.
Let's switch back to the rich tax block.
A lot of this should be familiar to you.
I'm naming my block udemy rich text.
The settings have been simplified.
I didn't bother adding the key words since this is a simple example.
The attributes are currently empty will be adding an attribute soon enough.
The edit function is returning a simple div tag with a title.
The save function isn't returning anything at all.
This should be enough to get us started.
The process for all of this should be straightforward.
First, we'll import any necessary components, then we'll define the attributes.
Next will load the component inside the added function.
Lastly, will render the block.
The component we're going to need will come from the WP editor Object Wieldy structure and grabbed the
rich text component.
The rich text component will allow the user to edit the content inside of it, while also allowing them
to format their content.
The next step is to create the attribute.
I'm going to create an attribute called message.
The type for this will be Ouray.
Previously, we used Stream, however, this time we're not just storing text, we're storing elements
and attributes as well.
The rich text component will generate a lot of content and so an array is ideal for multiple pieces
of content.
The source will be children.
Once again, the content generated will be complex when WordPress is extracting the data from the content,
it will need to grab everything.
This includes text elements, attributes and anything that is nested.
The children value will instruct it to do so.
The selector will be message container.
This element doesn't exist, but will be creating it soon enough, the attribute is now already let's
move onto the edit function right below the three elements and the rich text component.
The rich text component requires quite a few attributes in the resource section of this lecture, I
provide a link to the rich text component documentation.
Here you'll find information on the various attributes you can set and even some examples.
There should be an S5 example.
If you're using S5, feel free to read up on this page to learn more about this component.
Let's go back to our script.
The first property will set is the tag name property.
Set this to div.
This will be the element that's wrapped around the content and put it, you can set this to an age three
tag if you want the content to be a title, it's a very flexible component.
A div tag will do for our purposes.
The next property is multiline.
Set this, Tuppy.
The rich text component will allow your users to create multiline content whenever a user presses the
enter key on their keyboard.
Then this will determine how that content is broken down by default.
This will use a line break, but I prefer to use paragraph tags for better formatting.
The next property is placeholder.
Make this translatable and set it to add your content here.
The next property will be on change, just like the other components.
This will be triggered when the user changes the content, set this to an arrow function that will call
the props, set attributes, function and update the message attribute with the new value.
The last property will set is the value property, set this to props, Don attributes stock message.
This one should be straightforward.
It's the value or content inside the component that should finish things up.
Let's move on to the same function.
We won't have to do much to get this to work.
It's as simple as displaying the attribute.
Why don't you give this a try, pause the video and try displaying the content from the rich text component.
Welcome back.
If you were able to do it, then congrats, if not, that's fine as well.
Let's do it together.
Inside the function.
I'm going to return a pair of div tags.
I won't be applying the class as Gutenberg will do it for us inside this div tag.
I'm going to add the three tags with the message we had in the edit function.
This is not necessary, but I like to add it for consistency.
Lastly, I'll add another pair of div tags with the props attributes message inside.
Make sure to apply the message container class, since that's what we specified inside The Selecter
property for the attribute.
That should do it into the blocks directory and run the NPM run dev command.
You shouldn't see any error so far once you have that comp., go ahead and create a new recipe post
if you were to search for the rich text component.
You should see it appear with the title and icon.
Select the component to add it onto the editor.
It should appear without a problem.
If you check the console, then you shouldn't see any errors.
Now try editing the content area.
You can input anything you want and even add multiline content.
I can press control, be on my keyboard to make the content bold.
This is fantastic.
Let's see if things work on the front end.
Publish the post and then view the post.
The content should be rendered on the front end.
Congrats, you've created your first rich text block.
You can use this in several ways.
It's not practical to use this by itself since Gutenberg already has a blog but does something similar.
But I'm sure you'll find a use case for this.