In some situations, you may want to add in your own custom buttons to the toolbar, that's completely
possible.
WordPress even provides some components for making that process easier to get started.
Download the zip file in the resource section of this lecture.
Unzip the contents inside the app directory.
You should be provided with a folder called Night Mode Block.
We're going to be building a block where a user can enable Nite Mode.
Night Mode is a term used to describe UI that switches the contrast from light to dark.
This reduces eyestrain will make a button that will allow the user to toggle this feature.
There are several files here, but it's nothing you haven't seen before.
Let's start with the index file.
I'm importing the icon for the block and an icon for the button.
Let's check that out for a minute.
I'm viewing the icon in Illustrator.
If you don't have Illustrator, that's perfectly fine.
I've already taken the time to export it as an SVG file and export it.
You can find the icon inside the icon JS file.
All I'm doing here is exporting the SVG code as the default value, switching back to the index while
I'm importing a SACE file.
If you look inside the SAS file, you'll find that I'm just applying a dark background color and a light
font color.
Take note that this will only apply if the Class Nite mode is applied to the element.
All right, let's go back to the index file.
Everything else is the same.
We're grabbing some components and registering the block.
I'm leaving out the key words property again to save room.
Feel free to add it in.
If you like the edit function, we'll display some basic content.
We're not going to bother adding input fields or changeable content.
Everything will be static besides the toolbar right above the content.
I'm loading the block controls component.
It's currently empty but will be adding our custom toolbar soon enough.
The same function contains the same HTML as above.
That should be it.
Now that we have an overview of things, let's get started to create a custom toolbar.
We're going to need a couple of components.
These components are optional, but they handle a lot for us, such as formatting, positioning and
design.
All of these components will come from the WP components object.
So D structure that.
We'll need the toolbar button and tooltip components.
All talk about what these components do in just a moment.
Next, we're going to set up some attributes we only need one which will determine if the content should
have night mode enabled, create an attribute called night mode.
The type will be boolean and the default will be false.
We're not setting a source or selectors instance will be a simple value that makes it perfect for storing
it inside the comments with the attributes set, let's begin creating the toolbar inside the controls
component.
I'm going to load in the toolbar component.
The toolbar component will take care of adding a separator between the other toolbars that might be
loaded in it will properly positioning your button within the block controls component.
Next, we're going to load in the tooltip component.
This component will display a tooltip if the user hovers over the content placed inside of it.
We don't have to worry about the events or positioning as that's handled for us.
The only attribute we need to set is the text attribute.
Set this to Nite Mode and make it translatable.
Insigne of the tooltip component, add the button component, the order does matter here, if the button
component is placed inside the toolbar component, the mesh stylings for the button component will be
adjusted.
The adjustment will make things look consistent with the other buttons on the toolbar.
All right.
We're going to apply a few things to this button.
First, we have to apply a couple of classes.
However, we run into one problem.
React currently doesn't support multiple classes for a component.
If you scroll up, you'll see I'm loading a module called Class Names.
This is a third party module that we installed long ago.
I promised a very long time ago to explain what this is for.
And now I finally can.
This module will take care of allowing multiple classes for a component.
It's very easy to use on the button.
I'm going to apply the class name attribute.
The value for this will be fastenings function.
This will accept in the list of class names you'd like to apply.
I'm going to add classes which are components dash Eikon, dash button and component's dash toolbar,
underscore, underscore control.
We're going to apply one more class, which is is dash active, however, this will be inside an object.
If we want to have dynamic classes, then we have to format it like this.
The name will be the class to add and the value can either be true or false.
If it's true, then the class will be added.
If false, it won't be added.
Set this to prompts on attributes in night mode.
By default, night mode will be false.
So this class shouldn't be applying the IS act of class will let the user visually know the button is
enabled.
I was able to find these classes by looking at the other components and toolbars WordPress creates.
It's not documented.
So it's always good practice to dive into the code itself to better understand how things work.
Next, we want to change that night mode attribute.
If this button is clicked, we basically want to flip the current value.
The button component has an event called on Click.
This will be set to an arrow function just like before, we'll call the set attributes function and
set the night mode attribute to its opposite value like so.
Next will end the button icon variable as the content inside.
The width and height should be 20 pixels.
I've already applied that to the icon itself.
Now that the button is functioning, we just have to apply this to the content itself below.
I'm going to call the class names function instead of setting the class statically.
All and the content Dasch example class and make the night class dynamic.
The night class will take care of adding the dark background and white text.
This is what we named it in our SAS files.
This will be set to prompts Don attributes night mode.
I'm going to copy this code and paste it over to the save function, since it's the exact same thing.
The block is now finished, the last step is to import it inside the app index, just file import the
night mode block module.
Into the block's directory and run the NPM run dev command.
You shouldn't receive any errors so far.
Go ahead and create a recipe post, if you were to search for the night mode block, then you should
be able to find it with the Warp Who icon and the block to the editor.
All you should see is a simple message.
If you were to select it, then you should see the toolbar appear with our custom button and icon.
You can click it and it should toggle night mode.
If you hover your mouse over the button, then you should see the tool tip as well.
This is great.
We now have our own custom toolbar turn on night mode and then save the post.
Try viewing it on the front, end the block should have the stylings applied to it if you did everything
right.
There's not much to this, honestly.
You're just loading in a few components and using them to help build your custom toolbar.
Before I am this lecture, I do want to note one thing.
Tool tips are optional.
If you wanted to, you could remove this like so.
This is perfectly fine, however, I prefer to add it because it can provide more context to the user
just in case they don't understand what your buttons do.
I'll add it back in.
That does it for now, will continue exploring more components in the next lecture.