Media is a great way to enhance your content, WordPress fully supports all kinds of media, from images
to videos to audio files, you can view all the media you have uploaded on the media page in the WordPress
admin dashboard.
You may see some images here already.
These were provided by Fakher Press when we ran it.
We're going to create a blog that will allow the user to select an image from the media uploader and
render it on the page.
WordPress already provides this feature, but you may end up having to create your own version later
down the road.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provided zip file that contains everything you'll need,
download it and unzip the contents into the app directories.
You'll be provided a folder called Media Upload Block.
Inside this folder should be two files and indexed JS File and editor access file.
The editor file will contain some style links to position a remove button.
We will give our users the choice to remove an image they select.
The index file contains the usual.
We are restructuring some components and registering the block to get started.
We'll need to structure a couple more components from the WP editor object, the structure the media
upload and media upload sheet components.
From the WP components object, the structure, the dash icon object.
The media upload component will generate the UI for selecting and uploading images to the media uploader,
the media upload check component does something different than any other component we've encountered
so far.
It was specifically made to check to see if the user currently logged in has the correct permissions
to upload and manage files.
This component must be wrapped around the media upload component.
You'll see how that's done soon enough.
The dash icon component allows you to use the dash icon set anywhere in your block.
Previously we used the name to display an icon, but that's because WordPress took the time to render
this component for you.
If we want to use a dash icon in a custom location, then it will need to be the ones to render the
icon it super simple.
So don't worry with the components, the structured, let's set some attributes.
The attribute we're going to create will revolve around what the media upload or returns will be returned
inside your URL and alternative text.
Let's start with the ID.
The name will be image ID.
The type will be No.
The ID will be the ID of the media item, which is stored in the database.
We won't be using it, but it's still something you may need later down the road.
I'm also not going to store it in the element.
Instead, I'll just stored in the comments.
Next is the image you are the type will be stirring and the source will be attribute.
We're essentially telling WordPress that the value can be found inside an attribute when it's loading
the HTML from the database.
If you set the source to attribute, then you'll need to set the attribute property next.
This will allow you to specify the attribute the value is stored in.
Set this to source.
We'll be using an image tag, it would make sense that the euro would be stored there.
Lastly, to find The Selecter property and set it to image.
I'm going to make a copy of this as the alternative text will be the same thing, except the attribute
will be ALZ.
All right, the attributes are ready, the next step is to set up the UI, the UI will require a bit
of work to set up.
So prepare yourself first.
We're going to need to return some X.
Then we'll need to display a button that will render the media uploader here's the problem, though.
We only want to display the button if there is no media currently being displayed.
We want to use a conditional statement for this, but we can't use traditional conditional statements
in sex.
Instead will have to use a ternary operator for the condition.
I'm going to check if the prompts got attributes.
Dot image ID is set.
If it is, then we'll display the image, otherwise we'll display the button for the media uploader,
we'll start with the media uploader output the media upload, check and media upload components.
I'm wrapping the media upload component inside the media upload check component, this is required if
you want to limit who can and who can't upload images, you're not required to pass in any special attributes
to the media.
Upload check component.
It's already properly configured for you.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to this component's documentation.
This page will provide an example on how to use this component and its attributes.
Feel free to read up on it after you finish this lecture.
Back inside the script, the first attribute will define is allowed to types.
This should be set to an array of file types you'd like to allow.
We only want to allow one type of file, which is image.
This is optional, but if you set it, WordPress will limit what media file type of user can select.
We only want to allow users to select images.
Next, we'll need to set the value attribute, set this to props, the attributes, dot image ID.
If you pass in a value, then WordPress will automatically select the media item with the same ID,
this way the user doesn't have to scroll around to find the media item they selected previously.
The next attribute is on select cities to Select Image.
This is an event that will be triggered when the user selects an image, the value for this attribute
should be a function that will process the image we're passing in unnamed function that currently isn't
defined.
We'll define it in just a moment, but let's keep moving forward.
Lastly, we'll need to set the render attribute.
This attribute is used to render the button that will open the media uploader.
The media upload component will not display the media upload or immediately.
Instead, it gets rendered within a certain function is called the media upload component gives us the
opportunity to create that button ourselves.
The value for this attribute will be an anonymous function that will be passed in an object.
We only care about one property from this object and that's the open function, the structure that.
The open function will open, the media uploader will call this in a moment, but let's create a button
using the button component.
I'm applying the button and button dash large classes, the text inside will be upload image.
Now, let's set the unclick event to the open function.
Here's what's going to happen.
The media upload component will display the button we created in the render attribute.
The button will call the open function.
When the click event is triggered, the open function will take care of displaying the media uploader
when called.
Before we begin displaying the image after it's been selected, we'll need to store the image data for
the on select attribute.
We're calling the select image function.
Let's define that above.
The function will be passed in an object called image.
This object will contain the properties and values related to the image selected from the media uploader
using this object.
I'm going to set each attribute to their respective property.
To do this, I'm calling the set attributes function in a previous lecture, we would only set one value,
but it is possible to set multiple values like I'm doing here.
The idea of the image is stored in the ID property.
The image you are well is stored in the euro property and the alternative text is stored in the allt
property.
I was able to find out the names by simply logging the object and reviewing it in the console.
I recommend you try logging the object yourself.
This will give you a better idea of what properties are inside the object.
The next step is to display the image back inside the return statement.
I'm going to add the code to the section that will run if the condition is true, which is checking
if there is an image ID.
I'm going to wrap everything with a div tag.
The tag should have the class image container.
I'm adding this because we're going to have a button with absolute positioning in order to have elements
with absolute positioning, we need a tag with relative positioning, which is what this class does.
From here.
I'm going to add the image tag with the source and all attributes.
I'll set them to their respective attribute values.
Lastly, we need to add the button that will remove the image if the user clicks on it, we're going
to use another ternary operator for this.
We only want to display the button if the block is currently selected.
This is a user experience design decision.
If the user is editing the block, then it makes sense to display options related to editing the block.
However, if the block isn't selected, then we want to hide the options to prevent adding clutter to
the interface.
Once again, this step is optional, but I think it makes sense here.
We're going to check if the props DOT is selected.
Property is set to true.
Remember, this is a property WordPress will automatically update for you if the block is being edited.
If this returns true, then will display the button component.
I'm applying the class button remove and setting the on click event to remove image.
This function doesn't exist, but will be adding it soon enough for the content inside.
I'm going to add the dash icon component.
You have the option of adding your own custom SVG icon, but I think a dash icon will suffice here.
You can use any of the national icons provided by WordPress.
All you need to do is add the icon attribute and pass in the name of the icon you'd like to use.
You don't have to add the dash icon dash prefix as it's added for you.
The icon and we're going to use is the no icon, which is an X mark.
I'm also going to set the size attribute to twenty.
This is measured in pixels that should display the button.
It has absolute positioning.
Check out the editor file for the CSC Code.
To finish things off, we'll need to set the second half of the ternary operator to know which we'll
display nothing if the lock isn't selected.
The last step is to create the remove image function we specified for the on click event and created
above.
It will be the same thing as before, except all set.
All attributes to know like so.
All right, let's recap what this function will do.
Let's assume the block was added for the first time.
The first thing that will happen is this condition check.
It will check if there is a value for image ID by default, it should be.
No, since that's the case, the second half of this code will run.
The media upload component will be rendered.
That media upload component will display whatever is in the render property.
The render property will display a button that will run the open function.
When it's clicked, the open function was provided to us by the component, so we don't have to do anything
else.
The media library model will open and allow the user to select or upload an image.
If an image is selected, then the function inside the on select function will run scrolling up.
All we're doing here is using the image object and setting the attributes of their respective values.
This will cause the block to re render again.
This time since the image ID attribute has a value, the code inside the first half will render.
This will render the image the user selected.
This will also display a button that will allow them to remove the image of the block as active.
If they click the button, then the remove image function will run.
This will set all the attributes to know that's basically it.
The same function will display the image, use the image tag and set the source and all attributes to
their respective values.
Save your changes and import this block from the app index file.
Then segued into the blocks rectory and run the NPM run deve command.
Lastly, try creating a new recipe post and add this block to your content.
Initially, you should see a button, if you click it, then a model should appear.
This is the media library.
You can select any image and then press select the buttons should disappear and instead the image should
appear in its place.
There's also the option of removing the button.
If I were to deselect the block, then the remove button should go away.
If I were to select the block again, then it will reappear.
Clicking on this should remove the image.
I'm going to add the image back in and save the post.
Using the post on the front end should just display the image, we're finished, we know how to add
the media uploader to our blogs.
Feel free to play around with this.