Generating ideas for niche markets.
In this video we will be looking at a number of ways that you can generate a list of possible niche
markets that you could pursue.
We want to make it very clear that you will not be deciding on your niche at this stage.
A lot of newcomers to niche marketing get very excited about the prospect and skip this stage.
While we understand the excitement it is not a good idea to go into a niece that you cannot be passionate
about or has very little opportunity to make money.
Identify your passions.
There is a lot of information out there about choosing a niche market and most of them will tell you
to follow your passions.
If you are really passionate about something then this makes a lot of sense as you will be very motivated
to make it work.
But it doesn't always work.
If you have a passion for a niche but the size of that niche is really small and the people in it rarely
buy anything then you are just wasting your time.
Finding a niche that you can get passionate about is another story and we will discuss this later on.
We agree that it makes a lot of sense to enter a niche market that you are passionate about.
Remember at this stage you are just compiling a list of possible niche ideas in the next video.
We will look at how you can test each idea for viability so we recommend that you identify the subjects
that really interest you first.
What are you really passionate and knowledgeable about.
Get yourself a pen and paper and start to write down the things that you are interested in.
Do not make any judgments at this stage.
If you find yourself struggling here then ask yourself these questions.
What hobbies do I have.
What sports are my interested in if any.
How do I spend my free time.
What do I like to read about online and off line.
What TV programs really interest me.
What magazine subscriptions do I have.
What I really miss in my life if I couldn't participate in it or read about it.
What problems do I have at the moment.
What things do I look for when I search online.
Well what I like to learn more about what skills do I want to develop.
What could I improve in my life.
This is just a small sample of the questions that you can ask yourself what you are doing here is looking
introspective Lee to see what really interests you.
It is likely that a few things will be significantly more interesting than others such as hobbies sports
TV etc..
Again do not make any prejudgment after spending just a few minutes doing this you should be able to
create a fairly long list.
If you are still struggling to come up with a lot of ideas at this point then don't worry because there
are other steps you need to take.
Put your marketing hat on now it's time to look at the world from a marketing perspective.
When you do this you will be able to come up with even more ideas.
Even if you have no interest in them at the moment don't worry about this.
Just write the ideas down.
You're going to play detective here.
You need a pen and notebook or a mobile device where you can jot down or record ideas.
It is best to start doing this at the beginning of a new day as you progress through your day.
Make a note of the following.
Any problems that you encounter things around you that attract your attention.
The kinds of conversations you have with other people.
What was on TV that appealed to you.
The products and services you use things that make you happy.
Things that make you angry or sad.
Activities you participate in determine the time to stop recording these things.
Then take a look at each one you have made a record of and ask the following questions.
Are other people interested in the same things.
Are people spending money to do these things.
What kind of problems do you and others face.
What things really made you happy or excited.
What things made you angry or sad or frustrated.
Identify those things on your marketing list where you get a positive answer when you ask the questions.
Any of these can be good niche marketing ideas where you can make money.
What is working right now.
There are a lot of different websites that you can look at that will tell you what the current trends
are and which niche markets are working right now.
By visiting these websites you can come up with more potentially profitable niche marketing ideas.
Amazon.com the first website we recommend you visit is Amazon.
Amazon sells a ton of products every day and they are the largest online retailer in the world.
And the good news here is that you can become an Amazon associate and promote the products on Amazon
for a commission.
Click on the department's link at the top of the page and you will see a drop down menu with all the
categories listed.
Clicking on any of the categories will take you to the specific category page.
Once you arrive at the category page look at the top left of the page and you should see a number of
sub niches.
So for example in the arts and crafts category there are 13 submissions such as crafting fabric and
knitting and crocheting.
When you click on one of these subnets you are likely to find more some niches to give you even more
ideas within the main category.
You will see a number of products with a best seller orange color graphic you can find the best selling
items on Amazon by visiting this link that read WW dot Amazon.com forward slash best hyphen sellers
forged last Z g b s.
This actually changes on an hourly basis and you can dig around on this page and come up with a lot
of good ideas.
Click Bank dot com.
If you don't already know about Click Bank time com it is the biggest marketplace for digital products.
We will talk more about digital versus physical products in our later video.
You can take a look at the marketplace and Click Bank to see what categories the products are in on
the home page.
You will see several categories on the left hand side at the top of the page.
There is an affiliate marketplace link.
Each one of the main categories has subcategories or niches so you can get a lot of ideas here.
Look for active forums.
A forum is a community based Web site around a specific niche.
You can see what people are talking about and what their interests and problems are by visiting the
right forums.
There are also a great place for niche market ideas.
We recommend that you visit find a forum dot net to make life easy for you on the home page.
There is a section on the top 10 categories which will give you a lot of good ideas.
There is actually a niche link that you can use to find good ideas trends.
There are a number of ways to see what is trending on the Internet.
You can get ideas from these Web sites.
Twitter just log into your Twitter account and then open the notifications tab.
From here you can check for trending topics.
Google go to trends that Google dot com forward slash trends forward slash question mark geo equals
us to see what is trending in the Google search engine.
Most social platforms have ways that you can see what's trending on sites such as Facebook Instagram
and Pinterest.
Magazines that com despite the popularity of the Internet many people still subscribe to magazines every
month.
So get yourself over to magazines that com and take a look at what is on offer there at the top of the
pages of best sellers link.
So use this to see what magazines people are subscribing to invest numbers to get some great initial
ideas flip out dot com.
This is our secret weapon.
If you don't know flip a dot com is the world's largest leading marketplace for buying and selling websites
with a little digging you can find out what nieces are selling for the highest prices and what nieces
are watched the most.
Some niche websites have sold for incredible amounts of money on this platform recently flip published
a post on their blog which provides great insight into what really sells well.
Here's a link to the Post blog that flip a dot com forward slash revealed hyphen the hyphen niches hyphen
with hyphen the hyphen highest hyphen chance hyphen of Hyphen selling hyphen and hyphen more in this
great blog post you will discover niches with the highest chance of selling niches buyers are most interested
in shoes that fetch the highest prices niches with high demand and low supply.
Most watch monetization methods.
This really is a great post that we recommend you take a few minutes to read it will provide you with
some great niche ideas.
If you go to the home page and flip a dot com click on the websites link and then select just sold from
the dropdown list.
Here you will see examples of Web sites that have been sold recently and what income the sites were
generating.
You should have a pretty big list of niche market ideas by now.
The next video and discusses how you can test the ideas to see if they are worth pursuing.