Testing your niche ideas.
OK.
So you now have a list of niche market ideas.
The next step is to test the ideas to see if they are likely to be profitable for you.
There are two very important elements to this which are demand and commercial intent.
Demand is very important.
You do not want to go for a niche that is very small.
If you are not getting a good number of targeted visitors to your website then you are not going to
make much money.
If anything at all you need targeted visitors.
These are people that have an interest in your chosen niche.
This is cost effective and will increase your chances of achieving conversions.
Don't be tempted to purchase broad traffic for your niche.
There are a lot of vendors selling traffic from specific countries but this will just be a waste of
money.
The other important aspect is commercial intent.
If the niche is large but nobody spends money in it then you need to forget about it.
It doesn't matter if you have a real passion for the niche.
If there is no money to be made then you are just wasting your time.
You need to take the emotion out of your decision here.
It is possible that the best niche on your list is something that you don't know much about.
You need to ask yourself if you could get interested and passionate about it especially if it was to
make you a lot of money.
Niche size it is fairly easy and quick to see whether your niche is large enough or not.
Just use the google keyword planner tool at ads that Google that come forward slash home or slash tools
for Slash keyword hyphen planner to use the planner.
You will need a free Google AdWords account.
This doesn't mean that you have to spend any money on Google ads.
You can if you want to but it is not necessary at this stage.
You need to decide on a good seed keyword for your niche ideas.
Let's use an example here in your list of niche ideas you have the paleo diet.
So the seed keyword that we will use for our example is Paleo diet.
Enter this into the google keyword planner.
One of the great things about the google keyword planner is that it will provide you with related keyword
suggestions and show you the estimated search volumes at the time of writing.
We found the following Paleo diet.
One hundred thousand and one million monthly searches paleo diet foods one thousand ten 10000 Paleo
Meal plan one thousand and ten thousand paleo diet plan one thousand ten thousand.
The paleo diet 1000 10000 paleo weight loss 1000 10000 paleo diet weight loss 1000 10000 paleo diet
basics 1000 to 10000.
There were more keyword terms and this indicates that there is good search volume in this niche.
This is certainly a niche market idea worth pursuing further.
You can use the google keyword planner to check all of your niche ideas quickly.
What is the best size of niche.
Well there is no hard and fast rule but we would recommend that the C keyword has a minimum of ten thousand
searches a month for it to be viable.
In our example paleo diet easily exceeds this with between one hundred thousand and one million every
month.
The numbers above are the estimated search finds for the USA.
You can change this to make it worldwide where the numbers are usually going to be larger.
If you only intend to market to a specific country then you can choose this in the google keyword planner
to get the most accurate search volume.
We recommend that you go for niche markets that have global appeal.
The paleo diet certainly fits the bill as it is popular all over the world.
Why limit your options if you don't need to.
There are other keyword tools that you can use for this research.
But the google keyword planner is always likely to be the most accurate.
It is easy to use and free.
So it is not worth using anything else in our opinion.
COMMERCIAL INTENT.
OK so you have run all of your niche ideas through the google keyword planner and eliminated those were
the sizes the nation's too small.
The next step is to check for commercial intent at this point.
We want to make the distinction between physical and digital products.
You can become an affiliate for Amazon and promote their physical products physical products tend to
sell more easily than digital products.
But the commissions you can earn as an affiliate are usually a lot lower.
As a new Amazon affiliate you will earn just 4 percent commission on physical products.
This can amount to a few cents or a few dollars depending on the price of the product.
It is a good idea to target high ticket items at Amazon if you want to make good money.
A good example of this is flat screen TV ads which sell for 1000 dollars and upwards.
Digital products are guides videos and software.
They are something that the customer can instantly download or have access to once they have made their
purchase because it is usually more difficult to sell digital products.
The commissions are higher ranging from 30 percent to 100 percent.
Normally you can expect the 50 percent commission on digital products to make money online niche.
There are some examples of low price products offering 100 percent commission usually digital products
will be in a funnel which we will cover in more detail later.
The best niche market ideas have both physical and digital product opportunities there are lots of products
of both types available for you to make a commission on some niche ideas will only have physical products
available and some only digital products.
This is fine as long as people within the niche you're buying using Amazon you can use Amazon to see
if there's commercial intent for your niche ideas.
Just go to Amazon.com and then enter your seed keyword.
So let's continue with our example of Paleo diet.
There are not going to be a lot of physical products for the paleo diet as it is all about food choices.
What we did find is a lot of books and some of them with a high number of reviews.
The review can as important as people that actually buy the products leave them.
It is generally accepted that a single review on Amazon means that at least 10 people purchase the product
and as many as a thousand.
Only a small number of people will leave a review.
So if there are hundreds or even thousands of reviews then this is a good sign of commercial intent.
So run the remaining he said yes through Amazon and look out for review numbers.
Ideally you want at least 100 reviews for a product to suggest good commercial intent.
There will be related products as well and you can check the review numbers for these two using click
bank.
As you know click bank is the number one marketplace for digital products.
So go to click bank dot com and into your seed keyword in the affiliate marketplace section.
The first thing to do is note the number of products available for Paleo diet.
There were over 40 products available at the time of writing which is a good sign of commercial intent.
You can refine your search by changing the results to show the highest gravity.
This is a measure of the number of sales of a particular product by affiliates in the last week.
The top paleo diet product and click bank has a gravity of over sixty five and there are others with
the gravity of around 50.
This is all good as it shows sales are happening in this niche.
Google search another good test to see if a niche has commercial intent is to check for Google ads when
performing a Google search.
So we use Google to perform a search for paleo diet and found a number of ads.
You can also check this using the google keyword planner when you get the results back.
You will see a column called competition.
This is the competition for ads.
And if you see examples of medium or high competition.
This means that money is being spent on ads.
Google ads are not cheap and you can easily pay one dollar and upwards a click for the best keyword
terms.
Advertisers would not be spending this money if there was no commercial intent in their niche.
Other commercial intent methods there are a number of affiliate networks where you can find out which
products are selling well two of the most popular networks are commission junction and share a sale.
Both of these networks have analytics to show you the best APC earnings per click values and network
earnings.
It is not essential that you use these networks to validate the commercial intent of your niche ideas.
They are just useful to further validate an idea.
You will need to become a member of Commission Junction to use their analytics and this will not be
possible at this stage.
If you don't have a niche Web site set up yet another way of monetizing your niche Web site is by promoting
CPA cost per action offers.
Usually these offers will pay small commissions to you for your visitors providing specific details
such as an email address.
This is much easier than making a salable product.
If you are interested in the concept of CPA you can check what offers are available using a very useful
Web site called offer vault dot com.
All you need to do here is to enter your seed keyword into the search box and you will see all of the
relevant CPA offers displayed.
You can check Facebook and other social platforms to see if groups exist for your niche ideas.
Just log into Facebook and then perform a search using your seed keyword.
When we used paleo diet to search we found a number of Facebook groups with lots of members.
Try this out for other platforms such as Reddit Pinterest and Instagram.
Have a look for forums around the niche ideas.
If there are a number of forums and they are active then this is a good sign that there is a lot of
interest in a niche you can dig deeper to find if there are passionate posts and particular problems
where you could provide a commercial solution.
Time to decide at this stage you should have a small number of niche ideas left on your list by performing
the tests outlined above you have verified these as being a good size and having commercial intent.
So how do you choose a niche idea to get started.
Well the first thing we would recommend is that you go through the smallest and write down how you feel
about each one.
Are you already interested or passionate about any of them.
Could you develop a strong interest in any of them.
Let's say that you are now left with two or three ideas what you could do is to test each of them in
a small way.
This will involve setting up a small website for each initial idea.
You will need to add some content say three articles on each which will have a call to action to a product
or service that you are an affiliate for.
Sign up for Google AdWords and run ads for each niche minimum 100 clicks prudish.
At the end of this you can analyze the results to see if you made any commissions or achieved any email
list sign ups etc..
Ok now that you've decided on the niche you will go for it is time to set up your first niche website
which we will take you through in the next video.