Setting up your niche Web site before you start getting excited about setting up your new niche Web
site.
You need to think about how you're going to get targeted visitor traffic to it in a later video we will
discuss a number of ways that you can do this.
But we want to start this video off by discussing SEO Search Engine Optimization.
A lot of online marketers think that SEO is really too difficult these days with all of the changes
that Google has made to its search engine algorithm.
But this is a big mistake because it's actually easier to rank web pages now if they are optimized correctly.
So the first thing you need to do is keyword research.
The best niche websites start with comprehensive keyword research.
We have already mentioned the google keyword planner and how you can use this to identify search volumes
and related keywords for your niche.
You need to take this a step further now.
Unique Web site needs to be organized around the different types of keywords that you uncover.
We recommend that you use the WordPress blogging platform for your niche Web site and it is very easy
to set up different categories with this.
This is what Google and the other search engines want you to do.
So you want to generate a list of as many keywords for your list as you can.
You're not going to rank your individual web pages for all these keywords but you certainly will for
some of them as your Web site grows and becomes more of an authority then you will start to rank for
some of more competitive terms.
Think about the future now SEO is not a fast traffic solution but a long term one.
You can get traffic to your niche Web site using other methods as your site develops but you always
need to have SEO as the foundation of your niche Web site.
Go to the google keyword planner and start by entering in your seed keyword.
As we said before the planner will make suggestions for related keywords.
You can then use these related keywords to find other related keywords.
Set aside a few hours to create your initial list of keywords.
It is not difficult to come up with hundreds of different keywords for your niche Web site.
You can export the keywords that you find from the google keyword planner in CSP format and create Microsoft
Excel or other format spreadsheets from this.
These spreadsheets will be your mastered keyword lists.
You will have a few to work keywords such as paleo diet some three word keywords such as paleo weight
loss and quite a number of four and more keywords which will be your long tail keywords the long tail
keywords will not have massive search volume but they will be a lot easier to rank for without too much
effort.
These will be the start of your free traffic from the search engines.
Search engine traffic is the very best because it is really targeted.
If someone is searching for paleo diet weight loss then this is very specific.
They are truly interested in using the paleo diet to lose weight.
Your web pages need to be in the search results for these kinds of terms so that you can provide the
answers that people are looking for and either generate a new lead for your email list or make a sale
or a commission.
You need to understand that every keyword that you find will have a level of search engine competitiveness.
Usually the higher the search volume the more competitive the keyword term will be.
There are exceptions of course.
If a keyword is very competitive it will take a very long time for you to rank high in Google and the
other search engines for it.
Personal terms such as paleo it will probably be impossible for you to rank on the first page for this
no matter what you do.
So you need to know how competitive the keywords in your list are and then determine how competitive
they are.
Please note that this is not the same as the competition column in the google keyword planner.
This is the ads competition and will not be of any use to you.
It is possible to make an assessment of keyword competition manually but this requires a lot of skill
and time.
Fortunately there are the ways you can do this.
Here are the two methods that we recommend.
Traffic Travis this is a really great SEO tool used by the professionals but very few niche marketers.
You can download a free version at traffic Travis dot com.
The software does a lot of great things for SEO but one of the most valuable is that it will tell you
the competitiveness of keywords.
We recommend that you download the free version and give it a try first.
You can only look at a few keywords a day with the free version but you can see if you like the software
and then decide on whether or not to purchase the professional version at around ninety seven dollars.
When you use traffic Travis to estimate the FCO competition of a keyword it will tell you what it believes
to be the level of difficulty.
This is the range easy relatively easy medium difficult very difficult extremely difficult.
Anything that is easy relatively easy or medium is fair game.
The others will take a lot more work.
Traffic Travis queries Google several times to estimate keyword difficulty.
And lately Google has placed restrictions on this.
So analyzing hundreds of terms at once isn't possible anymore.
A ref scam.
This is a paid subscription service.
They do have an offer for seven dollars for seven days at the time of writing at a ref dot com a refs
is the king of the FCO analysis programs that will provide more accurate and up to date information
than any of the other programs out there.
It also has feature to measure keyword difficulty in a similar way to traffic Travis.
The difference is that a refs has all of this information already stored so there is no waiting for
the results.
If you are serious about SEO then the monthly subscription prices start at ninety nine dollars a month.
So to summarize you need a list of suitable keywords for your niche marketing site and you need to know
the keyword difficulty or competition for each keyword.
Then you can start to optimize your website and the content that you publish in line with this information
domain name and web hosting.
You will need to purchase a domain name and web hosting for your niche Web site.
We recommend that you choose a dot com domain name and that the name has some relevance to your niche.
It is very easy to register a domain name.
We recommend both go Daddy dot com and name cheap dot com is high quality domain registrars for your
new domain name.
Both of these websites have a feature where you can check the availability of a name.
So we used Go Daddy dot com and entered paleo Sage the dot com was taken.
But the paleo sage dot com was available at the time of writing.
This would be a good name to choose as it suggest wisdom and has the word paleo in it.
A few years ago it was really important to register a domain name with your main keyword in it.
These days it has very little effect if any but we would always recommend that you have a domain name
that makes people feel comfortable and that they have come to the right Web site.
A dot com domain name will cost you around ten dollars a year.
You are effectively renting your name and you will have to renew it every year in order to create your
niche Web site around your domain name.
You will need a web hosting account as well.
There are many companies offering Web hosting accounts from as little as three dollars a month.
Some of these companies offer a free domain name with their hosting but we recommend that you go for
a name from go daddy or name cheap as it is cleaner.
Think long term here you're going to be creating a valuable asset a successful niche Web site can sell
for a great deal of money and you do not want to be involved in a dispute with your web hosting company.
If you want to sell your Web site.
Here are some important things to look out for with a web host.
The monthly cost.
The location of the Web services.
In other words USA the UK Europe Asia etc..
How many domain names can you host.
How much disk space will you get.
How much bandwidth Internet traffic will you get.
Does the Web host have WordPress one click install software.
OK let's take a look at each one of these.
The cost Web hosting can start from one dollar a month and rise to hundreds a month.
We suggest that you choose a web host that will offer all the things in the above list for around 10
to 15 dollars a month web server location.
If you believe that the majority of your audience will be in the United States for example then it is
best to choose a web host with servers there.
Your website will load faster for your potential customers which is very important.
How many domain names if your web host will only allow you to add one domain name to your hosting.
Then if you want to create another Web site you will have to purchase another web hosting package.
Look for a web host that offers several or even unlimited domain names.
Disk space when you create a Web site you will add a number of files to your Web hosting servers.
A lot of web hosts these days offer unlimited disk space.
So look out for this bandwidth.
Some web hosts will limit the amount of bandwidth that you can use each month.
So look for web hosts that offer unlimited bandwidth one click installation of WordPress.
This is very important.
A lot of web hosts will have a feature where you can install the free Wordpress blogging platform on
your domain name with one click of your mouse.
You need this as you are going to use the word press blogging platform to create your Web site.
This is different to a free Web site at WordPress dot com.
We recommend host gate or dot com for your web hosting.
They have been around for years and are used to dealing with Internet marketers.
They have different packages available that offer unlimited domains one click install a wordpress on
metered or unlimited bandwidth and disk space in USA servers for around 10 dollars a month.
There are lots of other good web hosts available that can provide you with a similar deal.
Search for web host comparisons in Google to learn more.
Always go for a web host that has the one click WordPress install feature.
Once you have registered a web hosting account you will need to point your domain name to it.
There are a lot of videos on YouTube to show you how to do this and it is a lot easier than it sounds.
Install Wordpress when you purchase your web hosting account.
You will be provided with access to it using a special you are all Web site address.
Usually you gain access using a facility called C panel.
You can do a great number of things with C panel and one of the really great features is the automatic
installation of the WordPress blogging platform.
Usually there will be an icon and c panel for one click.
WordPress installations.
Click on this and then fill out the relevant details such as the name of your website and your admin
address.
If you need to supply a password then make sure this is strong and make a note of it.
Then click install and a few seconds later your website will be ready.
There are regular updates to the WordPress blogging platform and with most good hosting packages these
will automatically be installed on your website which is really convenient.
You always want to work with the very latest version of WordPress for security and other reasons.
Why do we recommend WordPress rather than other Web site platforms.
Well the main reason is that it is so easy to install and use.
You don't need any technical knowledge to install and run a wordpress Web site.
You can also customize your WordPress web site using themes and plugins.
A theme will determine the look and feel of your Web site.
There are thousands of free themes available and some premium themes too.
Once you find the theme that you want you can install it with one click and then customize it to add
your logo or change the color scheme.
A plug in is a piece of code that will enhance the features of your WordPress Web site.
For example there are good plugins for SEO such as all in one SEO which is totally free and highly recommended.
You can optimize all of your web pages using this plugin.
There are thousands of free plugins and premium ones too that will enhance your niche Web site so that
you provide a better experience for your users and maximize your chances of getting your pages and posts
ranked in the search engines.
You can find out a lot more about useful WordPress plugins by performing a Google search or looking
on YouTube dot com.
We would certainly recommend that you install a good SEO plugin and create a content form with a plugin
and check out plugins that speed up the loading of your Web site.
It is so easy to create new web pages using Wordpress.
You have the option to create a page or a post.
It is best to use pages for static pages such as about us.
Terms of conditions and other legal pages do not overlook these pages as it makes your website look
more professional and Google and the other search engines will expect to see these as well for your
general content.
You can create posts.
We always create our posts using a word processor such as Microsoft Word and then when we are happy
with them we copy and paste them into a new post.
You can easily add media to your post such as images and videos as a minimum we would recommend that
you had at least one image to break things up a continual block of text is not appealing for your visitors.
Relevant videos are always a good idea when you create a new page or post it.
It will be in draft mode.
It will only become live on the internet when you publish it.
You can make changes to any content you have published very easily.
But using the editing tools within WordPress logo and Web site header we recommend that you spend a
few dollars on having a professional logo and Web site header created for your new niche Web site.
If you are a graphic designer then you can create your own but if not then there are some good services
on offer for this on fiver dot com.
Look for designers that have a lot of positive recommendations.
Tell them the name of your website in the niche.
Also tell them the measurement for the header.
You should be able to find this in the theme details tell the designer what style design you want and
the color scheme.
If you already have installed your wordpress theme then give the designer your domain name so that they
can color match everything.
It is really worth the effort and expense to have your own unique logo and Web site.