Content for your niche Web site content really is king.
If you publish a low quality content on your Web site then you will turn your visitors away.
If you go to a poor Web site what are the chances that you will return there again.
Not a chance right.
So keep this in mind when you are creating the content for your Web site.
It is all about quality and not quantity.
We do recommend that you publish content fairly regularly to keep your visitors and the search engines
happy.
The best way to do this is to develop a content plan.
You can create a content plan based around the comprehensive keyword research that you did as the first
step to setting up your niche Web site.
When you are creating your content plan Don't worry about how you will write each piece of content.
There are a number of ways to do this as we will discuss here.
Write the content yourself.
If you are not an expert on the content you want to write.
Don't worry because you can soon become one.
Just use google and find web pages that have the information that you need.
Rewrite this information so it is unique and you have your post in terms of post length.
We would recommend that you go for at least 500 words per post.
It is a good idea to vary the amount of words that you use as this looks more natural to the search
engines long posts.
Fifteen hundred words and upwards do tend to rank better in search engines and shorter posts.
But this is not an exact science.
Think about your readers first and not the search engines.
If your readers like your content they will come back for more.
When you were writing your new posts always select some keywords to include and add these in a natural
way determine your most important keyword and add that to the title of the post.
Use the other keywords in the body of your posts.
Don't overdo it with keywords and use them too often as this can be seen as keyword stuffing by the
search engines.
Always check your new post for uniqueness use a service like copy scape that com to check this.
It is worth spending a few cents on this to ensure uniqueness.
If your post is not unique then it will be difficult to ranking in Google and the other search engines
outsource your content writing a lot of niche Web site owners don't want to write their own posts as
they feel that they are not good at writing or they just can't be bothered to spend the time to do this.
Having a good writer on board to write your posts is a good idea.
As you can spend your time on generating more traffic to your website where do you find a good writer.
Well there are many places you can find them such as gig based websites like 5 or dot com and people
per hour dot com and project Web sites such as Upward dot com freelancer dot com and guru dot com.
If you are choosing a writer for the first time then arrange a meeting via Instant Messenger with them.
Tell them what you are looking for and let them tell you about their experience and send you some samples
of their work.
There are other Web sites where you can get articles created very cheaply.
We're not going to name these Web sites here but the price charged will tell its own story.
A five dollar article is likely to be written by a person whose first language is not English.
Sometimes you can get lucky but most of the time you will have to contend with grammar errors and more.
There are reliable professional writers on websites like the Warrior Forum.
You can check their reviews before you decide one thing to note is that good writers are usually busy
and you may have to wait a few days for your content to be created.
Usually it is well worth the wait let your writer know the subject of your content and any keywords
you want included.
Also tell them what call the action you want at the end of the content.
Do you want readers to join your email list or check out a product page.
Once you find a good writer treat them well as they are pretty rare use PR content.
There are many different websites that provide private label rights.
People are content that you can purchase inexpensively and use for your website content.
We recommend that you rewrite or outsource the rewriting of any people our content and it is very likely
that a lot of people that purchase the Peel are will have just copied and pasted it.
You can purchase good peel our content on just about any niche these days.
It is possible to buy article packs that you can then rewrite and use his posts for your niche Web site.
There are also peel our packages with e-books and lead magnet reports.
You can rebrand the e-book to make it your own and sell it on your website.
Use the lead magnet to build a list even if you don't use the content of peeler packages for your website
content.
You can certainly get some good ideas from it.
Most of the good PR websites will show you a table of contents for the e-book and you can look at this
for ideas without having to purchase anything.
Google alerts.
There will be other people in your niche that are publishing new content regularly and you can find
new content by setting up a Google alert for your niche.
This is very easy to do if you have a Gmail account.
You will receive alerts in your inbox when Google discovers new content about your niche.
Just check out this new content and see if you can get some new ideas from it for your own content.