Our theme and plug in have come a long way since we first started.
It's now time to take it to the next level by working on some advanced concepts.
If you plan on selling your theme, then it would be wise to show support for some of the most popular
plugins available in this section.
We will work on adding support for Buddy Press and Will Commerce.
I want to make something clear.
By default, these plug ins are already compatible with our theme.
Most plug ins that are released to the public are compatible with WordPress.
As long as that theme and plug in are adhering to the WordPress coding standards, then they should
be compatible with each other.
What we'll be doing is furthering the compatibility by customizing the look and feel to match our theme.
This step is completely optional, but by doing this, you open yourself up to gaining more customers
and learning more about WordPress.
If you're not familiar with these plug ins, then let's take a mini tour.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide links to both plugins.
The first plugin will be working with is Buddy Press.
Buddy Press is a plugin that will convert your site into a social media site.
It adds features such as profiles, groups, activity streams, notifications and much more.
It's very easy to use and even comes with some default styles if your theme doesn't have any.
Woohoo!
Commerce is a plug in that will transform a WordPress site into a store.
This is one of the most popular plugins around.
It helps process payments, keep track of inventory and so much more.
On top of that, there are a lot of plugins that extend to commerce and and a plethora of features.
Adding support for this plug in is truly beneficial at this point of the course.
Things are about to get mixed up between both plug in and team development.
What I mean by this is that sometimes we'll be working in the theme and other times we'll be working
in the plug in.
We'll be switching often, so be prepared for that.
What you're experiencing is my workflow.
This is how I prefer to work.
Actually, this whole chorus has been showing my workflow.
Whenever I start working on a custom theme, I start with breaking down my HTML template into template
parts for WordPress, just like we did in the first section.
Once I have most of the foundation set, I start working on a custom plugin for the theme to add any
features I might like.
Eventually I'll start adding in the more advanced features and integrations like Buddy Press and Commerce.
Once it gets to that point, I find myself working in both the theme and plug in at the same time.
That's perfectly normal.
And WordPress development.
Hopefully you will find that workflow optimal for you too.
If you feel otherwise, let me know.
All right, let's get to work.
Oh.