We're almost done with Buddy Press, the last thing we want to do is learn how to make some customer
success changes.
It's simpler than you may think.
Inside the Buddy Press Default Nouveau template, you'll find a folder called CSX.
Buddy Press will look for a folder named CSX inside your theme's folder.
If it's available, then it will look for a file named Buddy Press Access and automatically load it
for you.
I'm going to copy the entire access folder and paste it into our team's folder like so.
To verify that this is working, I'm going to open the buddy press Dominique's file, I'm going to select
the Buddy Press ID and apply a random background color change.
Refresh the page after doing so, you should see the changes applied.
This shows that Buddy Press is now loading the stylesheets from our theme rather than its default stylings.
I'm going to remove the code we just added.
Now that we verified the case file was being loaded, we can now make some changes.
You're free to modify this Cyesis file any way you like.
It is as simple as that.
The only unfortunate part is that you need to name these files a certain way and they must be placed
inside a folder called success.
Other than that, everything else is customizable.
So that does it for the buddy press development.
Part of this course, there isn't much to it, honestly.
You'll end up doing one of three things you may want to modify the templates html.
You now know how to do that.
You just study the HTML or read the template hierarchy and add that file to your theme and their respective
directory.
Afterwards, you can make the changes you'd like to see.
You may want to hook into certain parts of Buddy Press.
It's as simple as looking for the do action function inside the templates and using that hook to output
some HTML.
In case you don't want to modify the template directly, the last thing you may want to do is make some
Cyesis changes.
And that's as simple as creating the Buddy Press Access file.
Before I wrap up this lecture and move on to the next thing you may be concerned about drastic changes
to Buddy Press.
Luckily, Buddy Press will always inform you about template changes.
If your theme supports Buddy Press, it's always best to keep up with the latest updates and to read
about them when they do release notes.
However, if for some reason you miss an email, you can always go to the Buddy Press theme development
documentation page.
On the sidebar, you'll find a list called Template Updates, followed by the version No.
I'm going to click on two point seven.
You'll be shown a list of changes made to their templates if you made a change to any of these templates,
then you just have to read through this and apply the changes manually.
This is the benefit of only copying the templates you use into your theme.
If you were to copy the entire directory into your theme, then you would end up having to apply every
single change documented here.
This is why I highly recommend you only override the templates you actually want to make changes.
You also, as you can see here, there is a lot of code and changes you'd have to make.
It's almost an entire night's worth of code here.
All right.
That does it for Buddy Press.
In the next couple of lectures, we're going to begin working on new commerce development.