Well, commerce is the best e-commerce WordPress plugin around it can be intimidating at first for developers,
but it's one of the easiest plug ins to work with.
Unlike other plugins, WordPress is well documented, encoded.
Unlike Buddy Press.
We can find a lot of the answers to our questions online.
If your theme supports commerce, then you would be adding a whole lot of value to your theme.
It's almost the standard today to support commerce and to come bundled with it.
If you're not familiar with commerce, then let's take a quick tour.
While Commerce allows you to convert your site into a store to sell physical and or digital products,
it has over twenty one million downloads and powers, over twenty eight percent of all stores.
You'll even find a list of partners and supporters of all commerce.
This is one of the reasons why commerce is well documented and supported.
A lot of companies and individuals rely on this software to work with so many people relying on such
a software for generating revenue.
You can imagine the amount of work needed to extend it.
This course isn't about teaching you how to use new commerce.
There are a lot of courses out there that teach you that what you'll be learning here is how to use
it in theme and plug in development.
Let's get started.
The very first step is to install and activate it, go to the admin dashboard and navigate to plug ins,
add new search for the plug in.
Will Commerce install and activate it?
This plugin is very big, so it might take some time to install it.
Currently, this plugin is on version three, which is very new and has a lot of breaking changes.
But all the code we write will be compatible with this version.
After activation, you'll be taken to a set of wizard.
I want you to go through it with all the default settings.
I didn't really bother going through the settings as I just use the defaults.
Nothing special.
After going through the wizard, newcomers will also generate some pages.
This is very important.
Just like Buddy Press will, commerce needs to generate some pages to display the content it generates
and manages for you.
So be sure to generate all the pages it needs or else this won't work for things like the payment gateway.
I'm going to use PayPal.
It doesn't really matter at this point.
You can always configure this later to your preferred payment method.
After going through the walkthrough, you can begin with preparing our theme for compatibility with
EU commerce.
You'll notice we have a couple of messages here warning us about extra steps we need to take before
we can fully use will commerce.
You may end up getting a message telling you that the current theme does not declare who commerce support.
You may even be recommending the theme.
Since we're developing our own theme, we won't take interest in the theme.
It should be noted that most themes are compatible with commerce by default.
Keep in mind that Woog Commerce is a WordPress plugin and uses the same functions and hooks as any other
plugin.
So even if we don't make any changes to our theme, world commerce will work as usual.
If we want to override some of commerce behavior, then we'll need to declare support for it.
That's simple to do.
All we have to do is call the ad team support function inside the after setup theme hook.
Let's do that now.
Open the setup file and call that function right after the other support functions.
Passan Woohoo commerce.
All this does is tell you commerce, that this thing fully supports its features and design after writing
it, we can now begin with development to make things easier.
I'm going to modify the menu to include the cart checkout and shop pages that do commerce generated.
Make sure to save the menu.
The very last thing I want to do is import some dummy data.
Luckily for us, do commerce already provides us with some dummy data we can use to test our theme with
commerce.
Go to Tool's import.
The Will Commerce plug in provides to importers one for products and one for rates.
We won't be dealing with taxes in this course.
We only need to import some products, run the new commerce product importer.
From here you can import a CSV file with your products.
You'll be asked to upload a file, go to the WEW Commerce plugin folder.
Inside you'll find a folder called Sample Data.
This will contain quite a few files, but we're only interested in the sample underscore products,
CSC file, upload this file.
After uploading it, you'll be asked to map the values.
Mapping is the process of making sure the values inside the file are correctly inputted into the correct
database columns.
If the file that's exported uses the same version as the commerce version, the file is being imported
in, then you won't have to worry about mapping.
The value should match up fine.
This is usually for product files that were exported with earlier versions of commerce.
The mapping may not correctly match with the current database design, since we're using a sample product
file from commerce.
We don't have to worry about this since it's maintained by the commerce team, they'll usually make
sure the file matches the current commerce version.
We don't just leave everything as is and continue.
This may take a while.
Just be patient.
You should see a success message and be taken to the list of products, if not, then you can click
on the products menu on the sidebar.
We now have a couple of Dommy products imported, which is nice with that finished.
Let's take a look at what we have.
Go to the front end of the site and view the shop page.
You'll see some products imported, which is what we want.
You'll notice that the page really isn't that well spaced and our footer is broken.
This is because of the success it makes the product page for width, which pushes the sidebar to the
footer.
This only happens on the shop and single product pages.
If you were to view the checkout and cart pages, you'll notice everything looks fine.
So what is going on here?
Well, let's take a look at the cart page and try editing it.
You'll notice that this is just normal page with a short code inserted that displays the cart's contents.
You can modify this page any way you like.
I'm going to make it full width and press update.
I'm going to do the same for the checkout page.
These two pages can be fully controlled like this, however, if you were to edit the shop page, you'll
notice you can't edit the page the same way as before.
There is no shortcode.
The reason for this is because the shop page generates more dynamic content than the other pages, because
of this, it needs more flexibility than a simple shortcode.
This is why we get different markup than the other pages in the next lecture.
We'll tackle this problem and make everything fit well with our theme.
Oh.