In this lecture, we're going to explore some more templates to get a better feel on how well Commerce
manages things.
Right now I'm looking at the cart page.
I've added one item to the cart.
There is one noticeable problem.
The checkout button is being spaced improperly, unlike last time.
We can't really change this through code, but it's more of a success and a female problem.
So we'll have to adjust the templates themselves.
It's rather simple.
Unlike the product page, the cart is just made up of template parts, so we don't have to worry about
every single little thing like last time.
All car related, simpler parts are placed inside the cart folder.
I'm going to copy this folder from the plug and into our theme's woohoo commis folder like so.
I'm going to delete all the files except for the proceed to checkout button template file.
This is the file that will require some modifications to come to this conclusion.
I just did the usual.
I studied the code and searched through every file until I was able to determine which files to modify.
It's pretty simple.
If you open up the template, it's just this button by itself.
I'm going to modify the class and replace it with the following values.
BTN, BTN, Dash blog, BTM Dash LGBT and Dash Primary.
This will make the button spaced out evenly.
The button won't be purple anymore, but that's fine with me.
That's it for the cart template.
Even though the cart template has so much more, it's basically repeating the same thing.
I'll talk more about that in just a moment.
Let's explore some more templates.
There's a possibility you may want to change the email templates.
Woohoo!
Commerce will send out an email whenever an action occurs, such as a password reset or a new order
has been placed.
If you were to go to the admin dashboard and navigate to woo commerce settings emails, you'll find
all the templates that are sent out.
Below, you'll see some settings, if you were to click on a certain email, you'll be taken to a page
where you can configure the settings even more.
What you can't do is modify the HTML.
If you want to modify the HTML, then you'll have to override the email templates.
You can find those inside the email folder.
Just like last time, you would simply copy and paste it from the plugin folder to your theme's folder
in the respective location.
I'm not going to do this as I'm fine with the email templates.
However, testing out email templates is a problem, especially with our development environment.
In order to view an email template, you will have to receive an email, which usually isn't possible
on a local environment.
Of course, you can set up an SMTP server, but that's beyond the scope of this course.
It's also a bit complicated.
The next best thing is to test it out on a live host, but that can cost money and it takes too long.
Luckily, someone made a very simple solution.
Go to the admin dashboard and navigate two plug ins, add new search for the plug and commerce email
test by race or web install and activate this plug in.
Before we can test this plugin, you may need to create an order, simply go to woo commerce orders,
add new and just fill in some dummy data.
I'm going to pause the video and add an order really quick once you filled in some data submitted.
Now we can test the email templates under the commerce menu, the plugin we just installed will generate
a new submenu called Email Test.
Let's check this menu item out.
You'll be taken to a very simple interface.
I'm going to select the order we just created and save it.
Then I'm going to click on the completed order button below.
Here is what one of the templates would look like if a user opens it in their inbox.
This is a great way to test your templates on a local server without the need for a life server.
I'm going to do something you should never do.
I'm going to open this template from the commerce plugin folder.
The completed order template.
Is the customer complete in order to file?
I'm going to make a simple modification.
I'm going to output the text test, you never want to modify a template inside the Woog Commerce plug
in as any changes you can make can be overridden after an update.
However, this is just for an example.
After making this change, I'm going to refresh the page.
The text should now be outputted.
I'm going to remove my changes.
So that's how you would go about making changes to the email templates in how to test them?
All right, let's move on to something else.
In some situations, you won't be able to make changes to the template themselves, even if it may seem
like it.
For example, if I were to go to my car and press checkout, I'll be taken to this form to fill out
my billing and shipping details.
A lot of the HTML here is broken.
In addition to this, you may want to have extra fields or remove some fields.
You will not be able to modify these fields through a template you'll have to use.
Hooks will tackle both problems.
First, let's fix the formatting issue we have here.
I'm going to inspect the form.
Inside this form there is one div tag with the class call to set inside this div tag.
We have two more additional tags with the classes.
Call one.
The reason the fields are getting squished together is because these two div tags have the call.
One class, the call one class is a bootstrap class that will make an element have a certain width.
If we were to look to the right, you'll see that both bootstrap and newcomer's trying to apply styling
that conflict with each other.
What do Commerce is attempting to do is make two columns that are about 50 percent in width.
Now, the question is, how do we go about attempting this?
Well, instead of letting commerce set the width, we'll let bootstrap do that will have to change the
classes used.
In order to do that, we'll need to modify the template ourselves.
We already know what classes and HTML to look for.
The next step is to find the template with the same HTML.
I've already gone ahead and found the template we'll need to make changes to open the checkout form.
Check out template.
You'll find the div tags with the call one classes and the form wrapped around it.
This is the template we want to modify.
I'm going to copy this file and paste it over to our theme, make sure it's placed inside the checkout
directory.
Now we'll just have to make a few adjustments.
First, we're going to end the row class to the div tag with the ID of customer details.
Then we're going to change the two inner div tag classes from call one to call six.
The row class I'm adding here will help bootstrap, make sure the two columns fit nicely side by side
on multiple resolutions, go ahead and refresh the page.
Everything should look nicer.
Now, the next step is to fix the stylings for the input fields.
Unfortunately, if you look at the template, you'll notice the individual fields aren't directly generated
here.
Instead, they're created dynamically through functions and hooks.
Therefore, we'll need to dive into some code to accomplish this.
There's already a plugin that does this already, but it's always good to understand how these things
work under the hood before you can fully appreciate a plugin.
First, we'll need to study the HTML to find the correct template to modify.
I've already done this for you.
The template can be found inside the checkout's form billing free file.
All the billing form fields can be found inside the div tag with the class woohoo!
Commerce billing fields, field wrapper.
Inside this element we have a loop being performed.
Let's break this down line by line.
The first line here is creating a variable called Fields'.
Its value is the value returned by the function.
Get check outfields.
This function will return all the fields required for the user to check out.
This will allow for a third party plugins to add additional fields if need be right after this.
Each field is loop through using a foreach loop.
What we want to focus on is the call to the function wou commerce forum fields.
This function is what we'll take care of generating the input field itself.
We can even check the documentation for this function.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to this function.
Here's what it says.
Outputs a checkout address form field.
A simple to understand function, but not much documentation is provided.
That's fine.
We can just inspect the code on this page.
You can click this link to where the function is located at.
Let's go there.
There's quite a bit of code going on here, but we don't need to examine much of it to understand what's
going on.
Right away you'll notice a variable called defaults is being created.
It'll contain default values for the field if they weren't created.
Three of these default settings have the key word class in them.
We can assume that these have to do with where the classes will be applied.
I've already dug into the code and can confirm they do indeed get applied as classes to elements.
The Klasky gets applied to the element that is wrapped around each input field.
The label Klasky is the class applied to the label.
The input class key is the class that gets applied to the input field itself.
These are the keys that will want to modify.
Now we have to figure out how to pass in the values.
Taking a closer look, we can see that the default array gets merged with another variable called ARGs.
ARGs is the variable that's passed into the function as the second parameter.
We just need to modify the second parameter of this function back inside the template.
The field variable is what's passed as the second argument to the function.
We'll just need to modify this variable.
Before we do that, we should copy this template over to our theme since will be making changes.
Copy this file over to our theme in the respective directory.
Next, let's modifying the Klasky and set it to an array, the value should be an array of classes.
We only need to add one class, which is form group.
The next key to set is the input class.
This will also be an array of classes.
The only class will pass in is form control.
You may be curious as to how I got these classes, these are bootstrap classes, bootstrap structures,
its form in a similar way to commerce.
You create a tag that wraps around the input field.
The element that gets wrapped around the input field needs to have the class form group apply to it.
The input field itself should have deform control class applied to it.
You can read up on the bootstrap documentation for more info on these classes.
That's all the changes will need to make.
Let's refresh the page and see what we get.
The input field should now look better than before.
So we've basically gone over the many ways to modify a template you could use either hooks or modify
the template itself by copying it over from the plug into your theme folder before in this lecture,
I want to provide one extra tip.
Sometimes you want to display products your own way.
In most cases, you'll want to add more options to the way products or sorted and filtered.
In cases like these, you'll most likely want to remove the default sorting option provided by commerce.
Go to the shop page to see what that looks like.
There are dozens of plug ins that will remove this dropdown for you, but let's do it manually.
Removing this isn't anything we haven't done before.
We already know that this page is generated using the archive product template.
I'm going to open up this template.
Inside this template, you'll eventually find a call to the do action function called Wuhu Commerce
before shop loop right above you'll find this comment for the functions while commerce calls.
We already went over how you would go about verifying all of this.
So we'll just take the comments word for it inside the functions file.
I'm going to call the remove action function and just pass in the info accordingly, using the info
from the commerce comment like so.
Refresh the page to check just like that, the sorting is gone, nothing really new here, but I just
wanted to show you this as it's something I find myself doing often.