Hello and welcome to the WordPress development course, this is one of the most comprehensive courses
on WordPress development around.
By the end of this course you'll have a solid understanding of the word press corps and its APIs.
WordPress is a very powerful CMS and currently powers over 60 million websites from around the world.
That number continues to rise every day.
The average WordPress and developer makes anywhere between fifty five to eighty five thousand dollars
a year.
There are currently about two hundred and fifty thousand jobs related to WordPress posted on various
job sites.
Right now, dozens are being added every day.
Currently, WordPress has about sixty five percent of the market share.
If you look at other platforms from Drupal to Squarespace, you'll find that the user base for each
platform is small compared to WordPress.
Squarespace, for example, only takes up about five percent of the market.
You can expect a more competitive and smaller job market since Squarespace is user base is small compared
to WordPress.
WordPress, on the other hand, it's very in demand and provides a lot of benefits.
Not only is it in demand, you'll find that the hours are flexible and you can work from anywhere in
the world.
Its popularity is due to the fact that you can create any kind of website you'd like.
You can create a simple blog out of the box, or you can create a full blown social network.
WordPress can be used to create ecommerce sites where you can sell both physical and digital products.
You could even sell services.
You can also create directories where users can find information about any subject.
You don't have to use it for big projects either.
Out of the box, you can use WordPress for smaller sites like your own personal portfolio or small business.
One of the greatest perks of developing for WordPress is that it is mostly front end agnostic.
What I mean by this is you can use any access or JavaScript framework you want.
WordPress gives you complete freedom as a result, creating responsive sites is pretty easy to pull
off.
By taking this course, you'll learn how to customize your WordPress site by creating custom plug ins
and themes.
Here's an overview of what you'll learn throughout this course.
Currently you're in Section one.
In Section one, we'll go over what WordPress is and what you need to know about the various resources
available to you will then start setting up an environment.
The Stack and WordPress itself will also dive into alternative options.
Besides, the one I go over, this section will be brief and the shortest section out of them all in
Section two will take a standard HTML template that I provide and take the first few steps to convert
it into a basic functioning WordPress theme.
The template I provide has no specific preparations made for WordPress.
This allows you to learn every step you need to take to make a template.
WordPress ready.
As you will see, WordPress will work with any template you provide.
You'll have full control over your success and HTML structure choices.
This section is broken down to be easy to understand and simple in Section three will then continue
developing the theme by creating templates.
The template system WordPress provides out of the box is simple but very flexible.
By the end of it, you'll understand how the WordPress template system works, along with getting to
know the customizer for adding custom theme options in Section four, we'll go over any templates I
may have skipped over in the previous sections.
The templates presented in this section aren't as popular as the other templates, but you may need
to know about them randomly in the future.
In Section five, we'll start talking about plugin development.
This is where we will really get the opportunity to extend the word press corps.
We'll discuss the various APIs you can use in a practical way.
Some of the topics we'll get into will be creating custom post types, authentication hooks.
Ajax requests security and work with the database.
By the end of the section, you'll have a better understanding of how WordPress works in Section six.
We're going to step away from WordPress for a moment.
As of WordPress five, Gutenberg was integrated into the core.
There are a lot of things you can do with Gutenberg, but in order to extend it, you need to know some
JavaScript concepts for those who aren't comfortable with things like the command line, know James
Webb, PIAC, react, etc..
Then this section is for you.
I talk about these things and give you a solid foundation to help you get started.
Once we've talked about those things, then in Section seven, our Introduce Gutenberg development,
I'll talk about how to set up your project and building a custom block from scratch.
We'll also talk about how to use the toolbar and how to use components provided by WordPress afterwards
in Section eight Wilkening.
Can you with Gutenberg development by talking about the other components provided by Gutenberg, things
like Rich text, the media, uploader, form comptrollers, etc., we'll cover anything that may have
been missed related to Gutenberg in Section nine, we'll explore various APIs to create things like
widgets and sugarcoats will even talk about how to authenticate and register users.
This will get us into topics such as security and nonces.
In Section 10, we'll talk about creating admin interfaces and setting up forms will manually process
those forms with various APIs.
After that, I'll show you some alternative and faster methods for performing those tasks to make you
an efficient developer.
And Section Eleven will start talking about Buddy Press and Will Commerce theme development.
I'm going to demystify some of the concepts behind these two plugins.
By the end, you'll have a better understanding on how these two plugins work and even understand how
the word press corps works.
You'll find yourself being comfortable navigating the files and extending anything you want in Section
12 will wrap things up by adding a few more features to the plugin and theme we developed will finalize
things by learning about debugging, unit testing, translations, child themes, RTL support and so
much more.
Everything you need to do before releasing your work to the public will even talk a little about licensing
in Section 13.
We'll talk about some advanced WordPress concepts.
It's a very experimental section and not really required to watch.
However, you can learn a thing or two to help with more larger projects for the first twelve sections.
This course focuses on developing one plugin and one thing.
A lot of courses out there will teach you how to build various projects so you can get practice applying
the same thing.
However, the problem with this is that a lot of the examples aren't practical.
I like to approach things differently.
Rather than give you ten different projects that have no real world usage, we build a more realistic
theme and plug it.
By doing this, the size will get pretty big.
This forces you to learn about organization and efficiency.
You'll experience my workflow and how I would tackle big projects.
Don't be afraid, though.
By the end of this course you'll have the confidence to navigate your way around the project we built.
This approach allows you to learn what you need to know as problems arise.
By taking this route, you'll learn how to apply certain concepts in a more practical situation.
You'll also develop a good workflow as you continue with this course.
WordPress comes with over ten different APIs and you'll learn how to use most of them by the end of
this course.
The great thing about WordPress is that all APIs are available to you, whether you're working on themes
or plugins.
So the things you learn while creating themes can also be applied to plugins and vice versa will take
a deeper look at this as the course progresses.
Before you even begin this course, there are a couple of requirements you need to know or have.
You will need a good understanding of HTML, VSS and JavaScript.
You'll also need to know some query.
You'll also need a local server to work on.
This can be your computer.
If you don't have one, then you'll learn how to set one up in the next couple of lectures.
You'll also need a text editor and he will do for this course.
I'll be using Visual Studio Code.
Lastly, you'll need a healthy thirst for learning.
There is a lot of content to digest, so you'll definitely be kept busy.
We will mainly focus on working with WordPress is inbuilt APIs, so we will not be covering most of
the HTML, S.O.S and JavaScript.
WordPress doesn't require you to learn any special HTML, S.O.S or JavaScript code.
As you'll learn, WordPress is extremely flexible on the front end.
I will provide you with a static HTML design that will convert into a WordPress.
If you wish, you can use your own thing, but I highly advise against it.
While you're learning, your code should be similar to mine before you decide to freestyle anything.