Before we begin coating anything, it's important to understand the various resources made available
to us by WordPress and this lecture, I'm going to break down each resource provided by WordPress.
You can follow along with me by checking out the links in the resource section on this lecture.
If we were to search for WordPress, you'll come across two sites which are WordPress, Dotcom and WordPress,
Digg, even though they have similar domain names, you should be aware that there is a huge difference
between the two.
The dot com domain is a hosting platform for WordPress that is supported by a private company.
I'll talk more about that company in just a moment.
Right off the bat, I want you to know something very important about WordPress hosting platforms.
There are a lot of them out there, but I do not recommend using these kinds of hosts as a developer,
you'll want to have full control over your WordPress sites.
A lot of WordPress hosting platforms really limit what you can install and use.
While they're user friendly, they're not developer friendly.
Sometimes you'll have a client asking what how do you recommend for their site in these instances?
Try to recommend something which gives you the developer more flexibility as this course progresses.
I'll definitely talk more about hosting options and what you should be looking for in a host.
All right, let's keep moving forward.
The dot org domain is for anyone who wants to download the source code of WordPress and host it themselves.
This is where will be spending ninety nine percent of our time throughout this course.
Right away you'll find a button to download.
WordPress, as of this course, will be working with version five of WordPress.
Download WordPress now as will be installing it on our machines in a future election.
Don't worry, if you see a higher version of WordPress, all code we write will be compatible with future
and past versions of WordPress.
Throughout this course, you'll find that features from versions as old as one point five are still
supported and used.
Let's explore this site a little more under its support.
Click documentation.
Here, you'll find information about WordPress and its features.
You'll notice that we're in something called the Codex.
That's just a fancy word WordPress uses to call its own documentation.
Back in the early days, WordPress used the codex for everything from code examples to simple explanations
about the user system.
However, as WordPress grew, the development team realized that mixing this information was not a good
idea.
So they took all the resources related to coding things and plug ins into its own site in the euro bar
changed the word codex to developer.
Remove anything after the domain extension.
Here, you'll find resources strictly related to developers throughout this course will be switching
between the Codex and developer resources.
From time to time, you'll find that the Codex resource contains code.
This is because the WordPress team hasn't fully transitioned all the code examples from the Codex to
the developer site.
It's currently a work in progress.
One of the great things about the site is that it is dynamically generated.
The WordPress team has made it so that this site will scan all the code and WordPress to help generate
the documentation.
This way, the site is always kept up to date.
Let's explore how to use this site very quickly.
Right off the bat, you'll be provided with links to four different sections, a section for developing
themes, plug ins and applications.
This last section is actually new, which provides information on how to use the WordPress SEELIE.
We'll be exploring all of these as the course progresses.
All these sections are only guides.
If you want to look up a function or class, then you need to scroll down and click the code reference
link.
You'll be taken to a search page where you can look up functions, hooks, classes and methods.
We haven't gone over hooks, so I don't expect you to know what that is.
Let's ignore that for now.
Right below this, you'll find that WordPress documents all the latest code added to the word press
corps.
This is a really great way to check out what functions are added on the right.
You'll find all the APIs available will be exploring most of these throughout the course.
Let's take a look at how to search for code.
I don't expect you to follow along.
You just need to understand that all this does is help you find more information about functions and
other WordPress code.
By the end of this course, you'll be more than comfortable using this tool.
All right, I'm going to search for something called the underscore content after submitting the search.
We should get about 10 results back.
I'm going to click on the first result.
WordPress will load this page that provides a lot of information on how you would go about using this
function.
There are a couple of things I want to highlight.
The first is that you'll always be provided with the original source code.
Here you'll find where WordPress defines this function.
This is a really great way to understand how WordPress functions internally.
A lot of this code may not make sense, but I assure you that you'll be able to read code like this
and understand what it means by the end of this course.
Next is the changelog section.
This will document when the function was first introduced and if there were ever any changes.
As you can see, this function has been around since version O, point seven one.
As I stated previously, WordPress is a popular choice because most code you write will be compatible
with earlier versions, not as early as this, but you shouldn't have any problems with a few versions
back down further.
You'll find a related uses section here.
You'll find where a function is used within WordPress itself.
This is a really great way to see how WordPress itself uses its own code.
You'll find some really great examples by reading through the WordPress code itself.
The last section is the user contributed note section.
This section is available for anyone and everyone to submit some tips and tricks on how you would go
about using this function.
Something important I should highlight is that not all pages are like this.
Some pages will provide even more information and others will provide very little.
For the most part, though, functions that are commonly used tend to be documented quite well.
I know this is a lot of resources to take in, but I promise you we will definitely be going over how
to use both of these resources to your advantage.
To reiterate, the codex is where you'll find information on WordPress and all its features.
The information presented here is user friendly.
The developer site provides information related to the code of WordPress.
A lot of this information is technical and aimed at developers.
Before I finish things off, let's explore the site.
Automatic Dotcom Automatic is a company that makes huge contributions to the WordPress software.
They own plugins such as jetpack and newcomer's.
Even though they don't own WordPress, they do have a big influence over the open source software.
Automatic owns the dotcom domain of WordPress, but they do not own WordPress itself.
It's very important to make that distinction anyway.
That's about it.
We're almost ready to begin writing some code in the next lecture.
We're going to start setting up our system for WordPress development.