Let's prepare our machines for WordPress development, if you already have things set up and prefer
your own kind of environment, then you're free to skip this lecture.
If not, then just follow along.
I'll try my best to explain everything.
The very first thing we need is a development environment.
There are various environments out there, but the one I recommend is Zamp.
It's free and constantly updated with the latest versions of software for web development to download
Zamp, you'll need to visit the site Apache Friends Dog.
I'll provide a link to this site in the resource section of this lecture.
Just a side note.
Most sites I talk about will be provided in the resource section of each lecture, so just be aware
of that.
You should see something similar to what I see.
Zamp is a program that bundles various programs together.
Let's take a deeper look at these programs.
The very first program is Apache.
The official Apache site is Apache Dog.
Apache is actually an open source software foundation that provides free programs for everyone.
One of their most popular programs is the HTTP server program.
We can find this program under projects.
You'll find a link to the server project.
This program allows you to turn your computer into a server that accepts and sends requests.
It's very lightweight and easy to use.
The next piece of software is Maria DB.
You can find more information about the software at Maria Dbag.
Maria DB is a database that allows you to store data about anything you want.
There are all kinds of databases out there, but the most popular choices are either Oracle or My School.
My school and Maria DB are the two databases WordPress is one hundred percent compatible with.
So you may be wondering why are we installing Maria DB instead of my school?
Well, there's a lot of business politics that I won't dive too much into because it's really boring.
But here's the overall gist of it.
My school has seen very little development in recent years.
A lot of developers have decided to fork my school and continue developing and under a new name, which
is Maria de Borking, is just a fancy term for downloading open source code and then adding on to it.
Essentially, Maria De is my school, but with more features and is constantly updated.
So most code that you write for my school will also be compatible with Maria DB and vice versa.
I promise that all code we write will be compatible with both Maria DB and my school.
The last piece of software is that you can find the official Web site at p dot net p p is the programming
language WordPress is built with.
I assume you already know about p p, so I won't be talking about it.
You'll notice that Perl is also bundled, but we won't be using Perl at all, so you don't have to worry
about that.
The X and Zamp stands for operating system, implying that Zamp is cross compatible with all operating
systems.
All these programs combined together will create an environment you can run on your computer.
This environment will allow you to install and work with WordPress locally.
There are other environments out there, but I highly recommend you use Zamp.
I find Zamp the easiest to work with out of all the environments available.
There are better options out there, but those tend to be overkill.
In the next lecture, I'll talk about other options and why we won't be using them for now.
Just keep following along with me.
Let's download and install Zamp.
There are various versions of Zamp, but I prefer the one that comes bundled with p p seven point two.
People ask me all the time what version of p p they should be using and I always recommend BB seven
or higher p p seven is fast and allows for faster processing times, which is great for development.
Let me show you something really quick.
Go to the WordPress Dawg site and I want you to click the about link.
On the side you'll find a page called Requirements.
WordPress will recommend you work with B seven.
If you read a little further, then you'll find that the absolute minimum version you need to run WordPress
is five point two point for a lot of hosts will still use five point two or five point three.
But I'm going to recommend that you don't develop for these versions of P.
It may seem like you're limiting the amount of clients you'll work with, but you save yourself a huge
headache by avoiding these versions.
The reason being is that these versions are no longer supported by P.
These versions have security vulnerabilities and exploitations.
Personally, I only developed plug ins and things that are compatible with P p seven Nannup.
A lot of developers such as Muffin Group and Theme Fusion don't even support these lower versions and
yet they still receive a lot of clients.
In the end.
It's a.
You all code we write will be compatible with IP Version seven and up, in case you were curious, you
can also check out this interesting link called Statistics.
This page shows information about the setup most hosts use and what versions of each software they're
using.
This should give you a good idea about what the market is like.
All right, let's move on, download and install Zamp.
Just go through the default settings as they usually will suit you best.
I won't be going through the installation as I've already installed one installed.
You can open up the control panel by searching for something called Zamp Control Panel.
The great thing about using Zamp is that it automatically bundles and configures most of the software
you need to run a local development environment.
It's fast and easy.
You'll notice that Zamp installs other programs such as File, Zillah, Mercury and Tomcat.
We won't be using this software, so you don't need to worry about what these do and what they're for.
To boot the server, you need to turn on Apache and MySQL.
You should see the modules highlighted in green indicating that these modules have successfully been
turned on and are currently running.
If you don't, then be sure to read the log below and ask for support at the Apache Friends site.
We can test to see if everything is working.
By clicking the admin button inside the Apache row, you'll be taken to localhost.
You may see a welcome message.
I don't because I deleted those files.
I'll show you where to delete those files in just a moment.
Let's set up the database first, open the control panel once again and click the admin button in the
MySQL wrote.
You'll be taken to a page called My Admin.
Personally, I don't like my admin because it is a web script almost like WordPress.
My admin is a way to manage and view your database inside your browser, just like any other script.
This script will load JavaScript Cyesis and handle all requests with me.
It works, but it tends to be very slow at times because you have to wait for the page to load to know
whether or not your request was successful.
I prefer to use something called Heidi Skill, which can be found at high school dotcom.
You can go to the download section and just download the appropriate download for your operating system.
Heidi doesn't work well for Mac Systems.
So here's an alternative solution.
If you're on a Mac OS system, then you should check out Sequel Pro.
It's fast and free.
You should be able to connect to any MySQL and Maria DB databases without any problem.
Once you have those installed, open it up like so.
Heidi Eskil is similar to my admin, except it is written in a language called Object Pascal, which
is a bit faster than a B and can execute MySQL queries so much faster.
This program also comes with more features which will be useful in later lectures.
It'll take some time to get used to this, but I promise it'll be worth it.
Using Heidi Eskil is pretty simple.
First, you need to create a new session.
Name it whatever you want.
I'll be naming mine localhost.
A lot of the default settings are pretty good.
The host should be one two seven zero zero one, which is the IP of localhost.
The username is root and the password will be left empty.
This user is automatically created for you.
When you install Zamp, everything else is fine.
Make sure to save and then click open.
You'll notice that I already have a few databases set up.
Let's create a new database.
You simply right click in the left column and under Create Click database you'll be presented with two
options.
The name of the database and the colation the name will be using is You To Me and the Colation will
be UTSA.
And before General SII, the colation determines how characters are sorted and compare.
For example, you can have the letter A as upper case or lower case which gets displayed first.
What about characters where there's an accent above the letter A?
As you can see, there are dozens of correlations with their own set of rules on how to compare characters.
For this course we'll be using UTF eight and before General SII because it's been tested to be highly
performance and accurate.
It works with all characters, including Chinese, Japanese and so much more.
Click OK, and that's it.
You can click on your database in the left hand column and you'll notice that it's empty.
We can now install WordPress in the previous lecture.
You should have downloaded WordPress.
If you haven't, then do so now.
The file you downloaded should be in the form of a zip file.
Have not file in hand.
Next, open the Zamp control panel from the control panel.
Click on the Explorer button.
This is where Zamp is installed all files.
That are served from the server to your browser is located in the Docs folder, he docks, stands for
hypertext documents, this folder is very important as we will be working inside it throughout most
of this course.
Feel free to delete any default files inside this folder.
You don't need them.
I already have some files here as I use them daily for web development.
Open your zip file and drag and drop the files from the zip file into this folder.
I'm going to rename this from WordPress to you to me.
We can now visit this by opening up the browser and navigating to localhost, argued Amy.
Upon arriving on the page, you'll be asked to begin installing WordPress.
Let's do this together.
You'll be asked to select your language.
Are we using English?
Select whatever language suits you best.
Afterwards, you'll be told that the WP config file isn't available.
WordPress will then ask you if you'd like to create this file now.
I'm going to let WordPress generate this file before it can do so, it's going to ask us for the database
details.
Let's go through it one by one.
The database name is Udemy and their user name is Root, there is no password and will leave the rest
as is the last field is table prefix.
The table prefix allows you to give your database tables a unique name.
Whatever you input here will be prefixed to all the tables WordPress generates.
WordPress will generate a little over 10 different tables for your site.
The names it generates tend to be very simple and basic.
This can cause issues.
If you already have tables inside your database to avoid naming conflicts, you can set a prefix to
give each table a unique name.
For example, there is a table named posts.
If you set the prefix to WP underscore, then the new name will be WPE underscore posts.
You should always be mindful of the setting as will be using in ourselves in the future.
For now, I'm going to leave this assets.
If you don't understand, that's fine.
You'll understand what I mean in a future lecture.
Run the installation.
After some time, you should see a success message, you'll be then asked to input some basic details
about your site and set up a user account input, whatever details you want.
You can just copy what I put, if you like.
Once you're finished, you should see a success message and you can now log in.
Congrats, we've successfully installed WordPress, we're pretty much done, there's one last thing
I want you to do before you finish things up here.
Go ahead and log into your WordPress site, then go to Settings Permalink, change the permalink settings
to Postnet.
This will make our new URLs easy to read.
It's not necessary, but it will make your life simpler.
We're now finished.
That was a lot to go through, but hopefully you got through it.
Oh.