Before we get started, I want to go over some these concepts that you should be aware of.
I want to make it clear that this isn't a BASIX course.
I expect you to know and some of the fundamental concepts, such as variables and functions.
With that being said, there are some techniques and concepts that you will see me use throughout this
course.
I just want to make sure we're all on the same page right now.
I'm on a site called Right Online.
I'll provide a link to this and the resource section of this lecture, I promise that will only be using
this tool for this lecture only.
So the first thing I want to go over is the final constant.
I'm going to echo out this constant and run the code.
This constant will always contain the full system path to the file it's being used in, it's very important
that you understand what the value returns when you use it.
Each page we file, you create will automatically define this content for you.
You also don't have to worry about conflicts between each file throughout.
This course will be working inside multiple directories when you're working inside multiple directories.
It can be rather difficult to determine where you are.
The file constant will help us greatly.
The next concept I want to go over is ARray's.
I'm going to create an array named Ah and it will contain the values one through five.
Arrays aren't anything special and aren't hard to understand, what I want to highlight is the way I'm
writing arrays.
I don't use the key word array.
Instead, I just use square brackets.
This is the shorthand way of writing arrays.
I know some people like to use the array keyword, but I won't be doing so just to speed things up.
If you prefer to use the array keyword, then that's perfectly fine.
I do want to give a warning.
Not all hosts support the shorthand version of writing appearance, so use these with caution.
If you plan on supporting older versions of the next thing I want to go over or anonymous functions,
I'm going to type one up quickly.
An anonymous function is exactly what it sounds like, it's a function that does not have a name since
it does not have a name, you have no way to reference it.
The reason you would use anonymous functions is to write less code if you write less code than your
code becomes more readable.
I'm going to delete my example and paste in a more practical one.
There's quite a bit going on here, so let me break down what's going on and creating a new array called
Array Double, this will be assigned to the value returned by the function array map.
The array map function will taken an array and call a function that will be passed in the value to manipulate
the function past.
It must return either to value a modified version of the value or add a completely different value.
And this example, I'm showing two ways of passing in a function in the first example and passing in
an anonymous function.
In the second example, I'm creating a named function and passing in the name to the array map function.
Both solutions are completely valid and acceptable.
After both of these, all I'm doing is printing the array.
Let's run the code and see what we get.
As expected, we get to arrays that are identical.
Both methods work and one isn't better than the other.
You're more than free to use either one.
Throughout this course, we'll be using a combination of both.
The last concept you should be aware of is object oriented programming, also known as OP.
OP is a pretty complex topic and I couldn't possibly cover it in this single lecture.
Instead, I'm going to refer you to a tutorial series which is completely free in this series.
A lot of things related to object oriented programming is covered.
We actually won't be writing a lot of opis throughout this course.
So you're OK with just knowing the bare minimum.
If you're already comfortable with OLP, then you can just skip on a head.
That's pretty much it.
I just wanted to highlight those concepts to you.
There's one last thing I want to show you.
In the resource section of this lecture, I provided a link to the WordPress Best Practices page.
WordPress provides a guideline for writing code.
If you plan on contributing to the word press corps, then these guidelines are important.
However, if you just plan on making your own plugins and themes, then you can follow any coding style
you like.
I'm going to click on the AP Coding Standards Link.
Basically, this page goes over how you should write your code from indentation to formatting blocks
of code.
You are absolutely not required to follow these standards.
With that being said, let's give this page three and go over these standards together.
The first thing that goes over is when to use single quotes or double quotes.
From word perspective, it generally doesn't matter.
The most important thing is that you escape your data when combining HTML and dynamic data together.
Up next is indentation.
There's a whole debate whether you should use tabs or spaces, but WordPress recommends you use real
tabs and not spaces.
Something that's also worth noting down is that WordPress prefers you align your code for readability.
And this example, you can see that the equals sign is perfectly aligned no matter how long the variable
name gets afterwards.
You're told you should always use braces when writing blocks of code.
Even if you're a block of code is only one line inside, you should still use braces.
This applies to loops, conditional statements, functions, classes and anything else you can think
of that uses braces.
When it comes to using conditional statements, you may end up using an elusive statement.
You can write this one of two ways.
You can write the else.
If with a space or without a space, WordPress recommends no spaces.
I'm going to skip regular expressions as we won't be using them that much throughout this course.
Down a little further, you'll see that you should use the long hand version of opening and closing
tax.
You should never use the shorthand version because it's not supported on most hosts.
On top of that, you'll see that you should take the time to format your code as opposed to having an
unreadable mess.
In this example.
After this, you'll see that WordPress recommends you space everything inside functions and loops.
Neatly omitting the spaces can really make it hard to read your code, especially if you're dealing
with variables versus hard coding.
Things aren't moving right along.
You'll then be told that you should take the time to format your skill queries.
They don't provide a good example here, but you'll see soon enough how to format your queries for readability.
Right after this, you'll be told about making queries directly to the database.
Throughout most of this course, we'll be using functions that will take care of querying the database
and sanitizing the data.
However, these functions will not cover all scenarios and these cases.
I'll show you how to properly query the database and make sure it's safe for execution.
Up next, it's telling us about naming conventions.
Whenever you create variables, classes or functions, it's recommended you use underscores if your
code contains multiple words.
If you're someone who uses Camil case, then you may want to.
Consider switching, there's also rules for how you should name your files if there are multiple words
and you should use hyphens to separate those words, I'm going to skip these next two as they're more
WordPress specific topics, which we'll cover soon enough.
Now we're at ternary operators, ternary operator or a shorthand way of writing conditional statements
for setting values.
They're really handy and it can even be readable if used.
Right.
Just make sure you space everything right and then it makes sense when you read it.
You'll see plenty of examples of ternary operators throughout this course.
Then we run into yota conditions.
It's a strange name, but this simply states that when writing conditional statements with variables,
you should place the variables on the right side.
And this example, it's read like this, if true, the force then victorious you will be.
I am not really a fan of this, but you can use it if it makes sense to you.
Lastly, it's telling us that you should choose readability over clever code.
What this means is that you shouldn't write your code just for the sake of writing less code while being
clever with your code does mean writing less.
It can also be harder to read for anyone else that will want to get into your code.
There's more here, but we can safely ignore this.
You can read them if you want.
Now, I do want to say that these standards are only recommendations.
You won't receive errors or warnings from writing your code differently.
The point of these standards is so that there's consistency across the board.
At the end of the day, it's up to you.
I myself follow some of these.
You'll notice that throughout this course I like to organize and format my code.
You're more than free to follow along with my coding style, even though it does take some time to get
used to.
I believe it is worth it.
It makes my code more readable and approachable.
All right, that's it.
Let's move on to developing a theme.