I want to get into talking about plug ins, but before we get to that, let's go over to temple attacks
again.
In the past two sections, we've been using template tag to display content.
They're pretty straightforward.
You simply call a function and data gets out, put it, the purpose of a template tag is to make your
code cleaner rather than querying the database and processing the data you can just call a simple function.
This is ideal because it allows you to put logic into its own file.
You even have the ability to create your own template tags, just create a regular page function and
then call it in your templates.
You can use the functions file to define your custom template tags.
Since that file gets loaded before your template does, let's break down template tags even further.
In most cases, you'll find that template tags come in one of two versions.
There's the get version and the non get version.
This doesn't apply to every tag, but it is common.
The non get version will echo out the value immediately.
The get version will return the value.
In the past, we've used both versions for various reasons.
Usually you want to use the non get version unless you need to process the data further.
Another thing you should be aware of is that most template tags have parameters to modify the value.
And this example I'm using the title function.
If we wanted to apply some div tag to the title, then there are two ways to go about it.
We can surround the function with the HTML or we can pass it into the function as parameters.
These two solutions will result in the same thing.
The main difference is whether you'll allow WordPress to handle it.
There is one advantage to passing in the HTML, though.
WordPress has a feature called Filter Hooks, which allow you to modify values.
Template tags contain hooks which can then be used by developers like you and me.
By being provided the HTML, we can make changes to it if we wish.
For the most part, though, most developers tend not to pass in the parameters and hard html.
Instead, when we start working on plugins, you'll understand how you can use these parameters and
extend them on your own.
For this section, we're going to need a template that we can experiment to create a new template called
experimental.
You can name this whatever you want, since this will be a custom template, this template will be pretty
straightforward.
Open the full dash with dash page template and copy the code from that template into our new one.
We're going to be making big changes to this template.
First, we're going to remove the loop completely.
Then up in the page title, remove the subtitle and change the main title to experimental code.
Lastly, let's update the template name to experimental.
Once you've made those changes, I want you to navigate to the WordPress dashboard and create a brand
new page.
You can name this page, whatever you want.
It doesn't matter.
What does matter is that you select the experimental template in the dropdown and save your changes.
Now that we're finished with that, we can begin exploring template tags.