Currently, I'm on the list of template tags available on WordPress, all template tags are stored in
nine files and those list of files can be found here.
You basically find them inside the WP dash includes directory.
We're going to work our way down this list to start things off.
We'll explore the general tags.
As you may expect, general tags are tags that don't necessarily fit in any other category that are
more general purpose.
And so you'll find a lot of functions for various scenarios.
The kind of functions you can expect to find are includes login functions, blog info, archive calendar.
The first set of tanks are include tags.
These are functions that take care of loading a template file inside another template file.
We've actually explored every single one of these functions in the past two sections.
So you already know what to expect out of these.
Before we move forward, I want to highlight that the comments template function isn't listed here,
despite being a general tag in the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to this function.
If you were to scroll down to the source section, you'll see that the function is defined inside the
comment template file.
Just be aware that some tags aren't defined in the same files as the other tags, despite it not being
defined in those files.
This is a template tag.
The next set of template tags are log-in tags, we haven't gone over authentication in this course,
but we will soon.
This is just a general overview.
The first function is the WP log in out function that will output a link to the login or long out pages.
Depending on if the user is authenticated.
The next two functions will provide the URL to the log and or log out you or else.
This is just in case you don't want to use the function above and have more control over your links.
Then we have the login form function which will just output a simple login form followed by the lost
password you URL and register functions which will output links to those pages.
Lastly, we have the is user logged in function which will return true or false if the user is logged
in.
Let's play around with some of these tanks right now, I'm inside the experimental template, inside
the content area, I'm going to echo out the value returned by the function WP login URL.
Let's go to our browser and refresh the page.
As expected, we get the URL to the login page, something worth noting is that this function doesn't
check if we're logged in or not.
Right now I'm logged in, so I shouldn't be able to view this URL if we want to let WordPress handle
this and we can go back to the editor and change the function to WP login out.
This function doesn't need to be echoed out so we can remove the echo statement, save your changes
and refresh the page, this function will take care of outputting the link while also surrounding it
with HTML tags.
A lot of this is very straightforward stuff.
The next function is the blog info function, this function will return information about your site.
There are two versions which are the blog info and get blog info functions.
Something worth highlighting is that you can only retrieve one value.
The value return depends on what you passed into the function.
Here are some examples of what you can pass into the function.
You can pass him the same values to both functions.
The only difference is that the log info function will echo out the value and the get blog info function
will return the value.
Right now, I'm on the documentation page for the blog info function, if you scroll down to the possible
value section, then you'll find all the values you can get from this function.
As you can see, we can grab information such as the name, your URL, character set, etc..
There is one thing I want to highlight about this function.
If you scroll up, you'll find the changelog section.
This function was introduced in WordPress version zero point seven one.
It's been around for quite some time.
When it was first introduced, there weren't a lot of ways to get certain values from the database.
However, five major versions later, WordPress has introduced a plethora of functions.
Scrolling back down, you'll see that WordPress recommends alternative functions to grab certain values.
For example, the URL description states.
The following displays the site address set in settings general.
This data is retrieved from the home record in the WP.
Underscore Options Table.
Consider echoing home your URL function and set.
There is no right or wrong answer here.
It really boils down to preference.
Whenever you use the log info function, always check the documentation for alternative solutions.
The next set of tags are archived tags, archive tags are specifically for archive templates like categories,
tags and taxonomies.
Apart from that, they can also be used outside of the loop, which can save you code in space.
Despite their appearance, archive templates are one of the most complicated pieces of pages WordPress
has.
This is because you can archive a post by category, date, tag, taxonomy, etc. There's just so much
information attached to a post because of this archive.
Tags are just as weird and complex.
I'm back inside the experimental template, I'm going to comment about any code we have here, then
I'm going to call the function single post title.
As you would expect, this will output the title of the current post, on top of that, you'll notice
we're not inside a loop.
Let's refresh the page and see what we get.
The title of the post now appears here.
That's great.
I won't be able to show you all the archive template tags, but I do want to show you one thing.
I'm going to open the category template for a moment.
Inside the page title section, you'll find that we're using the template tags, the archive title and
the archive description.
WordPress provides another function for displaying the category title, which is single cat title.
Once you have that set, go back to your browser and view a category page.
A small change has occurred, the text category does not appear before the name of the category, other
than that everything else is the same.
So at this point, you may be thinking, what's the point?
What makes one function better than the other?
Well, let's peek at the documentation for a second and the resource section.
On this lecture, I provide a link to the the archive title function.
If you scroll down to the source code section, then you'll see that this function calls the get the
archive title function.
Before we check out this function, I want you to take note of the changelog section, which says this
was introduced in version four point one of WordPress.
This is important to note and you'll see why in a moment.
Scrolling down further, you'll find a section called Related Uses, which provides information about
the functions used by this function.
I'm going to click on the link for the get the archive title function this time.
If you look at the source code, you'll see that there is way more going on.
This function will check if the current page is a category tag and date archive.
Taking a closer look, the single cat title function is called When the page is a category archive.
That's very strange, but let's keep going down the rabbit hole to understand what's going on.
Scrolling down to the related uses section, there should be a link for this function.
Click on it.
Two things worth noting on this page.
First up is the function.
If you call this function, then you'll see that it's just passing off the data onto another function
called single term title.
That's strange because that's also a template tag listed on the general template text file.
Anyway, let's go to the related uses section once more and click the link to this function.
Now, this is the function that actually takes care of grabbing the data we want.
WordPress goes through a lot of hurdles just to display a simple title, and that's what I want to highlight.
On one hand, archives are very broad and therefore they're complex.
A lot of checks have to be performed in order to grab the correct piece of information.
On the other hand.
This also shows that WordPress is not as organized as one may think.
WordPress receives criticism for gluing code together.
That's partially true.
The reason we have the archive title function is because developers still had to add this logic to their
templates.
This made the code look sloppy and unorganized.
That's why the archive title function was introduced recently, despite all these functions being around
for a while.
Luckily, the team behind WordPress is working really hard to clean things up.
It's starting to become clear which functions should be used.
This is why we use the archive title function.
It's because it takes care of checking for everything rather than us doing all the work.
That was a lot to dig through, but hopefully you understand what's going on behind the scenes.
If you were to go back to the list of template tags and clicked on the single tag title function, you'll
see that this function does the exact same thing as single cat title.
In my opinion, it's better to use the archive title function so you don't have to memorize various
functions.
I'm going to go back to my category template and reverse the changes.
The next set of template tags are the calendar tags, calendar tags aren't used much, so I won't be
diving too much into them.
The most commonly used template tag is the get calendar function, which will output a calendar in a
table format.
Lastly, we have these other tags which don't necessarily belong to a specific category.
None of these are worth going over, but you're more than free to check them out.
And the documentation, strangely enough, the WP and Q script function is also listed as a template
tag.
You already know what this function does.
So no need to recap on this.
All right.
That does it for the general tags.
I highly recommend you explore these tags once you finish the course.