When it comes to navigation tags, there's not much to go over.
If you look at the list of functions, you'll see that there are only two functions.
We've already gone over the first function and the second one is not that important.
There is one thing I didn't mention, though.
Let's go ahead and click on the WP now.
Menu function on the sidebar, you'll find a link to the section menu item CSS classes.
Upon clicking this link, you'll be provided a list of classes that WordPress will apply to the navigation
menu generated.
If you're creating your own walker, then these classes won't be applied.
You'll have to apply them manually.
WordPress also doesn't load any styles for these classes.
It's up to you to take advantage of them in your theme.
Currently, the theme we have isn't using any of these classes.
That's perfectly fine.
We don't need them anyway.
That's all I wanted to show you.
Let's move on to the next set of tanks.