The next set of tanks, we'll talk about our link tanks, these are tanks that return or output links
to different pages of your site.
You can use these functions to generate links to a specific post or the home page.
Here's a list of functions that take care of generating those girls.
A lot of these are pretty straightforward, so I won't be talking about most of them.
I just want to focus our attention on the get search link and the search query functions.
Right now, I'm inside my editor and I have the search template opened up, I'm going to scroll down
to the search box section and add my code here.
So one of the more interesting functions is the get search link function, as its name suggests.
This will return a zero to the search page.
I'm going to echo this function at.
This function has an optional parameter which will add a search term to the Eurail I'm going to pass
in the text hello immediately right after this.
I'm going to echo a break tag and call the function the search query.
That should do it.
Let's switch to the browser and try searching for something after a quick search, the search template
will load in our results.
Let's shift our focus to the text outputted above the search box.
Two things are output.
It first is the euro generated by the get search link function.
You'll notice that the euro generated is different than the euro up in the address bar.
There are two ways to load the search template.
You can add the first query to the URL or you can access the search page, followed by the phrase like
Here I'm going to copy this URL and paste it into the address bar.
We should see the search template load again.
You'll also notice the value from the search query function also changes the value in the euro.
Is the value outputted from this function?
I'm going to comment out the code we added in the template.
That's basically it when it comes to think tanks, they output you URLs and they're mostly straightforward.
I only showed the search functions because I wanted to demonstrate the various ways to access the search
template.
I also wanted you to understand why WordPress generated that URL.