The next step is to register and interview the assets, this will most likely be the last time you write
code for a while.
Unlike the other WordPress APIs, Gutenberg is mostly written in JavaScript.
Custom blocks are also written in JavaScript.
There are some exceptions, but we'll get to those later.
Registering and in the files are still a process, just like anything else will be.
Using hooks inside the main plug and file create an action hook called in queue block ed assets.
The name of the function will be R and Q block ed assets.
This function doesn't exist, so we'll need to create that next, create a file inside the Blocks Directorate
called Incudes up once again.
Any files related to the Gutenberg editor will be placed here after creating the file, define the function
and include it from the main plug and file.
The hook that we're using is specifically for the Gutenberg editor, the NQ Block editor assets hook
is triggered when the Gutenberg it's initialized for any post type on the admin end.
This is perfect as this will make sure only files meant for the editor will be loaded inside the function
called the WP Register a script function and set the name to our blocks bundle.
The second parameter will be the Eurail will use the plugins Eurail function for this, the path should
be slash blocks, slash dist slash bundle.
Keep in mind that we're loading the bundle file and not the files inside the after actory, the bundle
file will contain the finished result of everything.
Next up is an array of dependencies before we load this script.
We're going to need a few things.
The special thing about The Gutenberg editor is that it's modular.
The Gutenberg editor is split up into various modules that are bundled together to make it function
correctly.
We need to make sure that certain modules are loaded first before our script so that it can function
The scripts we're about to require are all registered by WordPress.
The first one is WP Dashi 18 in.
This script will provide us functions that we can use to translate our script.
Next is the WP Dash Element script.
This will provide us with the function for converting our Xcode into JavaScript functions in the previous
section, we would use react, but WordPress takes the time to Wrap's and love reacts functions.
I'll discuss this more in depth later.
For now, just include it afterwards.
We'll need the WP Dash Block's script.
This script will allow us to register our block and interact with Gutenberg, then we'll need the WP
dash components scripts.
Gutenberg comes with some components that we can reuse in our own script.
This script will allow us to access these features.
It's great because then we won't have to reinvent the wheel.
Up next is the WP Dash editor script.
This script comes with tools and functions related specifically for the editor.
These will help us create a more consistent user experience when building our blocks.
Lastly, we'll need the WP Dash API script.
This will allow us to interact with the WordPress rest API.
We haven't discussed the rest API in depth, but we will soon.
Something I want to note is that you won't be using all of these scripts right from the start, will
gradually introduce each one as the course progresses.
I'm just including them now so that we can focus more on the JavaScript code and not have to switch
back and forth between files.
The last parameter I want to set is the version.
As you may know, some browsers will cache our files.
We don't want this.
We always want the latest version.
I've already shown you how to do this in a previous lecture, but I want to show an alternative solution.
I'm going to call the file some time function.
This function requires the path to the file.
I'll pass that in as well.
The function I'm introducing here will get a philes last modification time, this function requires
the full system path.
I'm using the plug in dirt path function, which will return the full system path to a plug and file.
Then I'm appending the rest of the path to the file.
This is a really quick and easy way to get the latest version of a file.
All right, let's include the file now right below this called the WP NQ Script Function and pass in
the name.
That should do it before we confirm everything works, open the index JS file inside the App Directorate.
It should be empty.
I'm going to console log a simple message.
Then we'll need to compile this file inside the command line, you may have to seed into the blocks
directory once you're there, run the commands npm run Dev.
You should receive a success message and Web PAC should now be watching the files for any changes,
then go to the admin dashboard and try viewing the Gutenberg Ed.
This can be for any post type for the rest of this section.
I'll be focusing on the recipe post type.
The code should work for any post type, though.
Open the developer tools and review the console.
You should see the message appearing in the log that should confirm everything works.
We've taken care of the first two steps, which was prepare the environment and include the files.
The next step is to register our block.
We'll take a look at how to do that in the next lecture.
I'll see you there.