We're going to begin creating the UI for our block WordPress provides two different places for your
UI, which are both important right now.
The setting that displays our content is the same function right above it.
I'm going to create an arrow function called EDIT.
These two functions will display our content, but in different locations, the edit function will display
the content on the Gutenberg editor, the same function will display the content on the front end.
You can consider this the final result.
The edit function is where you'll be placing the UI for editing the block.
This includes buttons or input fields.
You can also use this function to add content on the sidebar.
Basically, anything related to the editor should be placed here, just like the same function you're
required to return ASX.
I'm going to copy the return statement from the same function and paste it into the edit function.
This is only temporary.
Soon enough, you'll be able to see the difference between these two functions before we get into coding
the content for our block, let's accept in the prompts object.
Both functions except in the props object, so be sure you're accepting that in in the previous section
we went over react and the props object as a refresher.
The props object contains the properties and attributes passed down to your component.
The great thing about Gutenberg is that most of the technical details are taken care of for us.
We don't have to worry about the code that makes Gutenberg function.
A general high level overview will suffice.
Gutenberg is a react application.
Most react applications are structured as components.
When we went over components, we only made one component.
However, you can have as many as you like in an application.
The way most developers go about it is by building one component and that component will load in more
components.
The component at the top level is considered the parent component.
Any components loaded below it are child components.
The data for the whole application is usually stored at the parent component level.
The parent component will then pass down the data to the children components.
Children components can then pass that data down to their children components.
There's no limit to how far data can be passed down.
Let's say that the data was updated in a child component.
The parent component will not be automatically notified about the update.
Instead, it's the job of the child component.
To tell the parent component about the data change.
You have to do this manually, but it's not hard at all, as you'll see soon enough.
Now, you may be thinking what if the data that's used on level two is also used on level one?
Well, once the parents component is updated, it'll send the data back down through all its child components.
This process repeats until all components are up to date with the latest changes.
This way, you don't have to send the data to all components.
You just have to send it to the parent component and everything else will follow suit.
The props object will contain the data for our block.
Not only does it contain the data, but it contains functions that you can use to send the data back
to the parent component.
Let's check out the value of this object.
I'm going to console log the props object.
Then inside the command line CD into the blocks directory and run the NPM run deve command afterwards.
You shouldn't receive any errors at this point once the file has been compiled, let's create a new
recipe post.
Be sure you have the developer tools open before you input anything.
I'm going to add my own recipe block.
All right, the block should be displaying without a problem, if you look at the log, you'll see an
object being outputted.
This is the props object.
If you look inside, you'll find things like attributes and the class name.
There is one property I want you to pay attention to.
The IS selected property is used to determine whether the user is focused on the block or not.
If they are, then the block tab will be in.
Focus on the sidebar.
I'm going to click outside of my block, which will make the editor lose focus of the Block immediately
after clicking away.
A new object is logged.
If you look inside, it's mostly the same.
However, the IS selected property is now set to force after it was set to false, everything in the
application changed as well.
The block tab on the sidebar is no longer focused.
The great thing about Gutenberg is that a lot of this is taken care of for you.
The WordPress development team have already taken care of the difficult parts.
This allows us to focus more on our blog.
Now that we understand what the props object is, let's begin creating the content.
We'll be learning more about the props object throughout this course, inside the edit function.
I'm going to remove the logging of the props object.
I'm also going to remove the code for the return statement and said, I'm going to add a pair of parentheses.
If you're writing one line of code, then you can commit these.
But if you want to have multiline JSM, then you're required to add these in.
As a reminder, the block we're going to create will display more information about a recipe.
This includes things like ingredients, cooking time, etc..
To start things off, I'm going to create a div tag with the attribute class name.
Well, remember that we're writing JavaScript code.
The key word class is taken, so jousts uses the class name attribute to assign an element access class.
The value for this will be a pair of curly brackets.
This is how you inject JavaScript code inside OSX.
We're going to make this value dynamic.
If the value for an attribute is dynamic, then you don't have to worry about wrapping this in quotes.
It will be done for you.
Once it's processed.
The value will be prompts class name.
The class name property will automatically be generated for your block, you will see the value for
this once we're finished.
I've already gone ahead and prepared the GML for this block inside the assets folder.
You'll find a folder called Extra's Open the recipe dash block, dash templates, copy everything and
pasted into the div tag.
There's nothing super special going on here.
We have an unknown wordlist with the class list Unstyled applied to it.
Something I want to know is that the list Unstyled class is only available within our theme styles.
We haven't include any styles for the Gutenberg.
Ed, I want you to keep this in mind as what we see on the Gutenberg editor will be slightly different
than what we'll see on the front end.
In reality, you will always want both styles to look the same.
This way the user won't get surprised when they view their post.
Usually what they see on the admin is what they expect to see on the front end.
Inside this list, we have a general overview of the recipe inside the strong tangs.
I'm going to wrap the text with the double underscore function.
I want you to do the same.
This text will never change, so we'll want to make it translatable.
We also have this text with uppercase letters that end with each page is short for Placeholder, will
be replacing this with dynamic values.
But for now, we'll leave this as is save your changes.
Web should be able to process the changes without any error.
Let's view what we have so far.
I want you to create a new recipe post.
Make sure your developer tools are opened.
I'm going to give my post a title and add the recipe block.
You shouldn't receive any errors related to our block, the block should output the unordered list with
our text translated.
I want you to publish this post.
Before we preview this, I want you to check out something, I'm going to inspect this element in my
developer tools.
You'll see our block is being displayed the same way we've written it.
One thing I want you to focus on is the class apply to the div tag for this tag.
We've used the class name property from the props object.
WordPress will provide you with a class for the block generated.
You're free to use your own classes, but it's better to use the one provided for consistency reasons.
All class names start with WP Dash, Block, Dash.
It's followed up with the name of the block.
In our case, this would be Udemy dash recipe.
The forward slash in the name was converted into a dash.
All right, let's view what we get on the front end.
What will be rendered on the front end is the hello world message, this is to be expected, as I stated
previously, the edit function is for content that gets rendered on the ED.
The same function is for content that gets rendered on the front end.
As the final result, providing the edit function is optional.
If you don't have an edit function available, then WordPress will just use the same function for both
sides.
Let's inspect the element for this.
Will see the paragraph tag being outputted with the class apply.
This is a pleasant surprise.
WordPress has taken the time to apply the class even though we didn't apply it in our code.
You don't have to apply the class name properly as WordPress will do it for you.
This only applies to the same function.
The edit function will not have the class applied to it automatically.
There's a reason for this, but we'll cover that soon enough.
For now.
Just know that if you want to use the class on the editor, then you'll need to apply it manually while
the front end will have it apply to automatically.
All right.
That should do it for now.
In the next lecture, we'll take a look at how to allow the user to modify these values.
Oh.