The next step to building our block is to create the inspector controls what our inspector controls.
The inspector controls are the settings that appear on the sidebar.
Let's select the recipe block for a moment.
If you look at the sidebar, you'll see the custom class field.
All fields that appear here are inspector controls.
Let's see how WordPress uses this.
I'm going to add the paragraph block.
The paragraph block is simple, but if you look at the sidebar, then you'll see that it's very flexible.
We can change the size of the text, the background color and even change the alignment.
It's a very clean and simple design.
We can create our own custom controls or use the ones that come bundled by default for our recipe block.
We won't eat anything super complex, but we will go over how to use these components later in the course.
Let's get started back inside the scripts we're going to need to load in a component at the very top
destruct.
The Inspector controls property from the WP editor object.
This is a component, just like any other component, we can use its name back inside the edit function,
we'll want to return this component.
That may seem strange, but just keep following along and it'll make sense soon enough.
Here's the problem, though.
We are already returning some code.
We need to be able to return the inspector controls component.
Luckily, there's a way to return multiple components.
Instead of just returning the block, we're going to return an array.
This is a little trick with react, as I mentioned previously, you can't have multiple root elements.
This will cause react to give you errors.
However, you can return array of six components, allowing you to have multiple root elements right
before our block.
I'm going to use the inspector controls component.
I'm going to input the text hello in between these two tanks.
You'll notice that I'm not wrapping this around with a pair of parentheses, if we're returning an array
of components, then we can admit the parentheses.
I'm going to remove the parentheses from our block.
I'll break this down in a moment.
But let's see if this works.
CD into the blocks directory and run the NPM run dev command.
Next, go to the recipe post we created previously, you should see everything working normally.
If you look inside the console, then you should see no errors.
I'm going to select the recipe block we have here.
It should work without any errors.
If you look inside the inspector controls, you'll see the hello message.
We input it.
Let's break down what's going on back inside the scripts, we're returning an array of components.
This will tell WordPress that you have multiple components for it to use.
It will scan the array and look for a component named inspector controls.
If it finds this component than anything inside, it will be rendered on the sidebar.
Anything else will be rendered as the block on the content portion itself.
With that said, you don't have to arrange this in any particular order.
You can put the block itself as the first item in the array.
Whatever you prefer.
In order to use the inspector controls, you have to grab it from the WP or enter object like we're
doing above.
WordPress provides this component for you out of the box.
It will take care of placing your content in the correct area and we'll make sure it only displays if
the user selects your block.
Right now, if we look at our UI, it's not really appealing.
If you look below the title and icon, you'll see that the CIA says class field is under the advanced
box.
This is what's called a panel.
Panels are talkable, making them great for organization.
WordPress allows us to create our own panels easily.
Let's look at how that's done.
I want you to open the Gutenberg handbook.
You should have bookmarked it earlier on the sidebar.
Click on the components link.
WordPress states the following about this section.
This package is includes a library of generic WordPress components to be used for creating common UI
elements shared between screens and features of the WordPress dashboard.
The components found here can be used to create our own UI.
Under this section, you'll find loads of components we can use in our plugin.
One important thing I want to know is that some of the components here are not exclusive to the Gutenberg
editor.
A lot of these are generic components that can be used outside of Gutenberg if you wish.
Components that are placed inside the components section are general components, these components can
be used anywhere in the Gutenberg, what they can be inside the sidebar or in the top bar.
This isn't completely confirmed, but there's a possibility that the whole WordPress admin dashboard
will be converted into a react app.
To prepare for that, WordPress has gone ahead and prepared some generic components like the ones you'll
find in this section.
If you scroll down just a little further, click on the panel component.
This page will go over on how to use the panel components, feel free to read up on it.
To learn more about panels.
Let's begin using the components listed here to use a component from the components section.
We'll have to access them from the WP components object just like last time.
I want to d structure the WP components object to make our code readable.
I'm going to grab two things, which are the panel body and panel RO components.
The panel bonding component will take care of creating the Tokugawa panel you see in the sidebar, the
panel RO component will take care of spacing the content within the body of the panel.
This component is optional, but the spacing will help with organization and readability.
Now that we're importing these components, let's go back down to the inspector controls component and
add these in like cell.
The panel body component has an attribute called title, which we can use to assign a title to the panel.
I'm going to set this to basics and make it translatable as well.
Save your changes and refresh the page, if you select the recipe block, then you'll see the panel
appear.
It should have the title basics.
You can even toggle this panel.
This is great.
We did very little to make this work.
Now that we have a panel, let's add the input field so that the user can manipulate the block back
inside the editor.
I'm going to change the text inside the panel row and add a paragraph tag.
The text inside will be configure the contents of the block here.
It will also be translatable.
Below the panel row component, we're going to add our tech fields, you may be wondering why aren't
we going to add the fields inside the Panero component?
Well, to better explain why.
First, we have to understand how farm fields work in Gutenberg.
There are two ways to create form fields.
We can create them manually, like we would for any typical HTML form.
Alternatively, we can let WordPress create the fields.
There's no wrong answer here.
However, one way is easier than the other.
It may not look like it, but WordPress handles a lot for us behind the scenes.
To better understand this, let's look at one of the fields we'll be using.
Go back to the handbook and under the components section, click the text control component.
One of the components we'll be using is called text control, the text control component is pretty straightforward.
You just added in and define a few properties.
Let's dive even deeper.
I want you to open the GitHub repository just like last time.
You'll be able to find the component section inside the package directory.
All components can be found inside the source directory.
Let's quickly open the text control directory.
Most components start at the end next door file, you may see more files and other components, but
that's usually the case for more complex things inside this file.
There are quite a few things going on, but I want our main focus to be on the input field.
As you can see, all WordPress is doing is creating a regular input element.
This may not seem like much, but all of this here provides a better user experience.
Let's use this component to see what exactly is generated back inside the editor.
We're going to need to grab the text control component.
Since this is inside the components folder, it's safe to assume it's inside the WP components object.
If you're not sure where something is, then feel free to along the WP object or read the documentation
inside structuring of the WP components object.
Grab the text control component.
Inside the inspector control component, we're going to add the text control component.
There are a couple of required attributes.
The first is the label attribute, set this to ingredients and make it translatable.
Then we're going to set the help attribute this is optional, but if you have it, then WordPress will
and text below the field with additional instructions on how to use this field.
The value for this will be, example, tomatoes, lettuce, olive oil, etc..
Up next is the value attribute, this will be the value of the field, this should be dynamic.
But we're going to make it static for now.
We haven't talked about attributes yet, so we're going to set this to test.
Lastly, we have the on change attribute, you may be used to listening for events in JavaScript, but
this is already JavaScript.
So if that's the case, then Java Sex provides a way to listen for events by using attributes.
Most events start with the word on, followed by the name of the event.
In this case, it would be when the input field is updated.
If it is, then the value inside will be triggered.
Ninety nine percent of the time you'll want to run a function.
I'm going to pass an arrow function that will accept in a value.
The value will be referred to as new value, then I'm going to console log the value.
The new value variable will be whatever the user input it, I know what may not make complete sense,
but react gives us the opportunity to work with the new value before we save it.
We won't be saving it in this lecture.
We just want to log it to see if it works.
Save your changes and refresh the Gutenberg editor.
Everything should be working fine.
Make sure your console is opened.
Select the recipe block.
You should see the input field appear before we go over what's generated.
Let's see if the on change function is working.
Input anything you like.
You should see the value appear inside the console.
All right, now that we've confirmed that the function is working, let's see what's generated.
I want you to inspect the input field.
First things first.
The panel RO component we use created this div tag with the class component panel room.
If you look inside this, you'll see the paragraph tag we created earlier.
Right below this.
We should have the input field created by using the text control component.
WordPress generated some extra HTML.
The input itself will be inside the div tag with the class component based control.
All these elements and classes bring structure to our input.
If you look at the input field, you'll see that it matches in design as well.
We could have created this ourselves, but why do that when WordPress takes care of it?
For us, this makes our code look cleaner and easier to manage.
Another thing worth mentioning is the accessibility.
The Gutenberg project has put emphasis on accessibility.
If you look at the input field, you'll find an attribute called Ariah.
These attributes help people with disabilities use your component.
Accessibility is something that shouldn't be overlooked in a future lecture.
I go over accessibility a little more in depth, but for now we'll let WordPress handle it.
Hopefully I convinced you to use the components WordPress provides rather than creating this on your
own.
Let's go back to the editor and create fields for the other options.
I'm going to copy and paste this to more times.
I'll update each one for the cooking time and utensils.
Pause the video so you can have what I have.
We're going to need two more fields for the cooking experience and meal type options rather than using
an input field.
We're going to use a dropdown field.
Let's go back to the handbook.
The name of the component will be using this time is called Select Control.
Here is what WordPress has to say, select control component is used to generate select input.
Fields, just by reading that, we know that this is indeed the component we want to use.
Just to double check.
Let's view the next James file in the GitHub repository.
You can find this inside the packages components source slash select control directory.
If you look inside the code, you'll find the element generated is a select element with the options
inside.
All right, let's begin back inside the scripts we need to restructure the select control component
from the WP components object.
Then under the input text fields, use the select control component.
The label will be cooking experience, and the help attribute will be how skilled should the reader
be?
Both will be translatable.
Next is the value attribute, just like last time, will make this static.
I'm going to set it to beginner.
Next, we have the options attribute, this will be set to an array of all the values.
Each value should be an object.
Each object will need two properties called value and label.
I'm going to set both to beginner.
I'm going to add two more objects with the values intermediate and expert.
This array will be used to generate the options for the select field.
The value will be used for the value attribute and the label should be human readable text.
The very last attribute will need to set is the on change attribute.
Once again, this will be an arrow function where we'll long the new value.
I'm now going to do the same for the meal type option, this time the values for the options will be
breakfast, lunch and dinner.
Pause the video if you need to have what I have, save your changes and refresh the page one last time.
If you select the recipe block, then you'll find the select fields appear.
These will not work, but that's to be expected.
If you were to change the value, then you'll see that the value is long.
However, the value inside the dropdown does not change.
This is because the value is static will be making this dynamic in a future lecture.
If you have what I have, then congrats.
We're finished.
We went through a lot just to get this far, but it was well worth it.
We have a consistent and clean you want.
Feel free to explore the options and values documented in the documentation.
Check out the code, change the values, create more fields.
Better yet, check out the other components.
We'll be going over the other components, but feed into your curiosity and explore the other components
before continuing.
Once you're ready, I'll see you in the next lecture.
Oh.