Welcome to another sidebar in this sidebar, I want to take the time to talk about the rest and spread
operators.
These are two new features in Essex.
You'll see them used often in Gothenburg.
We're going to step away from our project for a moment to focus solely on these concepts.
I'm in a different directorate with a file called Index J.S. In the resource section of this lecture,
I provide a zip file with this code, download it and unzip the contents.
The index file is pretty straightforward.
I'm creating a function called ADD where it will console log.
Any numbers passed in the ad function doesn't accept in any parameters.
Instead, it'll use the arguments object.
The arguments object will contain all the values passed in, including the ones that weren't specified
in the parameters.
We're using this by looping through all the values passed in and adding them all together.
This makes our function flexible.
If you look below, we can choose not to provide any parameters or up to three.
It's limitless.
The first call should result in zero, the second call should result in one and the last call should
result in six.
Let's test this out inside your command line code into the directory and run the command node index.
As expected, we get the numbers zero one and six outputted, we can clean this function up even further.
At first glance, the arguments object can be used like an array.
However, that's not completely the case.
I'm going to remove a lot of this code except for the console statement.
Then I'll paste in some code really quickly.
All right, this time I'm using the reduced function to loop through the array of values this will accept
in an anonymous function, what we passed in the values that are being looped through the purpose of
this function is to loop through all the values and then return one single value.
The function has two parameters.
The first is the total.
The second is the current number in the iteration.
In this example, we're simply adding no to the total.
After every number has been loop through, the total will be returned.
Let's try this out.
Input the command node index.
This time will receive an error, we get this error because the reduced function doesn't exist, the
reduced function is only available for a raise.
The arguments value we have here is not a true Arae.
We can access the values like a raise, but a lot of the functions that come with the raise are unavailable.
It's not the end of the world because there are different ways to loop through values.
But it would be nice if we could use the array functions.
This is where the rest operator comes into play.
What is the rest operator?
The rest operator allows you to create a variable that will be an array inside your function.
Inside the functions parameters create a parameter called numbers.
We want this variable to maintain all the values a user passes on to the function.
To do that, we'll need to add three dots right before the variable name like.
So now we can replace the arguments.
Key word with the numbers.
Variable like some.
This function will work, but there is one change we'll have to make below.
We can't call this function with no values like we're doing here.
We'll have to remove this first call as it will throw an error once you have it removed.
Go ahead and run the node index command.
You should see the numbers appear like before, this is great, our function is now cleaner and easier
to read.
Now, let's say you wanted to have some fixed parameters while also allowing this to be limitless.
That's totally possible.
Inside the parameters, I'm going to create a parameter called message.
When using the rest operator, it must be the last one in the set of parameters, all your fixed parameters
must come first.
In this example, I'm saying that the first value passed in should be set to message while all other
values will be for the numbers parameters.
I'm going to log the message variable before the numbers.
We're going to need to update our first call again this time I'm going to pass in.
Hello.
What do you think the result will be?
Take a moment to think about this.
All right, let's see.
Input the command node index.
What we'll end up seeing is, hello, one one five four, the first call it used Helo as the message
and one as the number two at the second call used one as the message and added two and three together.
So that's the rest operator and allows you to create a parameter in your function that will take in
an unlimited number of values in your function and assign it as an array.
Let's look at the Sprent operator now.
I'm going to comment about this code we have as we no longer need it.
Next, I'm going to paste in some code just to save some time.
All right, all I'm doing here is creating to erase in the first rate, I have two numbers, which are
two and three.
The second array contains the numbers, one, four and five.
I want to put the numbers in array one into Array two.
This way will only have to deal with one array.
You may come across these situations where you'll want to merge arrays together.
Traditionally, you would loop through the array and then push the values into the array with the sprint
operator.
You no longer have to do that.
Inside the second array, I'm adding the first array with the spread operator.
Just like last time.
I'm using three dots.
The spread operator merges two arrays together.
The array that has the spread operator applied to it will be the one that gets merged into the other
array.
In this example, Array one is merged with array to array.
Two will be the array with all the values combined.
Let's see if this is true inside the command line.
Run the command node index.
Both arrays are logged, Array one contains the numbers two and three, array two contains the numbers
it originally had while also containing the numbers two and three.
The great thing about the spread operator is that you can specify where you want to place your numbers.
You could place the numbers in the beginning, end or anywhere in between.
At this point, you may be thinking, aren't the spread and rest operators the same thing?
Well, they're definitely written the same, but they're completely different.
If you use the three dots inside a function's parameter, then it's called a rest operator.
The rest operator will combine all values together into an array.
The sprint operator does the opposite, which is spread the values out.
Any time you use the three dots outside of a function's parameters, it will be considered the spread
operator.
Now that we understand that, the next question is how does this apply to our code?
Well, let's look at Gutenberg code for a moment.
I want you to go into the text control component directory for a moment.
Open the index file.
There are two places where the rest and spread operators are used inside the parameter of the function.
You'll see the prompts variable uses a rest operator.
The prompts variable will contain all the attributes that are passed onto the component that aren't
already defined.
This would basically be any custom attributes we set.
We are allowed to do that.
We're not forced into just using the attributes this component uses.
If we want to add any extra attributes, then we can.
Then if you look inside the input element, you'll see that the spread operator is used to spread all
the attributes.
This is how WordPress handles custom attributes.
Let's try this one out.
If you have two positive videos, you can switch back to the main project.
Right now, I'm looking at the first text control component, which is used for our ingredients, I'm
going to add an attribute called FUX set to hello.
I'll add another attribute called Hello Set to Fu.
Lastly, CD into the blocks directory and run the NPM Run Dev Command.
If we did everything right, then we should be able to see these two attributes appear inside our input
field, go ahead and refresh the recipe post.
Select the recipe block and inspect the ingredients input field.
Just like that, our custom attributes are appearing without a problem, they don't really do anything,
but it's nice to know we can add them if we ever need to.
I'm going to undo these changes as they aren't practical components in Gothenburg.
Our flexible most components allow you to create custom attributes if you ever need that kind of power,
just to be sure.
I encourage you to check out the code yourself.
You'll see a formatted in the same way I showed you.
Don't ever be afraid to mess around with your code either.
It's how you'll learn and become comfortable with the tools provided.