We're going to load in some styles for our block.
I'm going to go over two approaches for this.
The first approach is the simplest one.
All you have to do is open the blocks in queue file and then in queue the styles file.
It would just be a regular access file.
You don't have to use any special tools or libraries to create the case file.
With that being said, I prefer another solution.
I tend to tackle a lot of large projects, so I usually have a set up that's a bit more complex than
the simple access file.
I like to use something called SAS or SES, SAS is a CSI says preprocessor, what does a preprocessor
basically you write SAS code that will then be converted into access code.
SAS is not supported by browsers, so the code needs to be processed beforehand.
SAS code is written just like access.
You input a selector and then modify its properties.
SAS adds features like variables, conditional statements, loops, vendor prefixes, etc..
CSC files can grow to be thousands of lines of code.
With SAS managing your success becomes easier.
You can split your code into separate files.
Let's say you had a variable that contained the color blue.
If you had multiple files that use that variable and you wanted to update the color, then you only
need to modify the variables, value and everything else will update accordingly.
If you look around, you'll find that some people refer to it as success.
Success is the newer version and the one will be using the SAS version is the older one, but it's still
used.
So you may come across this version as well.
These terms can be interchangeable, but know the difference.
For our purposes, it's a bit excessive.
However, if you're working on an ambitious or large project, then it would be beneficial to use it.
I won't be able to go every feature of SAS, but that's perfectly fine, SAS is written just like success.
If you know success, then you'll be able to pick up on it quickly.
If you already know SAS, then you'll learn how to add it to your workflow.
Let's begin.
First, we need to install and configure a couple of modules, all provide links in the resource section
of this lecture.
Be sure to check them out.
The first module will need is the raw loader module.
As you may know, the import statement allows us to import modules.
However, we're limited to importing just JavaScript files.
Let's say I wanted to import a case file like so this would give us an error by adding this module will
be able to load in any file.
This includes text, HTML and even access files.
Once this module is loaded, a line like this will work just fine.
The next module will need is the node SAS module.
SAS is written with the programming language C, however, we want to be able to use it with JavaScript.
This module will take care of allowing us to do so.
Afterwards, we'll need the SAS loader module.
Westpac and SAS are two different things.
The SAS loader module will take care of bridging these two together so that Westpac can process the
files.
Up next, we'll need the mini cyesis extract plug in module when we load says it will be a part of the
JavaScript code base.
However, we don't want that.
We want to put this access into its own file.
This module allows you to extract text from your files.
For example, if your file had the text hello, then you could extract that and put it into its own
file.
The way we'll use it is to extract access and place the CSA into its own file.
Lastly, we have the access loader module.
This module will take care of properly loading Cyesis files just in case the raw lunar module can't
quite a few modules, but they aren't hard to configure.
Once you've configured them, then you can forget about them and work on your project to get started.
We'll need to install these modules, switch to your command line and seed into the blocks directory.
Run the following command npm i raw loader, no Desh, SAS, SAS, Dasch Loader, CSX, that's loader
many dash says extract, plug, dash, dash, save, dash dev.
You're more than free to install multiple modules, you just chain them one after the other.
This may take a while for some of you, so be patient.
After the modules have been installed, check the package file, it should contain the dependencies
and their versions.
The next step is to configure these modules, open the web config file we created earlier right at the
top load.
The minister says extract plug in module.
Next, we need to create new instances of the planet.
I'm going to add a comment below that says, Extract access for Gutenberg Ed.
Create a constant named Ed success, plug in, this will be set to a new instance of excess extract
module.
The plugin requires that you pass in the path to a file that will contain the final result.
This will be relative to the path specified inside the output property first passed in an object inside
this object define a property called filename set to the value of blocks.
Dasch name Darzi Essense.
Next, we need to tell the plug in to use the loaders, loaders are responsible for connecting third
party modules to Web pack.
We have two, which are the access loader and SAS loader modules.
Just to save some time, I'm going to paste in the code.
The code I added was an object to the rules array.
Basically, I'm saying that if a file ends with the extension success, then it should be processed
by SAS and put into its own file.
The use property is set to an array.
This is how you specify multiple loaders.
For one rule.
I'm telling it to process SAS code through the SAS loader, followed by the excess loader and lastly,
the meniscus extract loader.
It's important that the excess extract loader is last because we only want to extract the excess after
it's been processed.
This will simply tell Westpac how to use the plugin.
We netz need to tell Westpac to use the plug in itself right under the module property.
Add another property called plug ins that will be set to an array.
Pass him the editors access plugin instant's.
All right, that should cover things, run the command npm, run deve.
Hopefully you won't receive any airs if you did everything right, if you look inside the dist folder,
then you may or may not see the case files.
This is because there's no iest being loaded.
Let's add some success to our blocks.
Open the recipe block directory, create a case file called Ed Dot success.
Just as a side note, Westpac won't give you any errors if you don't create these files, so don't feel
pressured to do so.
Let's focus on the ED file just to save some time.
I'm going to paste in this case for this.
Pause the video if you need to have when I have, I've provided two methods here for the blocks to assess
these, to do the exact same thing, but they're written differently.
The first approach is plain success.
The second approach is SAS.
It's written similarly to plain success.
However, there's one huge difference here.
Rather than constantly typing out WP Block Udemy recipe, we only write it once.
And then next, any related styles.
This SAS code will be converted into the code above.
The second approach is much more organized and less redundant.
You can nest as far as you want to.
Let's test to see if this works.
Open the index file for our block right at the top.
Import the SAS file.
We're not going to store the values, we just want to import it so that when people pick up on the file
to process and extract it, if you save the file, then Webapp should begin scanning these files, go
to your distribution folder and look for access files.
There should be one access file.
Open it.
You should see something similar to what I see.
If we were to compare the plane access and access code, then you'll notice that they're completely
identical.
Excessed took the time to correctly create the selections for our code even though it was nested.
It's a bit redundant to have both versions in our code.
So I'm going to comment about the plane success version.
After making those changes, if you look at the case file again, then you'll see that the code was
removed from the file completely.
That's fantastic.
The last step to all of this is to just include the files.
We're going to be using a different hook to include the files.
Gutenberg introduces two new hooks to include files we're already using, one of them inside the main
plug in the file.
We're using the NQ Block Ed assets hook.
This hook is triggered when the user reviews the ED on the admin side.
The second hook is called a Q block assets.
I'll add this in.
The name of the function will be are in Q block assets, this hook is triggered when the editor is loaded
or a page on the front end is viewed.
We essentially want our styles to be loaded in both scenarios.
This is the perfect hook to use for loading stylesheets inside the NQ file from the block's directory.
All define the function here.
Next call the WP register style function, passing a name and a path to the final.
Next, call the WP and Q style function and pass in the name.
That's it.
It's as simple as that, save your changes and refresh the editor, the file should load without a problem.
The Block no longer has the dots next to each list item and the spacing is more condensed.
This is now closer to the front end version.
That pretty much does it for now.
This example is a bit excessive for our needs, but if you're working on larger projects than SAS can
be a lifesaver in terms of management.
This is how I tackle projects and how I recommend you go about this.
We've barely scratched the surface of SAS.
This course really isn't about SAS, but I highly recommend you check out the SAS courses on Udemy.
It's super simple to learn, but very powerful and effective for any project.
I've got a challenge for you.
The font that's used for the ED is different than the one used on the theme.
The font that's being used is called Lato.
I want you to try and load this font for Gutenberg, then update the S.O.S to use this font.
It shouldn't be too hard.
I'll provide a link to the font in the resource section of this lecture.
Once you've tackled the challenge, I'll see you in the next lecture.
Good luck.