Here's what I want to do now, I want to add some profile tabs so other users can view any recipes a
user has submitted, this will take some time to do so.
Bear with me here in the resource section of this lecture, I provide a link to the BP core new NAV
item function.
This function will add a tab to the profile page.
This function can be found by going to documentation developer resources.
This page gives more of a technical overview for Buddy Press.
You'll find a list of functions on the sidebar, one of them being the function I just showed you.
Unfortunately, this example usage doesn't really explain everything to get started using it.
Don't worry, though, I'll explain the extra steps you need to take in order to use this function,
open the function, smile and use an action hook called BP.
Set up NAV.
This hook isn't documented by Buddy Press on their site, but this is the hook you need to use to begin
setting up navigation items on the profile page, the function I want to call will be named Jiyu Buddy
Press Profile Tabs.
As you may know, I like to stay organized.
I'm going to create a folder inside the includes folder called Buddy Press.
This folder will include all functions and code related to extending and modifying Buddy Press inside
this folder.
I'm going to create a file named Profile Dash Tabs, but I'm going to define the function here.
Lastly, I'm going to include it from the functions file.
Inside this function, we're going to need the global BP variable, this global variable is defined
and provided to you by buddy press.
The function we're about to call needs this variable so that it can function correctly.
Next, let's call the function BP core, new NAV item.
It has one parameter, which is an array of settings, the first setting is the name which will set
to recipe's.
This will appear as the tab name, make sure it's translatable as well.
The next setting is the slug, which is what will be appended to the member, you are out.
You'll see what this looks like in a minute.
I'm going to set it to recipe's.
The next setting is the position I'm going to set this to 100.
This will determine the spot, it appears in the menu, the lower the number, the chances are it'll
appear first inside the menu.
I want this to appear last.
So I'm setting this to a high number.
The next setting is the screen function.
You can pass in the name of the function that will take care of displaying the content to the user when
this page is loaded.
I'm going to set this to Jiyu recent recipes tab.
Up next is the show for displayed user setting.
This option will determine if the menu and page will appear, if the page belongs to the current logged
in user, if a user is logged in and they're viewing someone else's profile.
Should they be able to view this page or is it just for the page owner's eyes?
I'm going to set this to true.
This will mean everyone will be able to see this page.
The next setting is the item seaside setting, which is just the ID attribute you can use to style this
menu item.
I'm going to set this to J you user recipes.
The very last setting is the default sub now slug that will set to recipe's.
This is for the submenu navigation, there are usually two navigation menus for profiles, if you were
to look at the profile page, you'll see this main menu.
And under it is another menu, which is relative to the active main menu item.
If I were to change the item in the primary menu, you'll notice the sub navigation changes accordingly.
You'll also notice our recipes menu item up here and now I don't plan on having a sub navigation menu,
so I've decided to set the sub menu to the same name as the primary menu.
Buddy Press will be able to determine that there's no need for a sub menu and that it doesn't have to
worry about it.
Before we move forward with displaying the content, I want to perform one check before we run this
bit of code.
The content I want to display will only display submitted recipe posts by the user.
However, there is a chance that the admin will not even have this plugin installed or activated.
If that's the case, I don't want to display this menu item.
There are three solutions we can use.
The first solution is to use the function exists function like we've always done.
However, I want to take it a step further and check if the plugin is activated.
The second solution would be to move all the buddy press code into the recipe plug in itself.
While this might seem like a great solution and completely acceptable by Buddy Press, it does cause
a problem with having the recipe plug and be usable with any theme.
Keep in mind that plug ins should be compatible with most things by default.
I only want this functionality to be available with my Udemy theme and nothing else.
That's why we're doing all this in the theme itself.
The third solution would be to check if the plugin is activated.
This is very simple to do.
This is the solution will be using.
First, I'm going to create a new file inside the includes folder called Utility.
This file will contain all our utility functions, utility functions are just normal page functions
that really can't do anything by themselves but make it easier to process data, make sure to include
this file from the main functions file.
Before we define a function, I want to make sure if it's been defined beforehand, I'm going to check
if a function called Jiyu plug in activated check exists.
If it doesn't will define it ourselves, this function will accept the plug in filename, which will
be required to use this function.
Inside this function, we need to require the file.
WP dash admin includes plug in PHP.
The function I want to use is not loaded on every page.
We'll need to include it ourselves just in case.
Then I'm going to return the value returned by the ears, plug an active function.
Will pass him the plug and file name.
This is a WordPress function that will check if the plug and we passed in is activated and installed.
You can think of the function we just made as a sugar function because it's just a shorthand way of
writing these two lines of code into one line.
It's also common practice to check if certain utility functions have already been defined.
I've been in situations where I've developed multiple plug ins for the same site.
This has resulted in me reusing functions.
Checking if a function has already been defined is a good way to prevent collisions with your own code.
With the function defined, let's use it inside the profile taps file.
Let's use a conditional statement and call the utility function we just created.
The plug in filename is the file path relative to the plug ins directory, in our case it would be recipe
and then the main plug and file, which is the index top file.
If this function returns false, we're going to simply return the function, preventing it from executing
the rest of this code.
Now that we've got that established, we can begin to display the actual content.
I'm going to create a brand new file.
Inside the includes a buddy press directory called Profile Dash Postop BHP.
Define the screen function we passed into the town function, which should be Jiyu recent recipes tab
LASLEY include this file from the functions file.
Inside this function, we have to do three things we are allowed to just start outputting content,
but that's not really the correct way to do things.
But press is a plug in that is easily extendable.
If you looked through any of the templates, you'll notice there were a lot of due action and apply
filters function spread throughout the code.
This means that Buddy Press even allows other developers to extend it like we're doing right now.
Creating TAB pages is no different.
We should allow developers to extend this tab page just like any other body press page.
Luckily, it's pretty easy to do.
I want to call the function BP core load template.
This function will load a core template from Buddy Press with Fall-back support, the template that's
loaded depends on the string you pass in.
Before I pass in a string, I want to filter it.
We have to use the apply filters function the filter hook.
I want to call SBP core template plug in.
This is a buddy press hug that other developers can use to modify the path of a template, specifically,
this will modify the path to the plugin template.
The plugin template is a very special template in Buddy Press.
Its purpose is specifically for plugins plug ins, get a template to load their content.
The path to this template is members single slash plugins.
Let's take a look at this template inside the buddy press plug in.
Let's open this template file.
Here is what Buddy Press says about this plug in inside this blog, comic third party plug ins should
use this template to easily add template support to their plug ins for the members component.
This is the template that will load our plug ins content.
I'm fine with the way it is, so I'm going to leave this template as is now.
The question is, how do we load our content inside this template?
Well, if you scroll down this template, you'll find two calls to the BP nouveaux member hook function.
We won't go down the rabbit hole for this function because there's quite a bit going on with it.
I'll just explain what they do.
You pass in a value and it'll prepend the text BP underscore, template, underscore, then it'll call
the do action function and trigger a hook for you to use.
The first example will trigger the BP template title hook and the second example will trigger the BP
template content hook.
You can use these hooks to load your content.
It's important to understand that this template is meant for plugins other than Buddy Press.
Buddy Press does not use this page for its own pages.
Because of this, we're expected to use these hooks ourselves to load our content.
Normally we would open the functions, file and hook into these two hooks, but these two hooks are
available on those templates.
This is a problem as we could potentially divide or display information that we don't want to.
We only want our code to apply to the recipe page.
Luckily, we don't have to use the add action function in just the functions file back inside the tab
function.
I'm going to call the add action function twice for both hooks.
I'm going to pass in the two hooks and call the functions Jiyu Buddy Press recent post title and Jiyu
Buddy Press post content respectively.
Since the screen function will only run if the tab has clicked and loaded, we can safely assume these
two hooks will only be added and called at this point to this code will be placed right before we load
the template.
Since the template is the one calling these two hooks right below this code, I'm going to define both
functions.
The title function will just have a div tag with the class text center.
My text will be my recipe's.
The content function will have a list of the recipes the user has submitted, the first thing I want
to do is grab the ID of the current profile, create a variable called profile user ID and assign its
value returned by the function.
BP displayed user ID, which will grab the ID of the current user profile.
I'm going to make a conditional statement to make sure this I.D. is not empty, if it is empty.
We'll simply return the function and not display anything at all.
Now that we have an I.D., I'm going to create a new variable named Post, which will be a custom query.
There are only three things I want to set.
The first is the author, which will be set to the user ID.
We only want to grab posts based on the profile being viewed, then I want to set the posts per page
setting to 10.
I only want the ten most recent posts, since this is a custom post type.
We have to set the post type two recipe so that it'll only grou recipe posts.
Then, just like any other loop, I'm going to begin the process of looping through all of this.
Nothing new so far.
I only want to output the excerpt.
Luckily, we don't have to rewrite the code for that.
If you can recall, we already have a template for excerpts.
I'm going to call the git template part function and pass in Parshall's Post content dash excerpt,
which will use the template part we use in the index template.
Lastly, I'm just going to reset the data using the WP reset post data function.
Let's check out the recipe tab now, everything is coming out great except that the images are a bit
too big.
We really don't need all this space.
I'm going to adjust my tent a little bit.
I'm going to wrap my loop with two sets of div tags.
I'll apply the ID post to the first div with the classes row, justify content and center.
The second div tag will how the class is COLB MDH.
The classes I'm currently applying are bootstrap classes, I recommend you check out the bootstrap documentation
to learn more about these classes.
All they do is center the content for us, refresh the page and you should see everything looking a
bit better.
The classes I just used are bootstrap classes and are not specific to WordPress or Buddy Press in any
way.
Let me go over what happened.
The first thing we did was tell Buddy Press about a new menu item we'd like to add.
If a user clicks on this menu item, then the screen function will be called the screen function does
a few things.
What we want to do is display our content.
There are a couple of ways to go about this.
We could, if we wanted to, just output HTML directly from the function, that's perfectly fine.
However, it's always good practice to make the page matched the site and allow other plugins to extend
the page if they need to buddy press provide a template for plugins to use so that plug ins don't have
to worry about a lot of the markup or calling any required functions.
A special thing about this template is that there are action hooks called at certain points to allow
developers to display content.
That's exactly what we do here.
We use those action hooks specifically.
We hook into the title and content action hooks.
The functions that are called will output a title and the content respectively.
It's a lot of work, but well worth the effort that should do it for now.
Let's continue on to the next lecture.
Oh.